<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
     xmlns:pitt="https://github.com/ebeshero/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein"
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:th="http://www.blackmesatech.com/2017/nss/trojan-horse">
   <teiHeader>
      <titleSmt>
         <title>f1831  chapter_x</title>
      </titleSmt>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <milestone xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
                    unit="chapter"
                    type="start"
                    n="10"/>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app4-f1831">
            <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER X.<head ana="end"/>
         </seg>
         <head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" ana="start"/>CHAPTER X.<head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" ana="end"/>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p1">
            <seg xml:id="C16_app6-f1831">I <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p1_hi1">SPENT</hi> the following day roaming through the valley. I stood beside the sources of the Arveiron, which take their rise in a glacier, that with slow pace is advancing down from the summit of the hills, to barricade the valley. The abrupt sides of vast mountains were before me; the icy wall of the glacier overhung me; a few shattered pines were scattered around; and the solemn silence of this glorious presence-chamber of imperial Nature was broken only by the brawling waves, or the fall of some vast fragment, the thunder sound of the avalanche, or the cracking, reverberated along the mountains of the accumulated ice, which, through the silent working of immutable laws, was ever and anon rent and torn, as if it had been but a plaything in their hands.</seg> These sublime and magnificent scenes afforded me the greatest consolation that I was capable of  <seg xml:id="C16_app18-f1831">receiving.</seg> They elevated me from all littleness of   <seg xml:id="C16_app21-f1831">feeling;</seg> and although they  <seg xml:id="C16_app23-f1831">did not remove my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app24-f1831">grief,</seg> they  <seg xml:id="C16_app26-f1831">subdued and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app27-f1831">tranquillised</seg> it. In some degree,  <seg xml:id="C16_app29-f1831">also,</seg> they diverted my mind from the thoughts  <seg xml:id="C16_app31-f1831">over which</seg> it had brooded   <seg xml:id="C16_app33-f1831">for the last</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app34-f1831">month.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app35-f1831__I">I retired to rest at night; my slumbers, as it were, waited on and ministered to by the assemblance of grand shapes which I had contemplated during the day. They congregated round me; the unstained snowy mountain-top, the glittering pinnacle, the pine woods, and ragged bare ravine; the eagle, soaring amidst the clouds—they all gathered round me, and bade me be at peace.</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app6-f1831">I <hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p1_hi1">SPENT</hi> the following day roaming through the valley. I stood beside the sources of the Arveiron, which take their rise in a glacier, that with slow pace is advancing down from the summit of the hills, to barricade the valley. The abrupt sides of vast mountains were before me; the icy wall of the glacier overhung me; a few shattered pines were scattered around; and the solemn silence of this glorious presence-chamber of imperial Nature was broken only by the brawling waves, or the fall of some vast fragment, the thunder sound of the avalanche, or the cracking, reverberated along the mountains of the accumulated ice, which, through the silent working of immutable laws, was ever and anon rent and torn, as if it had been but a plaything in their hands.</seg>I <hi xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
             xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p1_hi1">SPENT</hi>SPENT the following day roaming through the valley. I stood beside the sources of the Arveiron, which take their rise in a glacier, that with slow pace is advancing down from the summit of the hills, to barricade the valley. The abrupt sides of vast mountains were before me; the icy wall of the glacier overhung me; a few shattered pines were scattered around; and the solemn silence of this glorious presence-chamber of imperial Nature was broken only by the brawling waves, or the fall of some vast fragment, the thunder sound of the avalanche, or the cracking, reverberated along the mountains of the accumulated ice, which, through the silent working of immutable laws, was ever and anon rent and torn, as if it had been but a plaything in their hands. These sublime and magnificent scenes afforded me the greatest consolation that I was capable of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app18-f1831">receiving.</seg>receiving. They elevated me from all littleness of   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app21-f1831">feeling;</seg>feeling; and although they  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app23-f1831">did not remove my</seg>did not remove my
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app24-f1831">grief,</seg>grief, they  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app26-f1831">subdued and</seg>subdued and
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app27-f1831">tranquillised</seg>tranquillised it. In some degree,  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app29-f1831">also,</seg>also, they diverted my mind from the thoughts  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app31-f1831">over which</seg>over which it had brooded   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app33-f1831">for the last</seg>for the last
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app34-f1831">month.</seg>month.
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app35-f1831__I">I retired to rest at night; my slumbers, as it were, waited on and ministered to by the assemblance of grand shapes which I had contemplated during the day. They congregated round me; the unstained snowy mountain-top, the glittering pinnacle, the pine woods, and ragged bare ravine; the eagle, soaring amidst the clouds—they all gathered round me, and bade me be at peace.</seg>I retired to rest at night; my slumbers, as it were, waited on and ministered to by the assemblance of grand shapes which I had contemplated during the day. They congregated round me; the unstained snowy mountain-top, the glittering pinnacle, the pine woods, and ragged bare ravine; the eagle, soaring amidst the clouds—they all gathered round me, and bade me be at peace.
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p2">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app35-f1831__F">Where had they fled when the next morning I awoke? <pb xml:id="F1831_v_097" n="81"/>All of soul-inspiriting fled with sleep, and dark melancholy clouded every thought.</seg> The rain  <seg xml:id="C16_app55-f1831">was pouring</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C16_app57-f1831">torrents,</seg> and thick mists hid the summits of  <seg xml:id="C16_app59-f1831">the mountains, so that I even saw not the faces of those mighty friends. Still I would penetrate their misty veil, and seek them in their cloudy retreats. What were rain and storm to me? My mule was brought to the door, and</seg> I resolved  <seg xml:id="C16_app87-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app88-f1831">ascend</seg> to the summit of  <seg xml:id="C16_app91-f1831">Montanvert.</seg> I remembered the effect  <seg xml:id="C16_app93-f1831">that</seg> the view of the tremendous and  <seg xml:id="C16_app95-f1831">ever-moving</seg> glacier had  <seg xml:id="C16_app97-f1831">produced upon my mind when I first saw</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app98-f1831">it.</seg> It  <seg xml:id="C16_app100-f1831">had then filled me with a sublime</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app101-f1831">ecstasy,</seg> that gave wings to the  <seg xml:id="C16_app103-f1831">soul,</seg> and allowed  <seg xml:id="C16_app105-f1831">it</seg> to soar from the   <seg xml:id="C16_app107-f1831">obscure</seg> world to light and joy. The sight of the awful and majestic in nature had indeed always the effect of   <seg xml:id="C16_app109-f1831">solemnising</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C16_app111-f1831">mind,</seg> and causing me to forget the  <seg xml:id="C16_app113-f1831">passing cares of life. I determined to go</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app114-f1831">without a guide,</seg> for I was well acquainted with the  <seg xml:id="C16_app116-f1831">path,</seg> and the presence of another  <seg xml:id="C16_app118-f1831">would</seg> destroy   <seg xml:id="C16_app120-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app121-f1831__I">solitary grandeur of the scene. </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app35-f1831__F">Where had they fled when the next morning I awoke? <pb xml:id="F1831_v_097" n="81"/>All of soul-inspiriting fled with sleep, and dark melancholy clouded every thought.</seg>Where had they fled when the next morning I awoke? <pb xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="F1831_v_097" n="81"/>All of soul-inspiriting fled with sleep, and dark melancholy clouded every thought. The rain  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app55-f1831">was pouring</seg>was pouring in  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app57-f1831">torrents,</seg>torrents, and thick mists hid the summits of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app59-f1831">the mountains, so that I even saw not the faces of those mighty friends. Still I would penetrate their misty veil, and seek them in their cloudy retreats. What were rain and storm to me? My mule was brought to the door, and</seg>the mountains, so that I even saw not the faces of those mighty friends. Still I would penetrate their misty veil, and seek them in their cloudy retreats. What were rain and storm to me? My mule was brought to the door, and I resolved  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app87-f1831">to</seg>to
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app88-f1831">ascend</seg>ascend to the summit of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app91-f1831">Montanvert.</seg>Montanvert. I remembered the effect  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app93-f1831">that</seg>that the view of the tremendous and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app95-f1831">ever-moving</seg>ever-moving glacier had  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app97-f1831">produced upon my mind when I first saw</seg>produced upon my mind when I first saw
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app98-f1831">it.</seg>it. It  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app100-f1831">had then filled me with a sublime</seg>had then filled me with a sublime
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app101-f1831">ecstasy,</seg>ecstasy, that gave wings to the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app103-f1831">soul,</seg>soul, and allowed  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app105-f1831">it</seg>it to soar from the   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app107-f1831">obscure</seg>obscure world to light and joy. The sight of the awful and majestic in nature had indeed always the effect of   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app109-f1831">solemnising</seg>solemnising my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app111-f1831">mind,</seg>mind, and causing me to forget the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app113-f1831">passing cares of life. I determined to go</seg>passing cares of life. I determined to go
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app114-f1831">without a guide,</seg>without a guide, for I was well acquainted with the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app116-f1831">path,</seg>path, and the presence of another  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app118-f1831">would</seg>would destroy   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app120-f1831">the</seg>the
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app121-f1831__I">solitary grandeur of the scene. </seg>solitary grandeur of the scene. 
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p3">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app121-f1831__F"> The ascent</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app122-f1831">is</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app123-f1831">precipitous,</seg> but the path is cut into  continual and short   <seg xml:id="C16_app127-f1831">windings,</seg> which enable  <seg xml:id="C16_app129-f1831">you</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app130-f1831">to</seg> surmount the  <seg xml:id="C16_app132-f1831">perpendicularity</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C16_app134-f1831">mountain.</seg> It is a scene  <seg xml:id="C16_app136-f1831">terrifically</seg> desolate. In a thousand  <seg xml:id="C16_app138-f1831">spots</seg> the traces of the winter  <seg xml:id="C16_app140-f1831">avalanche</seg> may be  <seg xml:id="C16_app142-f1831">perceived,</seg> where trees lie broken and strewed on the ground; some entirely  <seg xml:id="C16_app144-f1831">destroyed,</seg> others  <seg xml:id="C16_app146-f1831">bent, leaning</seg> upon  <seg xml:id="C16_app148-f1831">the jutting</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app149-f1831">rocks</seg> of the mountain, or   <seg xml:id="C16_app151-f1831">transversely</seg> upon other trees. The   <seg xml:id="C16_app153-f1831">path,</seg> as you  <seg xml:id="C16_app155-f1831">ascend</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app156-f1831">higher,</seg> is  <seg xml:id="C16_app158-f1831">intersected</seg> by ravines of  snow, down which stones continually roll from above; one of   <seg xml:id="C16_app162-f1831">them is particularly</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app163-f1831">dangerous,</seg> as the slightest  <seg xml:id="C16_app165-f1831">sound,</seg> such as even speaking in a loud  <seg xml:id="C16_app167-f1831">voice,</seg> produces a   <seg xml:id="C16_app170-f1831">concussion of air sufficient to draw destruction</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app171-f1831">upon</seg> the head of the speaker. The  <seg xml:id="C16_app173-f1831">pines</seg> are not tall or  <seg xml:id="C16_app175-f1831">luxuriant,</seg> but they are  <seg xml:id="C16_app177-f1831">sombre,</seg> and add an air of  <seg xml:id="C16_app179-f1831">severity</seg> to the scene. I looked on the valley   <seg xml:id="C16_app181-f1831">beneath;</seg> vast  <seg xml:id="C16_app183-f1831">mists</seg> were rising from the  <seg xml:id="C16_app185-f1831">rivers</seg> which ran through  <seg xml:id="C16_app187-f1831">it,</seg> and curling in thick wreaths around the opposite  <seg xml:id="C16_app189-f1831">mountains,</seg> whose summits were hid in the uniform clouds, while rain poured from the dark  <seg xml:id="C16_app191-f1831">sky,</seg> and added to the melancholy impression I received from the objects around  <seg xml:id="C16_app193-f1831">me.</seg> Alas!  <seg xml:id="C16_app195-f1831">why does man boast of sensibilities</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app196-f1831">superior to</seg> those apparent in the  <seg xml:id="C16_app198-f1831">brute;</seg> it only <pb xml:id="F1831_v_098" n="82"/>renders them more necessary beings. <seg xml:id="C16_app200-f1831">If our impulses were confined to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app201-f1831">hunger, thirst,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app203-f1831">desire,</seg> we might be  <seg xml:id="C16_app205-f1831">nearly</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app206-f1831">free;</seg> but now we are moved by every wind that  <seg xml:id="C16_app208-f1831">blows,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app210-f1831">a</seg> chance  <seg xml:id="C16_app212-f1831">word or scene that that</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app213-f1831">word</seg> may convey to  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app215-f1831__I">us. </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app121-f1831__F"> The ascent</seg> The ascent
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app122-f1831">is</seg>is
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app123-f1831">precipitous,</seg>precipitous, but the path is cut into  continual and short   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app127-f1831">windings,</seg>windings, which enable  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app129-f1831">you</seg>you
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app130-f1831">to</seg>to surmount the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app132-f1831">perpendicularity</seg>perpendicularity of the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app134-f1831">mountain.</seg>mountain. It is a scene  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app136-f1831">terrifically</seg>terrifically desolate. In a thousand  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app138-f1831">spots</seg>spots the traces of the winter  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app140-f1831">avalanche</seg>avalanche may be  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app142-f1831">perceived,</seg>perceived, where trees lie broken and strewed on the ground; some entirely  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app144-f1831">destroyed,</seg>destroyed, others  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app146-f1831">bent, leaning</seg>bent, leaning upon  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app148-f1831">the jutting</seg>the jutting
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app149-f1831">rocks</seg>rocks of the mountain, or   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app151-f1831">transversely</seg>transversely upon other trees. The   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app153-f1831">path,</seg>path, as you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app155-f1831">ascend</seg>ascend
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app156-f1831">higher,</seg>higher, is  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app158-f1831">intersected</seg>intersected by ravines of  snow, down which stones continually roll from above; one of   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app162-f1831">them is particularly</seg>them is particularly
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app163-f1831">dangerous,</seg>dangerous, as the slightest  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app165-f1831">sound,</seg>sound, such as even speaking in a loud  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app167-f1831">voice,</seg>voice, produces a   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app170-f1831">concussion of air sufficient to draw destruction</seg>concussion of air sufficient to draw destruction
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app171-f1831">upon</seg>upon the head of the speaker. The  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app173-f1831">pines</seg>pines are not tall or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app175-f1831">luxuriant,</seg>luxuriant, but they are  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app177-f1831">sombre,</seg>sombre, and add an air of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app179-f1831">severity</seg>severity to the scene. I looked on the valley   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app181-f1831">beneath;</seg>beneath; vast  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app183-f1831">mists</seg>mists were rising from the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app185-f1831">rivers</seg>rivers which ran through  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app187-f1831">it,</seg>it, and curling in thick wreaths around the opposite  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app189-f1831">mountains,</seg>mountains, whose summits were hid in the uniform clouds, while rain poured from the dark  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app191-f1831">sky,</seg>sky, and added to the melancholy impression I received from the objects around  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app193-f1831">me.</seg>me. Alas!  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app195-f1831">why does man boast of sensibilities</seg>why does man boast of sensibilities
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app196-f1831">superior to</seg>superior to those apparent in the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app198-f1831">brute;</seg>brute; it only <pb xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="F1831_v_098" n="82"/>renders them more necessary beings. <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app200-f1831">If our impulses were confined to</seg>If our impulses were confined to
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app201-f1831">hunger, thirst,</seg>hunger, thirst, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app203-f1831">desire,</seg>desire, we might be  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app205-f1831">nearly</seg>nearly
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app206-f1831">free;</seg>free; but now we are moved by every wind that  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app208-f1831">blows,</seg>blows, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app210-f1831">a</seg>a chance  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app212-f1831">word or scene that that</seg>word or scene that that
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app213-f1831">word</seg>word may convey to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app215-f1831__I">us. </seg>us. 
               <lg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
             xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1">
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l1">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app215-f1831__F">
                  </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C16_app217-f1831">rest;</seg> a dream has power to poison  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app219-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app219-f1831__F">
                  </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C16_app221-f1831">rise;</seg> one  <seg xml:id="C16_app223-f1831">wand’ring</seg> thought pollutes the  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app225-f1831__I">day. </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l3">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app225-f1831__F">
                  </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C16_app227-f1831">feel,</seg> conceive, or  <seg xml:id="C16_app229-f1831">reason;</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C16_app230-f1831">laugh</seg> or  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app232-f1831__I">weep, </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app232-f1831__F">
                  </seg> Embrace fond  <seg xml:id="C16_app234-f1831">woe,</seg> or cast our cares  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app236-f1831__I">away; </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app236-f1831__F">
                  </seg> It is the  <seg xml:id="C16_app238-f1831">same: for,</seg> be it joy or  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app240-f1831__I">sorrow, </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app240-f1831__F">
                  </seg> The path of its departure still is  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app242-f1831__I">free. </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app242-f1831__F"> Man’s</seg> yesterday may  <seg xml:id="C16_app244-f1831">ne’er</seg> be like  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app246-f1831__I">his morrow; </seg>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app246-f1831__F">
                  </seg> Nought may endure but  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app248-f1831__I">mutability! </seg>
            </l>
         </lg>
         <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l1">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app215-f1831__F">
                  </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C16_app217-f1831">rest;</seg> a dream has power to poison  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app219-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app215-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   We  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app217-f1831">rest;</seg>rest; a dream has power to poison  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app219-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>sleep. 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l2">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app219-f1831__F">
                  </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C16_app221-f1831">rise;</seg> one  <seg xml:id="C16_app223-f1831">wand’ring</seg> thought pollutes the  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app225-f1831__I">day. </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app219-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   We  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app221-f1831">rise;</seg>rise; one  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app223-f1831">wand’ring</seg>wand’ring thought pollutes the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app225-f1831__I">day. </seg>day. 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l3">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app225-f1831__F">
                  </seg> We  <seg xml:id="C16_app227-f1831">feel,</seg> conceive, or  <seg xml:id="C16_app229-f1831">reason;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app230-f1831">laugh</seg> or  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app232-f1831__I">weep, </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app225-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   We  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app227-f1831">feel,</seg>feel, conceive, or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app229-f1831">reason;</seg>reason;
                     <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app230-f1831">laugh</seg>laugh or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app232-f1831__I">weep, </seg>weep, 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l4">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app232-f1831__F">
                  </seg> Embrace fond  <seg xml:id="C16_app234-f1831">woe,</seg> or cast our cares  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app236-f1831__I">away; </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app232-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   Embrace fond  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app234-f1831">woe,</seg>woe, or cast our cares  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app236-f1831__I">away; </seg>away; 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l5">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app236-f1831__F">
                  </seg> It is the  <seg xml:id="C16_app238-f1831">same: for,</seg> be it joy or  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app240-f1831__I">sorrow, </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app236-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   It is the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app238-f1831">same: for,</seg>same: for, be it joy or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app240-f1831__I">sorrow, </seg>sorrow, 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l6">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app240-f1831__F">
                  </seg> The path of its departure still is  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app242-f1831__I">free. </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app240-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   The path of its departure still is  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app242-f1831__I">free. </seg>free. 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l7">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app242-f1831__F"> Man’s</seg> yesterday may  <seg xml:id="C16_app244-f1831">ne’er</seg> be like  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app246-f1831__I">his morrow; </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app242-f1831__F"> Man’s</seg> Man’s yesterday may  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app244-f1831">ne’er</seg>ne’er be like  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app246-f1831__I">his morrow; </seg>his morrow; 
                  <l xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_lg1_l8">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app246-f1831__F">
                  </seg> Nought may endure but  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app248-f1831__I">mutability! </seg>
         </l>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app246-f1831__F">
                  </seg>
                   Nought may endure but  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app248-f1831__I">mutability! </seg>mutability! 
               <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app248-f1831__F">
            </seg>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app249-f1831__I">
            </seg>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p4">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app249-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app250-f1831">It</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C16_app252-f1831">nearly</seg> noon when I arrived at the top of the  <seg xml:id="C16_app254-f1831">ascent.</seg> For some time I sat upon the  <seg xml:id="C16_app256-f1831">rock that overlooks the sea of ice. A mist covered both that and the surrounding</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app257-f1831">mountains.</seg> Presently a breeze dissipated the  <seg xml:id="C16_app259-f1831">cloud,</seg> and I descended  <seg xml:id="C16_app261-f1831">upon</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C16_app263-f1831">glacier.</seg> The surface is very  <seg xml:id="C16_app265-f1831">uneven,</seg> rising like the waves of a troubled sea,  <seg xml:id="C16_app267-f1831">descending</seg> low, and  <seg xml:id="C16_app269-f1831">interspersed</seg> by rifts that sink  <seg xml:id="C16_app271-f1831">deep.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C16_app273-f1831">field of ice is</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app274-f1831">almost</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C16_app276-f1831">league</seg> in width, but I   <seg xml:id="C16_app279-f1831">spent</seg> nearly two hours in crossing   <seg xml:id="C16_app282-f1831">it.</seg> The opposite  <seg xml:id="C16_app284-f1831">mountain is a bare perpendicular</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app285-f1831">rock. From the</seg> side where I now stood Montanvert was exactly  <seg xml:id="C16_app287-f1831">opposite,</seg> at the distance of a  <seg xml:id="C16_app289-f1831">league;</seg> and above  <seg xml:id="C16_app291-f1831">it</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app292-f1831">rose Mont</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app293-f1831">Blanc,</seg> in awful majesty. I remained in a recess of the  <seg xml:id="C16_app295-f1831">rock,</seg> gazing on this wonderful and  <seg xml:id="C16_app297-f1831">stupendous scene.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C16_app299-f1831">sea,</seg> or rather the vast river of ice, wound among   <seg xml:id="C16_app302-f1831">its</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app303-f1831">dependent mountains,</seg> whose  <seg xml:id="C16_app305-f1831">aerial</seg> summits hung over its recesses.  <seg xml:id="C16_app307-f1831">Their</seg> icy and glittering peaks shone in  <seg xml:id="C16_app309-f1831">the</seg> sunlight over the clouds. My   <seg xml:id="C16_app312-f1831">heart,</seg> which was  <seg xml:id="C16_app314-f1831">before sorrowful,</seg> now swelled with   <seg xml:id="C16_app317-f1831">something</seg> like  <seg xml:id="C16_app319-f1831">joy;</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app321-f1831">exclaimed—“Wandering</seg> spirits, if indeed ye  <seg xml:id="C16_app323-f1831">wander,</seg> and do not rest in your narrow beds, allow me this faint  <seg xml:id="C16_app325-f1831">happiness,</seg> or take  <seg xml:id="C16_app327-f1831">me,</seg> as your  <seg xml:id="C16_app329-f1831">companion,</seg> away from the joys of life.”  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app331-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app249-f1831__F">
               </seg>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app250-f1831">It</seg>It was  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app252-f1831">nearly</seg>nearly noon when I arrived at the top of the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app254-f1831">ascent.</seg>ascent. For some time I sat upon the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app256-f1831">rock that overlooks the sea of ice. A mist covered both that and the surrounding</seg>rock that overlooks the sea of ice. A mist covered both that and the surrounding
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app257-f1831">mountains.</seg>mountains. Presently a breeze dissipated the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app259-f1831">cloud,</seg>cloud, and I descended  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app261-f1831">upon</seg>upon the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app263-f1831">glacier.</seg>glacier. The surface is very  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app265-f1831">uneven,</seg>uneven, rising like the waves of a troubled sea,  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app267-f1831">descending</seg>descending low, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app269-f1831">interspersed</seg>interspersed by rifts that sink  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app271-f1831">deep.</seg>deep. The  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app273-f1831">field of ice is</seg>field of ice is
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app274-f1831">almost</seg>almost a  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app276-f1831">league</seg>league in width, but I   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app279-f1831">spent</seg>spent nearly two hours in crossing   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app282-f1831">it.</seg>it. The opposite  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app284-f1831">mountain is a bare perpendicular</seg>mountain is a bare perpendicular
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app285-f1831">rock. From the</seg>rock. From the side where I now stood Montanvert was exactly  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app287-f1831">opposite,</seg>opposite, at the distance of a  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app289-f1831">league;</seg>league; and above  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app291-f1831">it</seg>it
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app292-f1831">rose Mont</seg>rose Mont
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app293-f1831">Blanc,</seg>Blanc, in awful majesty. I remained in a recess of the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app295-f1831">rock,</seg>rock, gazing on this wonderful and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app297-f1831">stupendous scene.</seg>stupendous scene. The  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app299-f1831">sea,</seg>sea, or rather the vast river of ice, wound among   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app302-f1831">its</seg>its
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app303-f1831">dependent mountains,</seg>dependent mountains, whose  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app305-f1831">aerial</seg>aerial summits hung over its recesses.  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app307-f1831">Their</seg>Their icy and glittering peaks shone in  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app309-f1831">the</seg>the sunlight over the clouds. My   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app312-f1831">heart,</seg>heart, which was  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app314-f1831">before sorrowful,</seg>before sorrowful, now swelled with   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app317-f1831">something</seg>something like  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app319-f1831">joy;</seg>joy; I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app321-f1831">exclaimed—“Wandering</seg>exclaimed—“Wandering spirits, if indeed ye  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app323-f1831">wander,</seg>wander, and do not rest in your narrow beds, allow me this faint  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app325-f1831">happiness,</seg>happiness, or take  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app327-f1831">me,</seg>me, as your  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app329-f1831">companion,</seg>companion, away from the joys of life.”  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app331-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p5">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app331-f1831__F">
               </seg> As I said  <seg xml:id="C16_app333-f1831">this,</seg> I suddenly beheld  <seg xml:id="C16_app335-f1831">the figure of a</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app336-f1831">man,</seg> at some  <seg xml:id="C16_app338-f1831">distance,</seg> advancing towards me with superhuman  <seg xml:id="C16_app340-f1831">speed.</seg> He bounded over the crevices in the  <seg xml:id="C16_app342-f1831">ice,</seg> among which I had walked with   <seg xml:id="C16_app345-f1831">caution;</seg> his  <seg xml:id="C16_app347-f1831">stature,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app348-f1831">also,</seg> as he  <seg xml:id="C16_app350-f1831">approached, seemed</seg> to exceed that of  <seg xml:id="C16_app352-f1831">man. I</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C16_app354-f1831">troubled:</seg> a mist  <seg xml:id="C16_app356-f1831">came over</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C16_app358-f1831">eyes,</seg> and I felt  <seg xml:id="C16_app360-f1831">a</seg> faintness seize  <seg xml:id="C16_app362-f1831">me; but I was quickly restored by</seg> the cold  <seg xml:id="C16_app364-f1831">gale</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C16_app366-f1831">mountains.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app368-f1831">perceived,</seg> as  <seg xml:id="C16_app370-f1831">the shape</seg> came   <seg xml:id="C16_app372-f1831">nearer</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app373-f1831">(sight tremendous and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_099" n="83"/>abhorred!)</seg> that it was the wretch whom I  <seg xml:id="C16_app375-f1831">had</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app376-f1831">created.</seg> I trembled with rage  <seg xml:id="C16_app378-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app379-f1831">horror, resolving</seg> to wait his  <seg xml:id="C16_app381-f1831">approach,</seg> and then close with him in mortal combat. He approached;  <seg xml:id="C16_app383-f1831">his countenance bespoke bitter</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app384-f1831">anguish,</seg> combined with  <seg xml:id="C16_app386-f1831">disdain and malignity, while its unearthly ugliness rendered it almost too horrible for human eyes. But I</seg> scarcely observed   <seg xml:id="C16_app389-f1831">this;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app390-f1831">rage</seg> and hatred  <seg xml:id="C16_app392-f1831">had at first deprived me of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app393-f1831">utterance,</seg> and I recovered only to overwhelm him with  <seg xml:id="C16_app395-f1831">words expressive of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app396-f1831">furious</seg> detestation  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app398-f1831__I">and contempt. </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app331-f1831__F">
               </seg>
                As I said  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app333-f1831">this,</seg>this, I suddenly beheld  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app335-f1831">the figure of a</seg>the figure of a
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app336-f1831">man,</seg>man, at some  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app338-f1831">distance,</seg>distance, advancing towards me with superhuman  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app340-f1831">speed.</seg>speed. He bounded over the crevices in the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app342-f1831">ice,</seg>ice, among which I had walked with   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app345-f1831">caution;</seg>caution; his  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app347-f1831">stature,</seg>stature,
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app348-f1831">also,</seg>also, as he  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app350-f1831">approached, seemed</seg>approached, seemed to exceed that of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app352-f1831">man. I</seg>man. I was  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app354-f1831">troubled:</seg>troubled: a mist  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app356-f1831">came over</seg>came over my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app358-f1831">eyes,</seg>eyes, and I felt  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app360-f1831">a</seg>a faintness seize  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app362-f1831">me; but I was quickly restored by</seg>me; but I was quickly restored by the cold  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app364-f1831">gale</seg>gale of the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app366-f1831">mountains.</seg>mountains. I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app368-f1831">perceived,</seg>perceived, as  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app370-f1831">the shape</seg>the shape came   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app372-f1831">nearer</seg>nearer
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app373-f1831">(sight tremendous and <pb xml:id="F1831_v_099" n="83"/>abhorred!)</seg>(sight tremendous and <pb xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="F1831_v_099" n="83"/>abhorred!) that it was the wretch whom I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app375-f1831">had</seg>had
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app376-f1831">created.</seg>created. I trembled with rage  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app378-f1831">and</seg>and
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app379-f1831">horror, resolving</seg>horror, resolving to wait his  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app381-f1831">approach,</seg>approach, and then close with him in mortal combat. He approached;  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app383-f1831">his countenance bespoke bitter</seg>his countenance bespoke bitter
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app384-f1831">anguish,</seg>anguish, combined with  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app386-f1831">disdain and malignity, while its unearthly ugliness rendered it almost too horrible for human eyes. But I</seg>disdain and malignity, while its unearthly ugliness rendered it almost too horrible for human eyes. But I scarcely observed   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app389-f1831">this;</seg>this;
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app390-f1831">rage</seg>rage and hatred  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app392-f1831">had at first deprived me of</seg>had at first deprived me of
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app393-f1831">utterance,</seg>utterance, and I recovered only to overwhelm him with  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app395-f1831">words expressive of</seg>words expressive of
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app396-f1831">furious</seg>furious detestation  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app398-f1831__I">and contempt. </seg>and contempt. 
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p6">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app398-f1831__F">
               </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app399-f1831">“Devil,”</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app401-f1831">exclaimed,</seg> “do you dare approach  <seg xml:id="C16_app403-f1831">me?</seg> and do not  <seg xml:id="C16_app405-f1831">you</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app406-f1831">fear</seg> the fierce vengeance of my arm wreaked on  <seg xml:id="C16_app408-f1831">your</seg> miserable  <seg xml:id="C16_app410-f1831">head? Begone,</seg> vile  <seg xml:id="C16_app412-f1831">insect!</seg> or  <seg xml:id="C16_app414-f1831">rather, stay,</seg> that I may trample you to  <seg xml:id="C16_app416-f1831">dust! and, oh!</seg> that I  <seg xml:id="C16_app418-f1831">could,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C16_app420-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app421-f1831">extinction of</seg> your miserable   <seg xml:id="C16_app423-f1831">existence,</seg> restore those  <seg xml:id="C16_app425-f1831">victims</seg> whom you have  <seg xml:id="C16_app427-f1831">so diabolically murdered!”</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app398-f1831__F">
               </seg>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app399-f1831">“Devil,”</seg>“Devil,” I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app401-f1831">exclaimed,</seg>exclaimed, “do you dare approach  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app403-f1831">me?</seg>me? and do not  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app405-f1831">you</seg>you
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app406-f1831">fear</seg>fear the fierce vengeance of my arm wreaked on  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app408-f1831">your</seg>your miserable  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app410-f1831">head? Begone,</seg>head? Begone, vile  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app412-f1831">insect!</seg>insect! or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app414-f1831">rather, stay,</seg>rather, stay, that I may trample you to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app416-f1831">dust! and, oh!</seg>dust! and, oh! that I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app418-f1831">could,</seg>could, with  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app420-f1831">the</seg>the
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app421-f1831">extinction of</seg>extinction of your miserable   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app423-f1831">existence,</seg>existence, restore those  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app425-f1831">victims</seg>victims whom you have  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app427-f1831">so diabolically murdered!”</seg>so diabolically murdered!”
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p7"> “I <seg xml:id="C16_app429-f1831">expected</seg> this  <seg xml:id="C16_app431-f1831">reception,”</seg> said the  <seg xml:id="C16_app433-f1831">dæmon. “All</seg> men hate  <seg xml:id="C16_app435-f1831">the</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app436-f1831">wretched;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app437-f1831">how, then,</seg> must  <seg xml:id="C16_app439-f1831">I</seg> be   <seg xml:id="C16_app441-f1831">hated,</seg> who am miserable beyond  <seg xml:id="C16_app443-f1831">all living</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app444-f1831">things!</seg> Yet  <seg xml:id="C16_app446-f1831">you,</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C16_app448-f1831">creator, detest</seg> and spurn  <seg xml:id="C16_app450-f1831">me,</seg> thy  <seg xml:id="C16_app452-f1831">creature,</seg> to whom thou art bound  <seg xml:id="C16_app454-f1831">by</seg> ties only dissoluble by the  <seg xml:id="C16_app456-f1831">annihilation</seg> of one of us.  <seg xml:id="C16_app458-f1831">You</seg> purpose to kill me.   <seg xml:id="C16_app461-f1831">How</seg> dare you sport thus with life? Do your duty towards  <seg xml:id="C16_app463-f1831">me,</seg> and I will do mine towards you  <seg xml:id="C16_app465-f1831">and</seg> the rest of mankind.  <seg xml:id="C16_app467-f1831">If you</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app468-f1831">will</seg> comply with my  <seg xml:id="C16_app470-f1831">conditions, I</seg> will leave them and you at  <seg xml:id="C16_app472-f1831">peace; but</seg> if you  <seg xml:id="C16_app474-f1831">refuse,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app476-f1831">will</seg> glut the   <seg xml:id="C16_app478-f1831">maw of</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app479-f1831">death, until</seg> it be   <seg xml:id="C16_app482-f1831">satiated</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app483-f1831">with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app484-f1831">the blood of</seg> your  <seg xml:id="C16_app486-f1831">remaining</seg> friends.” </p> “I <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app429-f1831">expected</seg>expected this  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app431-f1831">reception,”</seg>reception,” said the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app433-f1831">dæmon. “All</seg>dæmon. “All men hate  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app435-f1831">the</seg>the
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app436-f1831">wretched;</seg>wretched;
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app437-f1831">how, then,</seg>how, then, must  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app439-f1831">I</seg>I be   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app441-f1831">hated,</seg>hated, who am miserable beyond  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app443-f1831">all living</seg>all living
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app444-f1831">things!</seg>things! Yet  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app446-f1831">you,</seg>you, my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app448-f1831">creator, detest</seg>creator, detest and spurn  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app450-f1831">me,</seg>me, thy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app452-f1831">creature,</seg>creature, to whom thou art bound  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app454-f1831">by</seg>by ties only dissoluble by the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app456-f1831">annihilation</seg>annihilation of one of us.  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app458-f1831">You</seg>You purpose to kill me.   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app461-f1831">How</seg>How dare you sport thus with life? Do your duty towards  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app463-f1831">me,</seg>me, and I will do mine towards you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app465-f1831">and</seg>and the rest of mankind.  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app467-f1831">If you</seg>If you
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app468-f1831">will</seg>will comply with my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app470-f1831">conditions, I</seg>conditions, I will leave them and you at  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app472-f1831">peace; but</seg>peace; but if you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app474-f1831">refuse,</seg>refuse, I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app476-f1831">will</seg>will glut the   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app478-f1831">maw of</seg>maw of
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app479-f1831">death, until</seg>death, until it be   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app482-f1831">satiated</seg>satiated
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app483-f1831">with</seg>with
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app484-f1831">the blood of</seg>the blood of your  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app486-f1831">remaining</seg>remaining friends.” 
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p8">
            <seg xml:id="C16_app488-f1831">“Abhorred monster!</seg> fiend that thou  <seg xml:id="C16_app490-f1831">art!</seg> the tortures of hell are too  <seg xml:id="C16_app492-f1831">mild a vengeance for thy crimes. Wretched devil! you reproach me with your creation;</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app493-f1831">come</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app494-f1831">on,</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app495-f1831">then,</seg> that I may extinguish the spark  <seg xml:id="C16_app497-f1831">which</seg> I so negligently bestowed.”  <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app499-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app488-f1831">“Abhorred monster!</seg>“Abhorred monster! fiend that thou  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app490-f1831">art!</seg>art! the tortures of hell are too  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app492-f1831">mild a vengeance for thy crimes. Wretched devil! you reproach me with your creation;</seg>mild a vengeance for thy crimes. Wretched devil! you reproach me with your creation;
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app493-f1831">come</seg>come
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app494-f1831">on,</seg>on,
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app495-f1831">then,</seg>then, that I may extinguish the spark  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app497-f1831">which</seg>which I so negligently bestowed.”  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app499-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p9">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app499-f1831__F">
               </seg> My rage was without  <seg xml:id="C16_app501-f1831">bounds;</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app503-f1831">sprang</seg> on  <seg xml:id="C16_app505-f1831">him,</seg> impelled by all the feelings which can arm one being against the existence of another.   <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app508-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app499-f1831__F">
               </seg>
                My rage was without  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app501-f1831">bounds;</seg>bounds; I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app503-f1831">sprang</seg>sprang on  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app505-f1831">him,</seg>him, impelled by all the feelings which can arm one being against the existence of another.   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app508-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p10">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app508-f1831__F">
               </seg> He  <seg xml:id="C16_app510-f1831">easily</seg> eluded  <seg xml:id="C16_app512-f1831">me, and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app513-f1831">said—</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app514-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app508-f1831__F">
               </seg>
                He  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app510-f1831">easily</seg>easily eluded  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app512-f1831">me, and</seg>me, and
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app513-f1831">said—</seg>said—
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app514-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p11">
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C16_app514-f1831__F"> “Be calm!</seg> I entreat  <seg xml:id="C16_app516-f1831">you to hear me, before you give vent to your hatred</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app517-f1831">on my devoted</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app518-f1831">head.</seg> Have I not  <seg xml:id="C16_app520-f1831">suffered enough,</seg> that you  <seg xml:id="C16_app522-f1831">seek</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C16_app524-f1831">increase</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C16_app526-f1831">misery? Life,</seg> although it  <seg xml:id="C16_app528-f1831">may</seg> only  <seg xml:id="C16_app530-f1831">be</seg> an accumulation of  <seg xml:id="C16_app532-f1831">anguish,</seg> is dear <pb xml:id="F1831_v_100" n="84"/>to <seg xml:id="C16_app534-f1831">me,</seg> and I will defend  <seg xml:id="C16_app536-f1831">it. Remember,</seg> thou hast made me more  <seg xml:id="C16_app538-f1831">powerful</seg> than  <seg xml:id="C16_app540-f1831">thyself;</seg> my height is superior to  <seg xml:id="C16_app542-f1831">thine;</seg> my joints more supple. But I  <seg xml:id="C16_app544-f1831">will not be tempted to set myself in opposition to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app545-f1831">thee.</seg> I am thy  <seg xml:id="C16_app547-f1831">creature,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app549-f1831">I will</seg> be even mild and docile   <seg xml:id="C16_app552-f1831">to</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app553-f1831">my natural</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app554-f1831">lord</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app556-f1831">king,</seg> if  <seg xml:id="C16_app558-f1831">thou</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app559-f1831">wilt also</seg> perform  <seg xml:id="C16_app561-f1831">thy</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app562-f1831">part,</seg> the which thou owest  <seg xml:id="C16_app564-f1831">me.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app565-f1831">Oh,</seg> Frankenstein,  <seg xml:id="C16_app567-f1831">be</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app568-f1831">not</seg> equitable to every  <seg xml:id="C16_app570-f1831">other,</seg> and trample upon me  <seg xml:id="C16_app572-f1831">alone,</seg> to whom thy  <seg xml:id="C16_app574-f1831">justice,</seg> and even  <seg xml:id="C16_app576-f1831">thy clemency and affection,</seg> is most due.  <seg xml:id="C16_app578-f1831">Remember,</seg> that I am thy  <seg xml:id="C16_app580-f1831">creature;</seg> I ought to be thy   <seg xml:id="C16_app583-f1831">Adam;</seg> but I am rather the fallen   <seg xml:id="C16_app586-f1831">angel,</seg> whom thou  <seg xml:id="C16_app588-f1831">drivest</seg> from joy for no  <seg xml:id="C16_app590-f1831">misdeed.</seg> Every where I see  <seg xml:id="C16_app592-f1831">bliss,</seg> from  <seg xml:id="C16_app594-f1831">which</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app596-f1831">alone</seg> am  <seg xml:id="C16_app598-f1831">irrevocably excluded.</seg> I was benevolent and  <seg xml:id="C16_app600-f1831">good;</seg> misery made me a fiend. Make me  <seg xml:id="C16_app602-f1831">happy,</seg> and I shall again be  <seg xml:id="C16_app604-f1831">virtuous.”</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app514-f1831__F"> “Be calm!</seg> “Be calm! I entreat  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app516-f1831">you to hear me, before you give vent to your hatred</seg>you to hear me, before you give vent to your hatred
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app517-f1831">on my devoted</seg>on my devoted
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app518-f1831">head.</seg>head. Have I not  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app520-f1831">suffered enough,</seg>suffered enough, that you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app522-f1831">seek</seg>seek to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app524-f1831">increase</seg>increase my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app526-f1831">misery? Life,</seg>misery? Life, although it  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app528-f1831">may</seg>may only  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app530-f1831">be</seg>be an accumulation of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app532-f1831">anguish,</seg>anguish, is dear <pb xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="F1831_v_100" n="84"/>to <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app534-f1831">me,</seg>me, and I will defend  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app536-f1831">it. Remember,</seg>it. Remember, thou hast made me more  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app538-f1831">powerful</seg>powerful than  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app540-f1831">thyself;</seg>thyself; my height is superior to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app542-f1831">thine;</seg>thine; my joints more supple. But I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app544-f1831">will not be tempted to set myself in opposition to</seg>will not be tempted to set myself in opposition to
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app545-f1831">thee.</seg>thee. I am thy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app547-f1831">creature,</seg>creature, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app549-f1831">I will</seg>I will be even mild and docile   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app552-f1831">to</seg>to
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app553-f1831">my natural</seg>my natural
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app554-f1831">lord</seg>lord and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app556-f1831">king,</seg>king, if  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app558-f1831">thou</seg>thou
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app559-f1831">wilt also</seg>wilt also perform  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app561-f1831">thy</seg>thy
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app562-f1831">part,</seg>part, the which thou owest  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app564-f1831">me.</seg>me.
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app565-f1831">Oh,</seg>Oh, Frankenstein,  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app567-f1831">be</seg>be
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app568-f1831">not</seg>not equitable to every  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app570-f1831">other,</seg>other, and trample upon me  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app572-f1831">alone,</seg>alone, to whom thy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app574-f1831">justice,</seg>justice, and even  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app576-f1831">thy clemency and affection,</seg>thy clemency and affection, is most due.  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app578-f1831">Remember,</seg>Remember, that I am thy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app580-f1831">creature;</seg>creature; I ought to be thy   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app583-f1831">Adam;</seg>Adam; but I am rather the fallen   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app586-f1831">angel,</seg>angel, whom thou  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app588-f1831">drivest</seg>drivest from joy for no  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app590-f1831">misdeed.</seg>misdeed. Every where I see  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app592-f1831">bliss,</seg>bliss, from  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app594-f1831">which</seg>which I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app596-f1831">alone</seg>alone am  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app598-f1831">irrevocably excluded.</seg>irrevocably excluded. I was benevolent and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app600-f1831">good;</seg>good; misery made me a fiend. Make me  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app602-f1831">happy,</seg>happy, and I shall again be  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app604-f1831">virtuous.”</seg>virtuous.”
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p12">
            <seg xml:id="C16_app606-f1831">“Begone!</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app608-f1831">will not hear you. There can be no community between you and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app609-f1831">me;</seg> we are  <seg xml:id="C16_app611-f1831">enemies. Begone,</seg> or  <seg xml:id="C16_app613-f1831">let us try our</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app614-f1831">strength</seg> in a  <seg xml:id="C16_app616-f1831">fight,</seg> in which one must  <seg xml:id="C16_app618-f1831">fall.”</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app606-f1831">“Begone!</seg>“Begone! I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app608-f1831">will not hear you. There can be no community between you and</seg>will not hear you. There can be no community between you and
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app609-f1831">me;</seg>me; we are  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app611-f1831">enemies. Begone,</seg>enemies. Begone, or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app613-f1831">let us try our</seg>let us try our
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app614-f1831">strength</seg>strength in a  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app616-f1831">fight,</seg>fight, in which one must  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app618-f1831">fall.”</seg>fall.”
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p13">
            <seg xml:id="C16_app620-f1831">“How</seg> can I move  <seg xml:id="C16_app622-f1831">thee?</seg> Will no entreaties cause  <seg xml:id="C16_app624-f1831">thee</seg> to turn a favourable eye upon thy  <seg xml:id="C16_app626-f1831">creature,</seg> who implores thy goodness and  <seg xml:id="C16_app628-f1831">compassion?</seg> Believe me,  <seg xml:id="C16_app630-f1831">Frankenstein:</seg> I was  <seg xml:id="C16_app632-f1831">benevolent; my</seg> soul glowed with love and   <seg xml:id="C16_app635-f1831">humanity:</seg> but am I not  <seg xml:id="C16_app637-f1831">alone,</seg> miserably  <seg xml:id="C16_app639-f1831">alone?</seg> You, my  <seg xml:id="C16_app641-f1831">creator,</seg> abhor  <seg xml:id="C16_app643-f1831">me;</seg> what hope  <seg xml:id="C16_app645-f1831">can I gather from</seg> your   <seg xml:id="C16_app647-f1831">fellow-creatures,</seg> who owe me  <seg xml:id="C16_app649-f1831">nothing? they</seg> spurn and  <seg xml:id="C16_app651-f1831">hate me. The</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app652-f1831">desert</seg> mountains and  <seg xml:id="C16_app654-f1831">dreary</seg> glaciers are my  <seg xml:id="C16_app656-f1831">refuge. I</seg> have wandered here many  <seg xml:id="C16_app658-f1831">days;</seg> the caves of  <seg xml:id="C16_app660-f1831">ice,</seg> which I only do not  <seg xml:id="C16_app662-f1831">fear,</seg> are a dwelling to  <seg xml:id="C16_app664-f1831">me,</seg> and the only one which man does not  <seg xml:id="C16_app666-f1831">grudge.</seg> These bleak skies I  <seg xml:id="C16_app668-f1831">hail,</seg> for they are kinder to me than   <seg xml:id="C16_app671-f1831">your</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app672-f1831">fellow-beings.</seg> If the multitude of mankind knew of my   <seg xml:id="C16_app675-f1831">existence,</seg> they would   <seg xml:id="C16_app678-f1831">do</seg> as you  <seg xml:id="C16_app680-f1831">do, and</seg> arm themselves for my  <seg xml:id="C16_app682-f1831">destruction. Shall</seg> I not then hate them who abhor   <seg xml:id="C16_app685-f1831">me?</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app687-f1831">will</seg> keep no   <seg xml:id="C16_app689-f1831">terms with</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app690-f1831">my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app691-f1831">enemies.</seg> I am  <seg xml:id="C16_app693-f1831">miserable,</seg> and they shall share my  <seg xml:id="C16_app695-f1831">wretchedness.</seg> Yet it is in your  <seg xml:id="C16_app697-f1831">power</seg> to recompense  <seg xml:id="C16_app699-f1831">me,</seg> and deliver them from an evil which  <seg xml:id="C16_app701-f1831">it</seg> only remains for you to make so great, that not only you and your   <seg xml:id="C16_app703-f1831">family,</seg> but thousands of  <seg xml:id="C16_app705-f1831">others,</seg> shall be swallowed up in the whirlwinds of its rage.  <seg xml:id="C16_app707-f1831">Let your compassion</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app708-f1831">be</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app709-f1831">moved,</seg> and do <pb xml:id="F1831_v_101" n="85"/>not disdain me. Listen to my <seg xml:id="C16_app711-f1831">tale:</seg> when you have heard  <seg xml:id="C16_app713-f1831">that, abandon</seg> or  <seg xml:id="C16_app715-f1831">commiserate me,</seg> as you shall judge that I   <seg xml:id="C16_app718-f1831">deserve.</seg> But  <seg xml:id="C16_app720-f1831">hear</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app721-f1831">me. The</seg> guilty  <seg xml:id="C16_app723-f1831">are</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app724-f1831">allowed,</seg> by human laws, bloody as they  <seg xml:id="C16_app726-f1831">are,</seg> to speak in their own defence before they are   <seg xml:id="C16_app731-f1831">condemned.</seg> Listen to  <seg xml:id="C16_app733-f1831">me, Frankenstein.</seg> You accuse me of  <seg xml:id="C16_app735-f1831">murder;</seg> and yet  <seg xml:id="C16_app737-f1831">you</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app738-f1831">would,</seg> with a  <seg xml:id="C16_app740-f1831">satisfied conscience,</seg> destroy  <seg xml:id="C16_app742-f1831">your</seg> own  <seg xml:id="C16_app744-f1831">creature. Oh,</seg> praise the eternal justice of  <seg xml:id="C16_app746-f1831">man! Yet</seg> I ask you not to spare  <seg xml:id="C16_app748-f1831">me:</seg> listen  <seg xml:id="C16_app750-f1831">to me;</seg> and then, if you  <seg xml:id="C16_app752-f1831">can,</seg> and if you will, destroy the work of your hands.” </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app620-f1831">“How</seg>“How can I move  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app622-f1831">thee?</seg>thee? Will no entreaties cause  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app624-f1831">thee</seg>thee to turn a favourable eye upon thy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app626-f1831">creature,</seg>creature, who implores thy goodness and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app628-f1831">compassion?</seg>compassion? Believe me,  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app630-f1831">Frankenstein:</seg>Frankenstein: I was  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app632-f1831">benevolent; my</seg>benevolent; my soul glowed with love and   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app635-f1831">humanity:</seg>humanity: but am I not  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app637-f1831">alone,</seg>alone, miserably  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app639-f1831">alone?</seg>alone? You, my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app641-f1831">creator,</seg>creator, abhor  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app643-f1831">me;</seg>me; what hope  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app645-f1831">can I gather from</seg>can I gather from your   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app647-f1831">fellow-creatures,</seg>fellow-creatures, who owe me  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app649-f1831">nothing? they</seg>nothing? they spurn and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app651-f1831">hate me. The</seg>hate me. The
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app652-f1831">desert</seg>desert mountains and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app654-f1831">dreary</seg>dreary glaciers are my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app656-f1831">refuge. I</seg>refuge. I have wandered here many  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app658-f1831">days;</seg>days; the caves of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app660-f1831">ice,</seg>ice, which I only do not  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app662-f1831">fear,</seg>fear, are a dwelling to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app664-f1831">me,</seg>me, and the only one which man does not  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app666-f1831">grudge.</seg>grudge. These bleak skies I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app668-f1831">hail,</seg>hail, for they are kinder to me than   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app671-f1831">your</seg>your
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app672-f1831">fellow-beings.</seg>fellow-beings. If the multitude of mankind knew of my   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app675-f1831">existence,</seg>existence, they would   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app678-f1831">do</seg>do as you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app680-f1831">do, and</seg>do, and arm themselves for my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app682-f1831">destruction. Shall</seg>destruction. Shall I not then hate them who abhor   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app685-f1831">me?</seg>me? I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app687-f1831">will</seg>will keep no   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app689-f1831">terms with</seg>terms with
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app690-f1831">my</seg>my
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app691-f1831">enemies.</seg>enemies. I am  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app693-f1831">miserable,</seg>miserable, and they shall share my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app695-f1831">wretchedness.</seg>wretchedness. Yet it is in your  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app697-f1831">power</seg>power to recompense  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app699-f1831">me,</seg>me, and deliver them from an evil which  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app701-f1831">it</seg>it only remains for you to make so great, that not only you and your   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app703-f1831">family,</seg>family, but thousands of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app705-f1831">others,</seg>others, shall be swallowed up in the whirlwinds of its rage.  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app707-f1831">Let your compassion</seg>Let your compassion
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app708-f1831">be</seg>be
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app709-f1831">moved,</seg>moved, and do <pb xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="F1831_v_101" n="85"/>not disdain me. Listen to my <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app711-f1831">tale:</seg>tale: when you have heard  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app713-f1831">that, abandon</seg>that, abandon or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app715-f1831">commiserate me,</seg>commiserate me, as you shall judge that I   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app718-f1831">deserve.</seg>deserve. But  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app720-f1831">hear</seg>hear
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app721-f1831">me. The</seg>me. The guilty  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app723-f1831">are</seg>are
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app724-f1831">allowed,</seg>allowed, by human laws, bloody as they  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app726-f1831">are,</seg>are, to speak in their own defence before they are   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app731-f1831">condemned.</seg>condemned. Listen to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app733-f1831">me, Frankenstein.</seg>me, Frankenstein. You accuse me of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app735-f1831">murder;</seg>murder; and yet  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app737-f1831">you</seg>you
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app738-f1831">would,</seg>would, with a  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app740-f1831">satisfied conscience,</seg>satisfied conscience, destroy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app742-f1831">your</seg>your own  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app744-f1831">creature. Oh,</seg>creature. Oh, praise the eternal justice of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app746-f1831">man! Yet</seg>man! Yet I ask you not to spare  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app748-f1831">me:</seg>me: listen  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app750-f1831">to me;</seg>to me; and then, if you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app752-f1831">can,</seg>can, and if you will, destroy the work of your hands.” 
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p14">
            <seg xml:id="C16_app755-f1831">“Why do</seg> you  <seg xml:id="C16_app757-f1831">call to my</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app758-f1831">remembrance,” I rejoined, “circumstances,</seg> of which I shudder to   <seg xml:id="C16_app761-f1831">reflect,</seg> that I have been the miserable origin and   <seg xml:id="C16_app764-f1831">author?</seg> Cursed be the  <seg xml:id="C16_app766-f1831">day, abhorred devil,</seg> in which you first saw  <seg xml:id="C16_app768-f1831">light!</seg> Cursed (although I curse myself) be the hands that formed  <seg xml:id="C16_app770-f1831">you!</seg> You have made me wretched beyond  <seg xml:id="C16_app772-f1831">expression.</seg> You have left me no power to consider whether I am just to  <seg xml:id="C16_app774-f1831">you,</seg> or  <seg xml:id="C16_app776-f1831">not. Begone!</seg> relieve me from  <seg xml:id="C16_app778-f1831">the sight of</seg> your  <seg xml:id="C16_app780-f1831">detested form.”</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app755-f1831">“Why do</seg>“Why do you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app757-f1831">call to my</seg>call to my
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app758-f1831">remembrance,” I rejoined, “circumstances,</seg>remembrance,” I rejoined, “circumstances, of which I shudder to   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app761-f1831">reflect,</seg>reflect, that I have been the miserable origin and   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app764-f1831">author?</seg>author? Cursed be the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app766-f1831">day, abhorred devil,</seg>day, abhorred devil, in which you first saw  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app768-f1831">light!</seg>light! Cursed (although I curse myself) be the hands that formed  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app770-f1831">you!</seg>you! You have made me wretched beyond  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app772-f1831">expression.</seg>expression. You have left me no power to consider whether I am just to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app774-f1831">you,</seg>you, or  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app776-f1831">not. Begone!</seg>not. Begone! relieve me from  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app778-f1831">the sight of</seg>the sight of your  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app780-f1831">detested form.”</seg>detested form.”
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p15">
            <seg xml:id="C16_app782-f1831">“Thus</seg> I relieve  <seg xml:id="C16_app784-f1831">thee, my creator,”</seg> he  <seg xml:id="C16_app786-f1831">said,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app788-f1831">placed his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app789-f1831">hated hands</seg> before my  <seg xml:id="C16_app791-f1831">eyes,</seg> which I flung from me with  <seg xml:id="C16_app793-f1831">violence; “thus I take from thee a</seg> sight  <seg xml:id="C16_app795-f1831">which</seg> you  <seg xml:id="C16_app797-f1831">abhor. Still thou canst</seg> listen to  <seg xml:id="C16_app799-f1831">me,</seg> and grant me  <seg xml:id="C16_app801-f1831">thy compassion. By</seg> the virtues  <seg xml:id="C16_app803-f1831">that</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C16_app805-f1831">once</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app806-f1831">possessed,</seg> I demand this  <seg xml:id="C16_app808-f1831">from you.</seg> Hear my  <seg xml:id="C16_app810-f1831">tale; it</seg> is long and  <seg xml:id="C16_app812-f1831">strange,</seg> and the temperature of this place is not fitting  <seg xml:id="C16_app814-f1831">to your fine sensations; come to the</seg> hut   <seg xml:id="C16_app816-f1831">upon</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C16_app818-f1831">mountain.</seg> The sun is yet high in the  <seg xml:id="C16_app820-f1831">heavens;</seg> before it descends to  <seg xml:id="C16_app822-f1831">hide itself behind</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app823-f1831">yon</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app824-f1831">snowy precipices,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app826-f1831">illuminate</seg> another  <seg xml:id="C16_app828-f1831">world,</seg> you will have heard my  <seg xml:id="C16_app830-f1831">story,</seg> and can decide.  <seg xml:id="C16_app832-f1831">On you it</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app833-f1831">rests,</seg> whether I quit for ever the  <seg xml:id="C16_app835-f1831">neighbourhood</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C16_app837-f1831">man,</seg> and lead a harmless  <seg xml:id="C16_app839-f1831">life,</seg> or become the scourge of your  <seg xml:id="C16_app841-f1831">fellow-creatures,</seg> and the author of your own speedy  <seg xml:id="C16_app843-f1831">ruin.”</seg>
         </p>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app782-f1831">“Thus</seg>“Thus I relieve  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app784-f1831">thee, my creator,”</seg>thee, my creator,” he  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app786-f1831">said,</seg>said, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app788-f1831">placed his</seg>placed his
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app789-f1831">hated hands</seg>hated hands before my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app791-f1831">eyes,</seg>eyes, which I flung from me with  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app793-f1831">violence; “thus I take from thee a</seg>violence; “thus I take from thee a sight  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app795-f1831">which</seg>which you  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app797-f1831">abhor. Still thou canst</seg>abhor. Still thou canst listen to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app799-f1831">me,</seg>me, and grant me  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app801-f1831">thy compassion. By</seg>thy compassion. By the virtues  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app803-f1831">that</seg>that I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app805-f1831">once</seg>once
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app806-f1831">possessed,</seg>possessed, I demand this  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app808-f1831">from you.</seg>from you. Hear my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app810-f1831">tale; it</seg>tale; it is long and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app812-f1831">strange,</seg>strange, and the temperature of this place is not fitting  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app814-f1831">to your fine sensations; come to the</seg>to your fine sensations; come to the hut   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app816-f1831">upon</seg>upon the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app818-f1831">mountain.</seg>mountain. The sun is yet high in the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app820-f1831">heavens;</seg>heavens; before it descends to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app822-f1831">hide itself behind</seg>hide itself behind
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app823-f1831">yon</seg>yon
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app824-f1831">snowy precipices,</seg>snowy precipices, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app826-f1831">illuminate</seg>illuminate another  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app828-f1831">world,</seg>world, you will have heard my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app830-f1831">story,</seg>story, and can decide.  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app832-f1831">On you it</seg>On you it
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app833-f1831">rests,</seg>rests, whether I quit for ever the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app835-f1831">neighbourhood</seg>neighbourhood of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app837-f1831">man,</seg>man, and lead a harmless  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app839-f1831">life,</seg>life, or become the scourge of your  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app841-f1831">fellow-creatures,</seg>fellow-creatures, and the author of your own speedy  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app843-f1831">ruin.”</seg>ruin.”
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
            xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter10_div4_div10_p16"> As he said <seg xml:id="C16_app845-f1831">this,</seg> he led the way across the  <seg xml:id="C16_app847-f1831">ice: I followed.</seg> My heart was  <seg xml:id="C16_app849-f1831">full,</seg> and I did not answer   <seg xml:id="C16_app852-f1831">him; but,</seg> as I  <seg xml:id="C16_app854-f1831">proceeded,</seg> I weighed the various arguments  <seg xml:id="C16_app856-f1831">that</seg> he had used,  <seg xml:id="C16_app858-f1831">and</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app859-f1831">determined at least to listen to his</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app860-f1831">tale. I</seg> was partly urged by curiosity, and compassion confirmed  <seg xml:id="C16_app862-f1831">my resolution.</seg> I had hitherto supposed him to be the  <seg xml:id="C16_app864-f1831">murderer</seg> of my  <seg xml:id="C16_app866-f1831">brother,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C16_app868-f1831">I eagerly sought a confirm<pb xml:id="F1831_v_102" n="86"/>ation or denial of this opinion.</seg> For the first   <seg xml:id="C16_app870-f1831">time, also,</seg> I felt what the duties of a creator towards his creature  <seg xml:id="C16_app872-f1831">were,</seg> and that I ought to render him happy before I complained of his wickedness. These motives urged me to comply with his  <seg xml:id="C16_app874-f1831">demand.</seg> We crossed the  <seg xml:id="C16_app876-f1831">ice,</seg> therefore, and ascended the opposite  <seg xml:id="C16_app878-f1831">rock.</seg> The air was  <seg xml:id="C16_app880-f1831">cold,</seg> and the rain  <seg xml:id="C16_app882-f1831">again</seg>
            <seg xml:id="C16_app883-f1831">began</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C16_app885-f1831">descend: we</seg> entered the  <seg xml:id="C16_app887-f1831">hut,</seg> the fiend with an air of  <seg xml:id="C16_app889-f1831">exultation,</seg> I with a  <seg xml:id="C16_app891-f1831">heavy heart,</seg> and depressed  <seg xml:id="C16_app893-f1831">spirits.</seg> But I consented to  <seg xml:id="C16_app895-f1831">listen; and,</seg> seating myself by the fire which   <seg xml:id="C16_app898-f1831">my odious companion had lighted,</seg> he thus  <seg xml:id="C16_app900-f1831">began his tale.</seg>
            <seg part="I" xml:id="C16_app901-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         </p> As he said <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app845-f1831">this,</seg>this, he led the way across the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app847-f1831">ice: I followed.</seg>ice: I followed. My heart was  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app849-f1831">full,</seg>full, and I did not answer   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app852-f1831">him; but,</seg>him; but, as I  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app854-f1831">proceeded,</seg>proceeded, I weighed the various arguments  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app856-f1831">that</seg>that he had used,  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app858-f1831">and</seg>and
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app859-f1831">determined at least to listen to his</seg>determined at least to listen to his
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app860-f1831">tale. I</seg>tale. I was partly urged by curiosity, and compassion confirmed  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app862-f1831">my resolution.</seg>my resolution. I had hitherto supposed him to be the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app864-f1831">murderer</seg>murderer of my  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app866-f1831">brother,</seg>brother, and  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app868-f1831">I eagerly sought a confirm<pb xml:id="F1831_v_102" n="86"/>ation or denial of this opinion.</seg>I eagerly sought a confirm<pb xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="F1831_v_102" n="86"/>ation or denial of this opinion. For the first   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app870-f1831">time, also,</seg>time, also, I felt what the duties of a creator towards his creature  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app872-f1831">were,</seg>were, and that I ought to render him happy before I complained of his wickedness. These motives urged me to comply with his  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app874-f1831">demand.</seg>demand. We crossed the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app876-f1831">ice,</seg>ice, therefore, and ascended the opposite  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app878-f1831">rock.</seg>rock. The air was  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app880-f1831">cold,</seg>cold, and the rain  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app882-f1831">again</seg>again
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app883-f1831">began</seg>began to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app885-f1831">descend: we</seg>descend: we entered the  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app887-f1831">hut,</seg>hut, the fiend with an air of  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app889-f1831">exultation,</seg>exultation, I with a  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app891-f1831">heavy heart,</seg>heavy heart, and depressed  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app893-f1831">spirits.</seg>spirits. But I consented to  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app895-f1831">listen; and,</seg>listen; and, seating myself by the fire which   <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app898-f1831">my odious companion had lighted,</seg>my odious companion had lighted, he thus  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app900-f1831">began his tale.</seg>began his tale.
                  <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="I"
              xml:id="C16_app901-f1831__I">
               </seg>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
              part="F"
              xml:id="C16_app901-f1831__F">
            </seg>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C16_app902-f1831">
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="10"/>
         </seg>
         <milestone xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
                    unit="chapter"
                    type="end"
                    n="10"/>
         <?xml-model href="../segMarkerTester.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <teiHeader>
               <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>
                     <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C17</title>
                  </titleStmt>
                  <publicationStmt>
                     <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
                     <date>2023—</date>
                     <availability>
                        <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
                     </availability>
                  </publicationStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                     <p>Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing
                                    on  2023-05-28 13:45:47.345979 .</p>
                     <p>Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein
                                    Variorum spine on 2023-05-31T15:50:17.3557974-04:00.</p>
                  </sourceDesc>
               </fileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
            <text>
               <body>
                  <div type="collation">
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app2-f1831">
                        <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C17"/>
                     </seg>
                     <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="11"/>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app4-f1831">
                        <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER XI.<head ana="end"/>
                     </seg>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1"> “I<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1_hi1">T</hi> is with <seg xml:id="C17_app6-f1831">considerable</seg> difficulty that I remember the  <seg xml:id="C17_app8-f1831">original</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app9-f1831">era</seg> of my  <seg xml:id="C17_app11-f1831">being:</seg> all the events of that period appear confused and indistinct.  <seg xml:id="C17_app13-f1831">A strange</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app14-f1831">multiplicity of sensations</seg> seized  <seg xml:id="C17_app16-f1831">me, and</seg> I saw,  <seg xml:id="C17_app18-f1831">felt, heard,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app20-f1831">smelt,</seg> at the same  <seg xml:id="C17_app22-f1831">time;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app24-f1831">was, indeed,</seg> a long time before I learned to distinguish between the  <seg xml:id="C17_app26-f1831">operations of my various senses. By</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app27-f1831">degrees,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app29-f1831">remember,</seg> a stronger light pressed upon my  <seg xml:id="C17_app31-f1831">nerves,</seg> so that I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app33-f1831">shut</seg> my eyes. Darkness then came over  <seg xml:id="C17_app35-f1831">me,</seg> and troubled  <seg xml:id="C17_app37-f1831">me;</seg> but hardly had I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app41-f1831">this, when, by</seg> opening my  <seg xml:id="C17_app43-f1831">eyes,</seg> as I now  <seg xml:id="C17_app45-f1831">suppose,</seg> the light poured in upon me  <seg xml:id="C17_app47-f1831">again.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app49-f1831">walked, and,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app51-f1831">believe,</seg> descended; but  <seg xml:id="C17_app53-f1831">I</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app54-f1831">presently</seg> found a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app56-f1831">alteration</seg> in my   <seg xml:id="C17_app58-f1831">sensations. Before,</seg> dark  <seg xml:id="C17_app60-f1831">and</seg> opaque bodies had surrounded me, impervious to my touch or  <seg xml:id="C17_app62-f1831">sight; but</seg> I now found that I could wander on at  <seg xml:id="C17_app64-f1831">liberty,</seg> with no obstacles which I could not either surmount or  <seg xml:id="C17_app66-f1831">avoid.</seg> The light  <seg xml:id="C17_app68-f1831">became</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app69-f1831">more</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app70-f1831">and</seg> more  <seg xml:id="C17_app72-f1831">oppressive</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app74-f1831">me; and,</seg> the heat wearying me as I  <seg xml:id="C17_app76-f1831">walked,</seg> I sought a place where I could  <seg xml:id="C17_app78-f1831">receive</seg> shade. This was the forest near  <seg xml:id="C17_app80-f1831">Ingolstadt; and</seg> here  <seg xml:id="C17_app82-f1831">I lay</seg> by the side of a brook  <seg xml:id="C17_app84-f1831">resting from my</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app85-f1831">fatigue, until</seg> I felt tormented by hunger and thirst. This roused me from my nearly dormant  <seg xml:id="C17_app87-f1831">state,</seg> and I ate some berries which I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app89-f1831">hanging</seg> on the   <seg xml:id="C17_app91-f1831">trees,</seg> or lying on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app93-f1831">
                           <pb xml:id="F1831_v_103" n="87"/>ground.</seg> I slaked my thirst  <seg xml:id="C17_app95-f1831">at</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app97-f1831">brook;</seg> and then  <seg xml:id="C17_app99-f1831">lying</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app100-f1831">down,</seg> was overcome by  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p2">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was dark when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app104-f1831">awoke;</seg> I felt cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app106-f1831">also,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app108-f1831">half-frightened,</seg> as it were  <seg xml:id="C17_app110-f1831">instinctively,</seg> finding myself so desolate. Before I had quitted your  <seg xml:id="C17_app112-f1831">apartment,</seg> on a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app114-f1831">cold,</seg> I had covered  <seg xml:id="C17_app116-f1831">myself</seg> with some  <seg xml:id="C17_app118-f1831">clothes;</seg> but these were  <seg xml:id="C17_app120-f1831">insufficient</seg> to secure me from the  <seg xml:id="C17_app122-f1831">dews of night. I was a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app123-f1831">poor, helpless,</seg> miserable  <seg xml:id="C17_app125-f1831">wretch; I knew,</seg> and could  <seg xml:id="C17_app127-f1831">distinguish, nothing;</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app128-f1831">but</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app129-f1831">feeling</seg> pain invade me on all   <seg xml:id="C17_app131-f1831">sides,</seg> I sat down and wept. </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3">
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app133-f1831">“Soon</seg> a gentle light stole over the  <seg xml:id="C17_app135-f1831">heavens,</seg> and gave me a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app137-f1831">pleasure.</seg> I started up, and beheld a radiant form rise  <seg xml:id="C17_app139-f1831">from among the trees.</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app140-f1831">*<note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3_note1">* The moon.</note>
                        </seg> I gazed with a kind of  <seg xml:id="C17_app142-f1831">wonder.</seg> It moved  <seg xml:id="C17_app144-f1831">slowly,</seg> but it enlightened my  <seg xml:id="C17_app146-f1831">path;</seg> and I again went out in search of berries. I was still  <seg xml:id="C17_app148-f1831">cold,</seg> when  <seg xml:id="C17_app150-f1831">under one of the trees I found a huge</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app151-f1831">cloak,</seg> with which  <seg xml:id="C17_app153-f1831">I</seg> covered myself, and sat down  <seg xml:id="C17_app155-f1831">upon</seg> the ground. No distinct ideas occupied my  <seg xml:id="C17_app157-f1831">mind;</seg> all was  <seg xml:id="C17_app159-f1831">confused.</seg> I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app161-f1831">light, and</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app162-f1831">hunger,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app164-f1831">thirst,</seg> and darkness; innumerable sounds rung in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app166-f1831">ears,</seg> and on all sides various scents saluted  <seg xml:id="C17_app168-f1831">me:</seg> the only object that I could distinguish was the  <seg xml:id="C17_app170-f1831">bright moon,</seg> and I fixed my eyes   <seg xml:id="C17_app173-f1831">on</seg> that with pleasure.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p4">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__F"> “Several</seg> changes of day and night  <seg xml:id="C17_app177-f1831">passed,</seg> and the orb of night had greatly  <seg xml:id="C17_app179-f1831">lessened,</seg> when I began to distinguish my sensations  <seg xml:id="C17_app181-f1831">from each</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app182-f1831">other.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app184-f1831">gradually saw plainly</seg> the clear stream that supplied me with   <seg xml:id="C17_app186-f1831">drink,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app188-f1831">trees that</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app189-f1831">shaded</seg> me with their foliage. I was delighted when I first discovered that a pleasant   <seg xml:id="C17_app191-f1831">sound,</seg> which often   <seg xml:id="C17_app194-f1831">saluted my</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app195-f1831">ears,</seg> proceeded from the throats of  <seg xml:id="C17_app197-f1831">the little</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app198-f1831">winged</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app199-f1831">animals</seg> who  <seg xml:id="C17_app201-f1831">had</seg> often intercepted the light from my eyes. I began also to  <seg xml:id="C17_app203-f1831">observe,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app205-f1831">greater</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app206-f1831">accuracy,</seg> the forms that surrounded  <seg xml:id="C17_app208-f1831">me,</seg> and to perceive the boundaries of the radiant  <seg xml:id="C17_app210-f1831">roof of</seg> light which  <seg xml:id="C17_app212-f1831">canopied</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app213-f1831">me. Sometimes</seg> I tried to imitate the pleasant songs of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app216-f1831">birds,</seg> but was  <seg xml:id="C17_app218-f1831">unable.</seg> Sometimes I  <seg xml:id="C17_app220-f1831">wished to express my sensations in my own</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app221-f1831">mode,</seg> but the uncouth and   <seg xml:id="C17_app224-f1831">inarticulate sounds</seg> which broke from me   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__I">frightened me into silence again. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p5">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__F">
               </seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app228-f1831">“The</seg> moon had  <seg xml:id="C17_app230-f1831">disappeared</seg> from the night,  <seg xml:id="C17_app232-f1831">and again,</seg>
                        <pb xml:id="F1831_v_104" n="88"/>with a lessened <seg xml:id="C17_app234-f1831">form,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app235-f1831">showed</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app236-f1831">itself,</seg> while I still remained in the forest. My  <seg xml:id="C17_app238-f1831">sensations</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app239-f1831">had,</seg> by this  <seg xml:id="C17_app241-f1831">time,</seg> become  <seg xml:id="C17_app243-f1831">distinct,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app245-f1831">my mind</seg> received every day   <seg xml:id="C17_app247-f1831">additional</seg> ideas. My eyes became accustomed to the   <seg xml:id="C17_app250-f1831">light,</seg> and to perceive objects in their right forms; I  <seg xml:id="C17_app252-f1831">distinguished</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app254-f1831">insect from the herb,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app255-f1831">and,</seg> by  <seg xml:id="C17_app257-f1831">degrees,</seg> one herb from  <seg xml:id="C17_app259-f1831">another.</seg> I found that the sparrow uttered none but harsh  <seg xml:id="C17_app261-f1831">notes,</seg> whilst  <seg xml:id="C17_app263-f1831">those of</seg> the blackbird   <seg xml:id="C17_app265-f1831">and thrush</seg> were sweet and enticing.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p6">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__F"> “One day,</seg> when I was oppressed by  <seg xml:id="C17_app269-f1831">cold,</seg> I found a fire  <seg xml:id="C17_app271-f1831">which</seg> had been left by some wandering  <seg xml:id="C17_app273-f1831">beggars,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app275-f1831">overcome</seg> with delight  <seg xml:id="C17_app277-f1831">at the warmth</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app278-f1831">I</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app279-f1831">experienced</seg> from it. In my joy I thrust my hand into the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app281-f1831">embers,</seg> but quickly drew it  <seg xml:id="C17_app283-f1831">out again</seg> with a cry  <seg xml:id="C17_app285-f1831">of</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app286-f1831">pain.</seg> How strange, I thought, that the same cause should  <seg xml:id="C17_app288-f1831">produce such</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app289-f1831">opposite</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app290-f1831">effects! I</seg> examined the materials of the fire, and to my joy found it to be  <seg xml:id="C17_app292-f1831">composed of wood.</seg> I quickly collected some  <seg xml:id="C17_app294-f1831">branches;</seg> but they were  <seg xml:id="C17_app296-f1831">wet,</seg> and would not burn. I was pained at  <seg xml:id="C17_app298-f1831">this,</seg> and sat still watching the  <seg xml:id="C17_app300-f1831">operation</seg> of the fire. The wet wood  <seg xml:id="C17_app302-f1831">which</seg> I had placed near the heat  <seg xml:id="C17_app304-f1831">dried,</seg> and itself   <seg xml:id="C17_app306-f1831">became</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app307-f1831">inflamed.</seg> I reflected on   <seg xml:id="C17_app309-f1831">this; and,</seg> by touching the various  <seg xml:id="C17_app311-f1831">branches,</seg> I discovered the  <seg xml:id="C17_app313-f1831">cause,</seg> and busied myself in  <seg xml:id="C17_app315-f1831">collecting</seg> a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app317-f1831">quantity</seg> of   <seg xml:id="C17_app319-f1831">wood,</seg> that I might dry  <seg xml:id="C17_app321-f1831">it,</seg> and have a  <seg xml:id="C17_app323-f1831">plentiful supply</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app324-f1831">of fire.</seg> When night came   <seg xml:id="C17_app326-f1831">on,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app328-f1831">brought sleep with it ,</seg> I was in the greatest fear lest my fire should be  <seg xml:id="C17_app330-f1831">extinguished.</seg> I covered it carefully with  <seg xml:id="C17_app332-f1831">dry wood and</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app333-f1831">leaves,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app335-f1831">placed</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app336-f1831">wet branches</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app337-f1831">upon it;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app339-f1831">then,</seg> spreading my  <seg xml:id="C17_app341-f1831">cloak,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app343-f1831">lay</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app345-f1831">ground,</seg> and sunk into sleep.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p7">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was morning when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app349-f1831">awoke,</seg> and my first care was to visit the  <seg xml:id="C17_app351-f1831">fire. I</seg> uncovered  <seg xml:id="C17_app353-f1831">it,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app355-f1831">a gentle breeze quickly fanned it into a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app356-f1831">flame.</seg> I observed this  <seg xml:id="C17_app358-f1831">also,</seg> and contrived a fan of  <seg xml:id="C17_app360-f1831">branches,</seg> which roused the embers when  <seg xml:id="C17_app362-f1831">they</seg> were nearly extinguished. When night  <seg xml:id="C17_app364-f1831">came</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app365-f1831">again,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app367-f1831">found,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app369-f1831">pleasure,</seg> that the fire gave light as well as  <seg xml:id="C17_app371-f1831">heat;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app373-f1831">that</seg> the discovery of this element was useful to me  <seg xml:id="C17_app375-f1831">in my</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app376-f1831">food;</seg> for I found some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app378-f1831">the</seg> offals that the travellers had left had been  <seg xml:id="C17_app380-f1831">roasted,</seg> and tasted much more savoury than the berries I  <seg xml:id="C17_app382-f1831">gathered from the trees.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app384-f1831">tried, therefore,</seg> to dress my food in the same manner, placing  <seg xml:id="C17_app386-f1831">it</seg> on the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app388-f1831">embers.</seg> I found that the berries <pb xml:id="F1831_v_105" n="89"/>were spoiled by this <seg xml:id="C17_app390-f1831">operation,</seg> and the nuts  <seg xml:id="C17_app392-f1831">and roots</seg> much improved.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p8">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__F"> “Food, however,</seg> became  <seg xml:id="C17_app396-f1831">scarce;</seg> and I often spent  <seg xml:id="C17_app398-f1831">the whole</seg> day searching in vain for a few acorns to assuage the pangs of hunger. When I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app400-f1831">this, I</seg> resolved to quit the place  <seg xml:id="C17_app402-f1831">that</seg> I had hitherto  <seg xml:id="C17_app404-f1831">inhabited,</seg> to seek for  <seg xml:id="C17_app406-f1831">one</seg> where the few wants I experienced would be more easily satisfied. In this   <seg xml:id="C17_app408-f1831">emigration,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app410-f1831">exceedingly</seg> lamented the loss of   <seg xml:id="C17_app412-f1831">the fire which I</seg> had obtained  <seg xml:id="C17_app414-f1831">through accident,</seg> and knew not how to  <seg xml:id="C17_app416-f1831">reproduce</seg> it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app418-f1831">I gave several hours to the</seg> serious consideration  <seg xml:id="C17_app420-f1831">of this difficulty;</seg> but I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app422-f1831">relinquish all</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app423-f1831">attempt</seg> to supply  <seg xml:id="C17_app425-f1831">it; and, wrapping</seg> myself up in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app427-f1831">cloak,</seg> I struck across the wood towards the setting  <seg xml:id="C17_app429-f1831">sun.</seg> I passed three days in these  <seg xml:id="C17_app431-f1831">rambles,</seg> and at length discovered the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app433-f1831">country.</seg> A great fall of snow had taken place the night  <seg xml:id="C17_app435-f1831">before,</seg> and the fields were of one  <seg xml:id="C17_app437-f1831">uniform white;</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app439-f1831">appearance</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C17_app441-f1831">disconsolate,</seg> and I found my feet chilled by the cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app443-f1831">damp</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app444-f1831">substance that covered the</seg>
                        <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__I">ground. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p9">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was about seven in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app447-f1831">morning,</seg> and I longed to obtain food and  <seg xml:id="C17_app449-f1831">shelter;</seg> at length I perceived  <seg xml:id="C17_app451-f1831">a small</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app452-f1831">hut, on a rising ground,</seg> which had  <seg xml:id="C17_app454-f1831">doubtless been built for the convenience of</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app455-f1831">some</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app456-f1831">shepherd.</seg> This was a new sight to  <seg xml:id="C17_app458-f1831">me;</seg> and I examined the  <seg xml:id="C17_app460-f1831">structure</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app461-f1831">with great curiosity.</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app462-f1831">Finding the door</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app463-f1831">open,</seg> I entered. An old man sat  <seg xml:id="C17_app465-f1831">in it, near a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app466-f1831">fire,</seg> over  <seg xml:id="C17_app468-f1831">which he was preparing his</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app469-f1831">breakfast.</seg> He turned  <seg xml:id="C17_app471-f1831">on hearing a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app472-f1831">noise; and,</seg> perceiving  <seg xml:id="C17_app474-f1831">me,</seg> shrieked  <seg xml:id="C17_app476-f1831">loudly, and, quitting</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app478-f1831">hut,</seg> ran across the fields with a speed  <seg xml:id="C17_app480-f1831">of which his debilitated form hardly appeared</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app481-f1831">capable. His appearance, different from any I had ever before seen, and</seg> his  <seg xml:id="C17_app483-f1831">flight,</seg> somewhat surprised  <seg xml:id="C17_app485-f1831">me.</seg> But I was  <seg xml:id="C17_app487-f1831">enchanted by</seg> the appearance of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app489-f1831">hut:</seg> here the snow and rain could not  <seg xml:id="C17_app491-f1831">penetrate;</seg> the ground was  <seg xml:id="C17_app493-f1831">dry;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app495-f1831">presented</seg> to me then as   <seg xml:id="C17_app497-f1831">exquisite</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app498-f1831">and divine</seg> a retreat as  <seg xml:id="C17_app500-f1831">Pandæmonium</seg> appeared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app502-f1831">dæmons</seg> of hell  <seg xml:id="C17_app504-f1831">after</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app505-f1831">their sufferings</seg> in the lake of fire. I greedily devoured the   <seg xml:id="C17_app508-f1831">remnants</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app510-f1831">shepherd’s breakfast,</seg> which consisted of bread, cheese,  <seg xml:id="C17_app512-f1831">milk,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app514-f1831">wine; the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app515-f1831">latter, however,</seg> I did not like.  <seg xml:id="C17_app517-f1831">Then,</seg> overcome by  <seg xml:id="C17_app519-f1831">fatigue,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app520-f1831">I lay</seg> down among some  <seg xml:id="C17_app522-f1831">straw,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app523-f1831">and</seg> fell asleep. </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p10">
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app525-f1831">“It</seg> was noon when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app527-f1831">awoke; and,</seg> allured by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app529-f1831">
                           <pb xml:id="F1831_v_106" n="90"/>warmth of</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app530-f1831">the sun, which shone brightly on the white ground,</seg> I determined to recommence my  <seg xml:id="C17_app532-f1831">travels; and,</seg> depositing the   <seg xml:id="C17_app535-f1831">remains</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app537-f1831">peasant’s</seg> breakfast in a wallet I found, I proceeded across the fields for several hours,  <seg xml:id="C17_app539-f1831">until</seg> at sunset I  <seg xml:id="C17_app541-f1831">arrived at</seg> a village. How miraculous did this   <seg xml:id="C17_app543-f1831">appear!</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app545-f1831">huts,</seg> the neater  <seg xml:id="C17_app547-f1831">cottages,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app549-f1831">stately houses,</seg> engaged my admiration by  <seg xml:id="C17_app551-f1831">turns.</seg> The vegetables in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app553-f1831">gardens,</seg> the milk and cheese that I saw placed at  <seg xml:id="C17_app555-f1831">the windows of some of the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app556-f1831">cottages,</seg> allured  <seg xml:id="C17_app558-f1831">my appetite.</seg> One of the best of these I  <seg xml:id="C17_app560-f1831">entered;</seg> but I had hardly placed my foot  <seg xml:id="C17_app562-f1831">within</seg> the   <seg xml:id="C17_app564-f1831">door,</seg> before the children  <seg xml:id="C17_app566-f1831">shrieked,</seg> and one of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app568-f1831">women</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app569-f1831">fainted.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app571-f1831">whole</seg> village was  <seg xml:id="C17_app573-f1831">roused;</seg> some  <seg xml:id="C17_app575-f1831">fled, some</seg> attacked  <seg xml:id="C17_app577-f1831">me, until,</seg> grievously bruised by  <seg xml:id="C17_app579-f1831">stones</seg> and   <seg xml:id="C17_app581-f1831">many other kinds of missile</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app582-f1831">weapons,</seg> I escaped to the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app584-f1831">country,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app585-f1831">and</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app586-f1831">fearfully</seg> took refuge in a low  <seg xml:id="C17_app588-f1831">hovel, quite bare,</seg> and making a wretched appearance after the  <seg xml:id="C17_app590-f1831">palaces</seg> I had beheld in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app592-f1831">village.</seg> This  <seg xml:id="C17_app594-f1831">hovel, however, joined</seg> a cottage of a neat and pleasant  <seg xml:id="C17_app596-f1831">appearance; but,</seg> after my late  <seg xml:id="C17_app599-f1831">dearly</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app600-f1831">bought </seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app601-f1831">experience,</seg> I dared not enter it. My place of refuge  <seg xml:id="C17_app603-f1831">was constructed of wood,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app604-f1831">but</seg> so   <seg xml:id="C17_app606-f1831">low,</seg> that I could with difficulty sit upright in it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app608-f1831">No</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app609-f1831">wood, however,</seg> was placed on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app611-f1831">earth,</seg> which formed  <seg xml:id="C17_app613-f1831">the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app614-f1831">floor,</seg> but it was  <seg xml:id="C17_app616-f1831">dry;</seg> and although the wind entered  <seg xml:id="C17_app618-f1831">it</seg> by innumerable  <seg xml:id="C17_app620-f1831">chinks,</seg> I found it an  <seg xml:id="C17_app622-f1831">agreeable asylum</seg> from the snow  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__I">and rain. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p11">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__F"> “Here then I retreated, and lay</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app625-f1831">down</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app626-f1831">happy to have found a shelter, however miserable, from the inclemency of the season,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app628-f1831">still more from the barbarity of man.</seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p12">
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app630-f1831">“As</seg> soon as morning  <seg xml:id="C17_app632-f1831">dawned,</seg> I crept from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app634-f1831">kennel,</seg> that I might view the adjacent  <seg xml:id="C17_app636-f1831">cottage,</seg> and discover if I could remain in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app638-f1831">habitation</seg> I had found. It was situated  <seg xml:id="C17_app640-f1831">against</seg> the back of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app642-f1831">cottage,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app644-f1831">surrounded</seg> on   <seg xml:id="C17_app646-f1831">the</seg> sides which were exposed by a   <seg xml:id="C17_app648-f1831">pig-sty</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app650-f1831">a clear</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app651-f1831">pool</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app653-f1831">water.</seg> One part was  <seg xml:id="C17_app655-f1831">open,</seg> and by that I had crept  <seg xml:id="C17_app657-f1831">in;</seg> but now  <seg xml:id="C17_app659-f1831">I</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app660-f1831">covered</seg> every crevice  <seg xml:id="C17_app662-f1831">by which I might be</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app663-f1831">perceived with stones and wood,</seg> yet in such a manner that I  <seg xml:id="C17_app665-f1831">might</seg> move  <seg xml:id="C17_app667-f1831">them</seg> on  <seg xml:id="C17_app669-f1831">occasion to pass</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app670-f1831">out:</seg> all the light I enjoyed came through the  <seg xml:id="C17_app672-f1831">sty,</seg> and that was  <seg xml:id="C17_app674-f1831">sufficient</seg> for me. </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p13">
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app676-f1831">“Having</seg> thus arranged my  <seg xml:id="C17_app678-f1831">dwelling, and</seg> carpeted it with clean straw, I  <seg xml:id="C17_app680-f1831">retired;</seg> for I saw the figure of a man  <seg xml:id="C17_app682-f1831">
                           <pb xml:id="F1831_v_107" n="91"/>at</seg> a   <seg xml:id="C17_app684-f1831">distance,</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app686-f1831">remembered</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app687-f1831">too well my treatment the night</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app688-f1831">before,</seg> to trust myself in his power. I had  <seg xml:id="C17_app690-f1831">first, however,</seg> provided for my sustenance for that  <seg xml:id="C17_app692-f1831">day,</seg> by a loaf of  <seg xml:id="C17_app694-f1831">coarse</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app695-f1831">bread,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app697-f1831">purloined,</seg> and a cup  <seg xml:id="C17_app699-f1831">with</seg> which I could   <seg xml:id="C17_app701-f1831">drink,</seg> more conveniently than from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app703-f1831">hand,</seg> of the pure water which  flowed by my   <seg xml:id="C17_app707-f1831">retreat. The floor</seg> was a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app709-f1831">raised,</seg> so that it was kept   <seg xml:id="C17_app712-f1831">perfectly</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app713-f1831">dry,</seg> and by its vicinity to the chimney  <seg xml:id="C17_app715-f1831">of the cottage it was tolerably warm.</seg>
                        <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p14">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__F"> “Being</seg> thus  <seg xml:id="C17_app718-f1831">provided,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app720-f1831">resolved</seg> to reside in this  <seg xml:id="C17_app722-f1831">hovel, until</seg> something should occur which might alter my determination. It was indeed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app724-f1831">paradise,</seg> compared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app726-f1831">bleak</seg> forest, my former residence,  <seg xml:id="C17_app728-f1831">the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app729-f1831">rain-dropping branches,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app731-f1831">dank</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app732-f1831">earth.</seg> I ate my breakfast with  <seg xml:id="C17_app734-f1831">pleasure,</seg> and was about to remove a plank to procure myself a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app736-f1831">water,</seg> when I heard a  <seg xml:id="C17_app738-f1831">step,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app739-f1831">and</seg> looking through a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app741-f1831">chink, I</seg> beheld a young  <seg xml:id="C17_app743-f1831">creature,</seg> with a pail on her  <seg xml:id="C17_app745-f1831">head,</seg> passing before my hovel. The girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app747-f1831">young,</seg> and of gentle  <seg xml:id="C17_app749-f1831">demeanour,</seg> unlike what I have since found cottagers and  <seg xml:id="C17_app751-f1831">farm-house</seg> servants to  <seg xml:id="C17_app753-f1831">be.</seg> Yet she was  <seg xml:id="C17_app755-f1831">meanly dressed,</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app757-f1831">coarse</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app758-f1831">blue</seg> petticoat and a linen jacket being her only   <seg xml:id="C17_app760-f1831">garb;</seg> her fair hair was  <seg xml:id="C17_app762-f1831">plaited,</seg> but not adorned; she looked  <seg xml:id="C17_app764-f1831">patient,</seg> yet sad.  <seg xml:id="C17_app766-f1831">I lost sight of her; and</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app768-f1831">about</seg> a quarter of an hour  <seg xml:id="C17_app770-f1831">she</seg> returned,  <seg xml:id="C17_app772-f1831">bearing the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app773-f1831">pail,</seg> which was now partly filled with milk. As she walked  <seg xml:id="C17_app775-f1831">along,</seg> seemingly incommoded by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app777-f1831">burden,</seg> a young man met  <seg xml:id="C17_app779-f1831">her,</seg> whose countenance expressed a deeper  <seg xml:id="C17_app781-f1831">despondence.</seg> Uttering a few  <seg xml:id="C17_app783-f1831">sounds</seg> with   <seg xml:id="C17_app785-f1831">an air of</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app786-f1831">melancholy,</seg> he took the pail from her  <seg xml:id="C17_app788-f1831">head,</seg> and bore it  <seg xml:id="C17_app790-f1831">to</seg> the cottage himself. She  <seg xml:id="C17_app792-f1831">followed,</seg> and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app794-f1831">disappeared.</seg> Presently I saw the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app796-f1831">again,</seg> with some tools in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app798-f1831">hand,</seg> cross the field  <seg xml:id="C17_app800-f1831">behind</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app802-f1831">cottage;</seg> and the girl was also  <seg xml:id="C17_app804-f1831">busied, sometimes</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app806-f1831">the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app807-f1831">house,</seg> and sometimes in the  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__I">yard. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p15">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__F"> “On examining</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C17_app811-f1831">dwelling,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app813-f1831">found</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app815-f1831">one of the windows</seg> of the cottage  <seg xml:id="C17_app817-f1831">had formerly occupied a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app818-f1831">part</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app820-f1831">it,</seg> but the panes had  <seg xml:id="C17_app822-f1831">been filled up with wood. In one of these was a small and</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app823-f1831">almost</seg> imperceptible  <seg xml:id="C17_app825-f1831">chink, through which</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app826-f1831">the eye could just</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app827-f1831">penetrate. Through</seg> this  <seg xml:id="C17_app829-f1831">crevice</seg> a small room was visible,  <seg xml:id="C17_app831-f1831">whitewashed</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app832-f1831">and</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app833-f1831">clean,</seg> but very bare of  <seg xml:id="C17_app835-f1831">furniture.</seg> In  <seg xml:id="C17_app837-f1831">one</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app838-f1831">corner,</seg> near a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app840-f1831">fire, sat</seg> an old  <seg xml:id="C17_app842-f1831">man,</seg> leaning his head on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app844-f1831">hands</seg> in a  <seg xml:id="C17_app846-f1831">disconsolate <pb xml:id="F1831_v_108" n="92"/>attitude.</seg> The young girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app848-f1831">occupied in arranging the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app849-f1831">cottage;</seg> but presently  <seg xml:id="C17_app851-f1831">she took</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app852-f1831">something</seg> out of  <seg xml:id="C17_app854-f1831">a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app855-f1831">drawer,</seg> which employed her  <seg xml:id="C17_app857-f1831">hands,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app859-f1831">she</seg> sat down beside  <seg xml:id="C17_app861-f1831">the old</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app862-f1831">man, who,</seg> taking up an  <seg xml:id="C17_app864-f1831">instrument,</seg> began to  <seg xml:id="C17_app866-f1831">play,</seg> and to produce  <seg xml:id="C17_app868-f1831">sounds</seg> sweeter than the voice of the thrush or  <seg xml:id="C17_app870-f1831">the</seg> nightingale.  <seg xml:id="C17_app872-f1831">It was a lovely</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app873-f1831">sight,</seg> even to  <seg xml:id="C17_app875-f1831">me,</seg> poor  <seg xml:id="C17_app877-f1831">wretch!</seg> who had never beheld aught beautiful before.  <seg xml:id="C17_app879-f1831">The</seg> silver   <seg xml:id="C17_app881-f1831">hair and</seg> benevolent countenance  <seg xml:id="C17_app883-f1831">of</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app884-f1831">the</seg> aged  <seg xml:id="C17_app886-f1831">cottager</seg> won my  <seg xml:id="C17_app888-f1831">reverence,</seg> while  <seg xml:id="C17_app890-f1831">the</seg> gentle manners of the girl enticed my love. He played a sweet mournful   <seg xml:id="C17_app892-f1831">air,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app894-f1831">perceived</seg> drew tears from the eyes of  <seg xml:id="C17_app896-f1831">his</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app897-f1831">amiable</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app898-f1831">companion,</seg> of which the old man took  <seg xml:id="C17_app900-f1831">no</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app901-f1831">notice, until</seg> she sobbed  <seg xml:id="C17_app903-f1831">audibly;</seg> he  <seg xml:id="C17_app905-f1831">then pronounced a few</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app906-f1831">sounds,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app908-f1831">fair creature,</seg> leaving her  <seg xml:id="C17_app910-f1831">work,</seg> knelt at his  <seg xml:id="C17_app912-f1831">feet.</seg> He  <seg xml:id="C17_app914-f1831">raised her,</seg> and smiled with such  <seg xml:id="C17_app916-f1831">kindness</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app917-f1831">and affection,</seg> that I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app919-f1831">sensations of a peculiar and overpowering nature:</seg> they were a  <seg xml:id="C17_app921-f1831">mixture of pain and</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app922-f1831">pleasure,</seg> such as I had never  <seg xml:id="C17_app924-f1831">before experienced,</seg> either from  <seg xml:id="C17_app926-f1831">hunger or cold,</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app927-f1831">warmth or</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app928-f1831">food;</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app930-f1831">withdrew</seg> from  <seg xml:id="C17_app932-f1831">the window,</seg> unable  <seg xml:id="C17_app934-f1831">to bear</seg> these  <seg xml:id="C17_app936-f1831">emotions.</seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p16">
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app938-f1831">“Soon</seg> after this the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app940-f1831">returned,</seg> bearing on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app942-f1831">shoulders</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app944-f1831">load of</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app945-f1831">wood.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app947-f1831">girl met him at the</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app948-f1831">door,</seg> helped to relieve him of his  <seg xml:id="C17_app950-f1831">burden, and,</seg> taking some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app952-f1831">the fuel</seg> into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app954-f1831">cottage,</seg> placed it on the fire;  <seg xml:id="C17_app956-f1831">then she and the youth went apart into a</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app957-f1831">nook</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app959-f1831">cottage,</seg> and he  <seg xml:id="C17_app961-f1831">showed</seg> her a large loaf and a piece of  <seg xml:id="C17_app963-f1831">cheese.</seg> She seemed  <seg xml:id="C17_app965-f1831">pleased,</seg> and went into the garden for  <seg xml:id="C17_app967-f1831">some</seg> roots and  <seg xml:id="C17_app969-f1831">plants,</seg> which she placed in  <seg xml:id="C17_app971-f1831">water,</seg> and then upon the  <seg xml:id="C17_app973-f1831">fire.</seg> She  <seg xml:id="C17_app975-f1831">afterwards</seg> continued her   <seg xml:id="C17_app977-f1831">work,</seg> whilst the young man went into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app979-f1831">garden,</seg> and appeared busily employed in digging and  <seg xml:id="C17_app981-f1831">pulling up</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app982-f1831">roots. After</seg> he had been employed thus about  <seg xml:id="C17_app984-f1831">an</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app985-f1831">hour,</seg> the young woman joined him, and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app987-f1831">entered</seg> the cottage  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__I">together. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p17">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__F"> “The</seg> old man  <seg xml:id="C17_app991-f1831">had,</seg> in the mean  <seg xml:id="C17_app993-f1831">time,</seg> been  <seg xml:id="C17_app995-f1831">pensive; but,</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app997-f1831">appearance</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app999-f1831">his</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1000-f1831">companions,</seg> he assumed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app1002-f1831">more</seg> cheerful air, and they sat down to eat.   <seg xml:id="C17_app1004-f1831">The</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1005-f1831">meal</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1006-f1831">was quickly</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1007-f1831">despatched.</seg> The young woman was again occupied in arranging the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1009-f1831">cottage;</seg> the old man walked before the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1011-f1831">cottage</seg> in the sun for a few   <seg xml:id="C17_app1014-f1831">minutes,</seg> leaning on the arm of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1016-f1831">youth.</seg> Nothing could exceed in beauty the contrast <pb xml:id="F1831_v_109" n="93"/>between these two <seg xml:id="C17_app1018-f1831">excellent</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1019-f1831">creatures.</seg> One was old, with silver hairs and a countenance beaming with  <seg xml:id="C17_app1021-f1831">benevolence</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1023-f1831">love:</seg> the younger was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1025-f1831">slight</seg> and graceful in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1027-f1831">figure,</seg> and his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1029-f1831">features</seg> were moulded with the finest  <seg xml:id="C17_app1031-f1831">symmetry;</seg> yet his eyes and attitude expressed the utmost sadness and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1033-f1831">despondency.</seg> The old man returned to the cottage; and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1035-f1831">youth,</seg> with tools different from those  <seg xml:id="C17_app1037-f1831">he had used in the morning, directed his steps across the</seg>
                        <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__I">fields. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p18">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__F"> “Night</seg> quickly shut  <seg xml:id="C17_app1040-f1831">in; but,</seg> to my extreme  <seg xml:id="C17_app1042-f1831">wonder,</seg> I found that the cottagers had a means of prolonging  <seg xml:id="C17_app1044-f1831">light</seg> by the use of  <seg xml:id="C17_app1046-f1831">tapers,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1048-f1831">delighted</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1050-f1831">find</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app1052-f1831">the</seg> setting of the sun did not put an end  <seg xml:id="C17_app1054-f1831">to the pleasure I experienced in watching</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1055-f1831">my human</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1056-f1831">neighbours. In</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1058-f1831">evening,</seg> the young girl and her companion were employed in various  <seg xml:id="C17_app1060-f1831">occupations</seg> which I did not   <seg xml:id="C17_app1063-f1831">understand;</seg> and the old man again took  <seg xml:id="C17_app1065-f1831">up the instrument</seg> which produced  <seg xml:id="C17_app1067-f1831">the</seg> divine sounds that had enchanted me in the morning.  <seg xml:id="C17_app1069-f1831">So soon as</seg> he had   <seg xml:id="C17_app1071-f1831">finished,</seg> the youth  <seg xml:id="C17_app1073-f1831">began,</seg> not to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1075-f1831">play,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C17_app1077-f1831">to</seg> utter   <seg xml:id="C17_app1079-f1831">sounds</seg>
                        <seg xml:id="C17_app1080-f1831">that</seg> were  <seg xml:id="C17_app1082-f1831">monotonous,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1084-f1831">neither resembling</seg> the harmony of the old   <seg xml:id="C17_app1086-f1831">man’s</seg> instrument  <seg xml:id="C17_app1088-f1831">nor</seg> the songs of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1090-f1831">birds:</seg> I since found that he read  <seg xml:id="C17_app1092-f1831">aloud,</seg> but at that time I knew nothing of the science of words or letters.   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                     </p>
                     <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p19">
                        <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__F"> “The family, after having been thus occupied for a short time,</seg> extinguished their  <seg xml:id="C17_app1098-f1831">lights,</seg> and retired, as I conjectured, to  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__I">rest. </seg>
                     </p>
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__F">
            </seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1101-f1831">
                        <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="11"/>
                     </seg>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </text>
         </TEI>
         <teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <fileDesc>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C17</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
                  <date>2023—</date>
                  <availability>
                     <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
                  </availability>
               </publicationStmt>
               <sourceDesc>
                  <p>Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing
                                    on  2023-05-28 13:45:47.345979 .</p>
                  <p>Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein
                                    Variorum spine on 2023-05-31T15:50:17.3557974-04:00.</p>
               </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
         </teiHeader>
         <fileDesc xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <titleStmt>
               <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C17</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
               <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
               <date>2023—</date>
               <availability>
                  <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
               </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <p>Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing
                                    on  2023-05-28 13:45:47.345979 .</p>
               <p>Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein
                                    Variorum spine on 2023-05-31T15:50:17.3557974-04:00.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
         <titleStmt xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C17</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <title xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C17</title>Bridge Phase 5:  Witness f1831, Collation unit C17
            <publicationStmt xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>
            <date>2023—</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <authority xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Frankenstein Variorum Project</authority>Frankenstein Variorum Project
               <date xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">2023—</date>2023—
               <availability xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>
         </availability>
         <licence xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                                        Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
            <sourceDesc xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <p>Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing
                                    on  2023-05-28 13:45:47.345979 .</p>
            <p>Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein
                                    Variorum spine on 2023-05-31T15:50:17.3557974-04:00.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
         <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing
                                    on  2023-05-28 13:45:47.345979 .</p>Produced from collation output prepared in batch file processing
                                    on  2023-05-28 13:45:47.345979 .
               <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein
                                    Variorum spine on 2023-05-31T15:50:17.3557974-04:00.</p>Edited to correct alignments and prepared for the Frankenstein
                                    Variorum spine on 2023-05-31T15:50:17.3557974-04:00.
      <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <body>
               <div type="collation">
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app2-f1831">
                     <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C17"/>
                  </seg>
                  <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="11"/>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app4-f1831">
                     <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER XI.<head ana="end"/>
                  </seg>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1"> “I<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1_hi1">T</hi> is with <seg xml:id="C17_app6-f1831">considerable</seg> difficulty that I remember the  <seg xml:id="C17_app8-f1831">original</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app9-f1831">era</seg> of my  <seg xml:id="C17_app11-f1831">being:</seg> all the events of that period appear confused and indistinct.  <seg xml:id="C17_app13-f1831">A strange</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app14-f1831">multiplicity of sensations</seg> seized  <seg xml:id="C17_app16-f1831">me, and</seg> I saw,  <seg xml:id="C17_app18-f1831">felt, heard,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app20-f1831">smelt,</seg> at the same  <seg xml:id="C17_app22-f1831">time;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app24-f1831">was, indeed,</seg> a long time before I learned to distinguish between the  <seg xml:id="C17_app26-f1831">operations of my various senses. By</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app27-f1831">degrees,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app29-f1831">remember,</seg> a stronger light pressed upon my  <seg xml:id="C17_app31-f1831">nerves,</seg> so that I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app33-f1831">shut</seg> my eyes. Darkness then came over  <seg xml:id="C17_app35-f1831">me,</seg> and troubled  <seg xml:id="C17_app37-f1831">me;</seg> but hardly had I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app41-f1831">this, when, by</seg> opening my  <seg xml:id="C17_app43-f1831">eyes,</seg> as I now  <seg xml:id="C17_app45-f1831">suppose,</seg> the light poured in upon me  <seg xml:id="C17_app47-f1831">again.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app49-f1831">walked, and,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app51-f1831">believe,</seg> descended; but  <seg xml:id="C17_app53-f1831">I</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app54-f1831">presently</seg> found a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app56-f1831">alteration</seg> in my   <seg xml:id="C17_app58-f1831">sensations. Before,</seg> dark  <seg xml:id="C17_app60-f1831">and</seg> opaque bodies had surrounded me, impervious to my touch or  <seg xml:id="C17_app62-f1831">sight; but</seg> I now found that I could wander on at  <seg xml:id="C17_app64-f1831">liberty,</seg> with no obstacles which I could not either surmount or  <seg xml:id="C17_app66-f1831">avoid.</seg> The light  <seg xml:id="C17_app68-f1831">became</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app69-f1831">more</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app70-f1831">and</seg> more  <seg xml:id="C17_app72-f1831">oppressive</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app74-f1831">me; and,</seg> the heat wearying me as I  <seg xml:id="C17_app76-f1831">walked,</seg> I sought a place where I could  <seg xml:id="C17_app78-f1831">receive</seg> shade. This was the forest near  <seg xml:id="C17_app80-f1831">Ingolstadt; and</seg> here  <seg xml:id="C17_app82-f1831">I lay</seg> by the side of a brook  <seg xml:id="C17_app84-f1831">resting from my</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app85-f1831">fatigue, until</seg> I felt tormented by hunger and thirst. This roused me from my nearly dormant  <seg xml:id="C17_app87-f1831">state,</seg> and I ate some berries which I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app89-f1831">hanging</seg> on the   <seg xml:id="C17_app91-f1831">trees,</seg> or lying on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app93-f1831">
                        <pb xml:id="F1831_v_103" n="87"/>ground.</seg> I slaked my thirst  <seg xml:id="C17_app95-f1831">at</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app97-f1831">brook;</seg> and then  <seg xml:id="C17_app99-f1831">lying</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app100-f1831">down,</seg> was overcome by  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p2">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was dark when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app104-f1831">awoke;</seg> I felt cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app106-f1831">also,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app108-f1831">half-frightened,</seg> as it were  <seg xml:id="C17_app110-f1831">instinctively,</seg> finding myself so desolate. Before I had quitted your  <seg xml:id="C17_app112-f1831">apartment,</seg> on a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app114-f1831">cold,</seg> I had covered  <seg xml:id="C17_app116-f1831">myself</seg> with some  <seg xml:id="C17_app118-f1831">clothes;</seg> but these were  <seg xml:id="C17_app120-f1831">insufficient</seg> to secure me from the  <seg xml:id="C17_app122-f1831">dews of night. I was a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app123-f1831">poor, helpless,</seg> miserable  <seg xml:id="C17_app125-f1831">wretch; I knew,</seg> and could  <seg xml:id="C17_app127-f1831">distinguish, nothing;</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app128-f1831">but</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app129-f1831">feeling</seg> pain invade me on all   <seg xml:id="C17_app131-f1831">sides,</seg> I sat down and wept. </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3">
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app133-f1831">“Soon</seg> a gentle light stole over the  <seg xml:id="C17_app135-f1831">heavens,</seg> and gave me a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app137-f1831">pleasure.</seg> I started up, and beheld a radiant form rise  <seg xml:id="C17_app139-f1831">from among the trees.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app140-f1831">*<note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3_note1">* The moon.</note>
                     </seg> I gazed with a kind of  <seg xml:id="C17_app142-f1831">wonder.</seg> It moved  <seg xml:id="C17_app144-f1831">slowly,</seg> but it enlightened my  <seg xml:id="C17_app146-f1831">path;</seg> and I again went out in search of berries. I was still  <seg xml:id="C17_app148-f1831">cold,</seg> when  <seg xml:id="C17_app150-f1831">under one of the trees I found a huge</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app151-f1831">cloak,</seg> with which  <seg xml:id="C17_app153-f1831">I</seg> covered myself, and sat down  <seg xml:id="C17_app155-f1831">upon</seg> the ground. No distinct ideas occupied my  <seg xml:id="C17_app157-f1831">mind;</seg> all was  <seg xml:id="C17_app159-f1831">confused.</seg> I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app161-f1831">light, and</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app162-f1831">hunger,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app164-f1831">thirst,</seg> and darkness; innumerable sounds rung in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app166-f1831">ears,</seg> and on all sides various scents saluted  <seg xml:id="C17_app168-f1831">me:</seg> the only object that I could distinguish was the  <seg xml:id="C17_app170-f1831">bright moon,</seg> and I fixed my eyes   <seg xml:id="C17_app173-f1831">on</seg> that with pleasure.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p4">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__F"> “Several</seg> changes of day and night  <seg xml:id="C17_app177-f1831">passed,</seg> and the orb of night had greatly  <seg xml:id="C17_app179-f1831">lessened,</seg> when I began to distinguish my sensations  <seg xml:id="C17_app181-f1831">from each</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app182-f1831">other.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app184-f1831">gradually saw plainly</seg> the clear stream that supplied me with   <seg xml:id="C17_app186-f1831">drink,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app188-f1831">trees that</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app189-f1831">shaded</seg> me with their foliage. I was delighted when I first discovered that a pleasant   <seg xml:id="C17_app191-f1831">sound,</seg> which often   <seg xml:id="C17_app194-f1831">saluted my</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app195-f1831">ears,</seg> proceeded from the throats of  <seg xml:id="C17_app197-f1831">the little</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app198-f1831">winged</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app199-f1831">animals</seg> who  <seg xml:id="C17_app201-f1831">had</seg> often intercepted the light from my eyes. I began also to  <seg xml:id="C17_app203-f1831">observe,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app205-f1831">greater</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app206-f1831">accuracy,</seg> the forms that surrounded  <seg xml:id="C17_app208-f1831">me,</seg> and to perceive the boundaries of the radiant  <seg xml:id="C17_app210-f1831">roof of</seg> light which  <seg xml:id="C17_app212-f1831">canopied</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app213-f1831">me. Sometimes</seg> I tried to imitate the pleasant songs of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app216-f1831">birds,</seg> but was  <seg xml:id="C17_app218-f1831">unable.</seg> Sometimes I  <seg xml:id="C17_app220-f1831">wished to express my sensations in my own</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app221-f1831">mode,</seg> but the uncouth and   <seg xml:id="C17_app224-f1831">inarticulate sounds</seg> which broke from me   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__I">frightened me into silence again. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p5">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__F">
               </seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app228-f1831">“The</seg> moon had  <seg xml:id="C17_app230-f1831">disappeared</seg> from the night,  <seg xml:id="C17_app232-f1831">and again,</seg>
                     <pb xml:id="F1831_v_104" n="88"/>with a lessened <seg xml:id="C17_app234-f1831">form,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app235-f1831">showed</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app236-f1831">itself,</seg> while I still remained in the forest. My  <seg xml:id="C17_app238-f1831">sensations</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app239-f1831">had,</seg> by this  <seg xml:id="C17_app241-f1831">time,</seg> become  <seg xml:id="C17_app243-f1831">distinct,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app245-f1831">my mind</seg> received every day   <seg xml:id="C17_app247-f1831">additional</seg> ideas. My eyes became accustomed to the   <seg xml:id="C17_app250-f1831">light,</seg> and to perceive objects in their right forms; I  <seg xml:id="C17_app252-f1831">distinguished</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app254-f1831">insect from the herb,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app255-f1831">and,</seg> by  <seg xml:id="C17_app257-f1831">degrees,</seg> one herb from  <seg xml:id="C17_app259-f1831">another.</seg> I found that the sparrow uttered none but harsh  <seg xml:id="C17_app261-f1831">notes,</seg> whilst  <seg xml:id="C17_app263-f1831">those of</seg> the blackbird   <seg xml:id="C17_app265-f1831">and thrush</seg> were sweet and enticing.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p6">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__F"> “One day,</seg> when I was oppressed by  <seg xml:id="C17_app269-f1831">cold,</seg> I found a fire  <seg xml:id="C17_app271-f1831">which</seg> had been left by some wandering  <seg xml:id="C17_app273-f1831">beggars,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app275-f1831">overcome</seg> with delight  <seg xml:id="C17_app277-f1831">at the warmth</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app278-f1831">I</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app279-f1831">experienced</seg> from it. In my joy I thrust my hand into the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app281-f1831">embers,</seg> but quickly drew it  <seg xml:id="C17_app283-f1831">out again</seg> with a cry  <seg xml:id="C17_app285-f1831">of</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app286-f1831">pain.</seg> How strange, I thought, that the same cause should  <seg xml:id="C17_app288-f1831">produce such</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app289-f1831">opposite</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app290-f1831">effects! I</seg> examined the materials of the fire, and to my joy found it to be  <seg xml:id="C17_app292-f1831">composed of wood.</seg> I quickly collected some  <seg xml:id="C17_app294-f1831">branches;</seg> but they were  <seg xml:id="C17_app296-f1831">wet,</seg> and would not burn. I was pained at  <seg xml:id="C17_app298-f1831">this,</seg> and sat still watching the  <seg xml:id="C17_app300-f1831">operation</seg> of the fire. The wet wood  <seg xml:id="C17_app302-f1831">which</seg> I had placed near the heat  <seg xml:id="C17_app304-f1831">dried,</seg> and itself   <seg xml:id="C17_app306-f1831">became</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app307-f1831">inflamed.</seg> I reflected on   <seg xml:id="C17_app309-f1831">this; and,</seg> by touching the various  <seg xml:id="C17_app311-f1831">branches,</seg> I discovered the  <seg xml:id="C17_app313-f1831">cause,</seg> and busied myself in  <seg xml:id="C17_app315-f1831">collecting</seg> a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app317-f1831">quantity</seg> of   <seg xml:id="C17_app319-f1831">wood,</seg> that I might dry  <seg xml:id="C17_app321-f1831">it,</seg> and have a  <seg xml:id="C17_app323-f1831">plentiful supply</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app324-f1831">of fire.</seg> When night came   <seg xml:id="C17_app326-f1831">on,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app328-f1831">brought sleep with it ,</seg> I was in the greatest fear lest my fire should be  <seg xml:id="C17_app330-f1831">extinguished.</seg> I covered it carefully with  <seg xml:id="C17_app332-f1831">dry wood and</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app333-f1831">leaves,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app335-f1831">placed</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app336-f1831">wet branches</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app337-f1831">upon it;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app339-f1831">then,</seg> spreading my  <seg xml:id="C17_app341-f1831">cloak,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app343-f1831">lay</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app345-f1831">ground,</seg> and sunk into sleep.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p7">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was morning when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app349-f1831">awoke,</seg> and my first care was to visit the  <seg xml:id="C17_app351-f1831">fire. I</seg> uncovered  <seg xml:id="C17_app353-f1831">it,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app355-f1831">a gentle breeze quickly fanned it into a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app356-f1831">flame.</seg> I observed this  <seg xml:id="C17_app358-f1831">also,</seg> and contrived a fan of  <seg xml:id="C17_app360-f1831">branches,</seg> which roused the embers when  <seg xml:id="C17_app362-f1831">they</seg> were nearly extinguished. When night  <seg xml:id="C17_app364-f1831">came</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app365-f1831">again,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app367-f1831">found,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app369-f1831">pleasure,</seg> that the fire gave light as well as  <seg xml:id="C17_app371-f1831">heat;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app373-f1831">that</seg> the discovery of this element was useful to me  <seg xml:id="C17_app375-f1831">in my</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app376-f1831">food;</seg> for I found some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app378-f1831">the</seg> offals that the travellers had left had been  <seg xml:id="C17_app380-f1831">roasted,</seg> and tasted much more savoury than the berries I  <seg xml:id="C17_app382-f1831">gathered from the trees.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app384-f1831">tried, therefore,</seg> to dress my food in the same manner, placing  <seg xml:id="C17_app386-f1831">it</seg> on the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app388-f1831">embers.</seg> I found that the berries <pb xml:id="F1831_v_105" n="89"/>were spoiled by this <seg xml:id="C17_app390-f1831">operation,</seg> and the nuts  <seg xml:id="C17_app392-f1831">and roots</seg> much improved.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p8">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__F"> “Food, however,</seg> became  <seg xml:id="C17_app396-f1831">scarce;</seg> and I often spent  <seg xml:id="C17_app398-f1831">the whole</seg> day searching in vain for a few acorns to assuage the pangs of hunger. When I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app400-f1831">this, I</seg> resolved to quit the place  <seg xml:id="C17_app402-f1831">that</seg> I had hitherto  <seg xml:id="C17_app404-f1831">inhabited,</seg> to seek for  <seg xml:id="C17_app406-f1831">one</seg> where the few wants I experienced would be more easily satisfied. In this   <seg xml:id="C17_app408-f1831">emigration,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app410-f1831">exceedingly</seg> lamented the loss of   <seg xml:id="C17_app412-f1831">the fire which I</seg> had obtained  <seg xml:id="C17_app414-f1831">through accident,</seg> and knew not how to  <seg xml:id="C17_app416-f1831">reproduce</seg> it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app418-f1831">I gave several hours to the</seg> serious consideration  <seg xml:id="C17_app420-f1831">of this difficulty;</seg> but I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app422-f1831">relinquish all</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app423-f1831">attempt</seg> to supply  <seg xml:id="C17_app425-f1831">it; and, wrapping</seg> myself up in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app427-f1831">cloak,</seg> I struck across the wood towards the setting  <seg xml:id="C17_app429-f1831">sun.</seg> I passed three days in these  <seg xml:id="C17_app431-f1831">rambles,</seg> and at length discovered the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app433-f1831">country.</seg> A great fall of snow had taken place the night  <seg xml:id="C17_app435-f1831">before,</seg> and the fields were of one  <seg xml:id="C17_app437-f1831">uniform white;</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app439-f1831">appearance</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C17_app441-f1831">disconsolate,</seg> and I found my feet chilled by the cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app443-f1831">damp</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app444-f1831">substance that covered the</seg>
                     <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__I">ground. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p9">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was about seven in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app447-f1831">morning,</seg> and I longed to obtain food and  <seg xml:id="C17_app449-f1831">shelter;</seg> at length I perceived  <seg xml:id="C17_app451-f1831">a small</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app452-f1831">hut, on a rising ground,</seg> which had  <seg xml:id="C17_app454-f1831">doubtless been built for the convenience of</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app455-f1831">some</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app456-f1831">shepherd.</seg> This was a new sight to  <seg xml:id="C17_app458-f1831">me;</seg> and I examined the  <seg xml:id="C17_app460-f1831">structure</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app461-f1831">with great curiosity.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app462-f1831">Finding the door</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app463-f1831">open,</seg> I entered. An old man sat  <seg xml:id="C17_app465-f1831">in it, near a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app466-f1831">fire,</seg> over  <seg xml:id="C17_app468-f1831">which he was preparing his</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app469-f1831">breakfast.</seg> He turned  <seg xml:id="C17_app471-f1831">on hearing a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app472-f1831">noise; and,</seg> perceiving  <seg xml:id="C17_app474-f1831">me,</seg> shrieked  <seg xml:id="C17_app476-f1831">loudly, and, quitting</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app478-f1831">hut,</seg> ran across the fields with a speed  <seg xml:id="C17_app480-f1831">of which his debilitated form hardly appeared</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app481-f1831">capable. His appearance, different from any I had ever before seen, and</seg> his  <seg xml:id="C17_app483-f1831">flight,</seg> somewhat surprised  <seg xml:id="C17_app485-f1831">me.</seg> But I was  <seg xml:id="C17_app487-f1831">enchanted by</seg> the appearance of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app489-f1831">hut:</seg> here the snow and rain could not  <seg xml:id="C17_app491-f1831">penetrate;</seg> the ground was  <seg xml:id="C17_app493-f1831">dry;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app495-f1831">presented</seg> to me then as   <seg xml:id="C17_app497-f1831">exquisite</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app498-f1831">and divine</seg> a retreat as  <seg xml:id="C17_app500-f1831">Pandæmonium</seg> appeared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app502-f1831">dæmons</seg> of hell  <seg xml:id="C17_app504-f1831">after</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app505-f1831">their sufferings</seg> in the lake of fire. I greedily devoured the   <seg xml:id="C17_app508-f1831">remnants</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app510-f1831">shepherd’s breakfast,</seg> which consisted of bread, cheese,  <seg xml:id="C17_app512-f1831">milk,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app514-f1831">wine; the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app515-f1831">latter, however,</seg> I did not like.  <seg xml:id="C17_app517-f1831">Then,</seg> overcome by  <seg xml:id="C17_app519-f1831">fatigue,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app520-f1831">I lay</seg> down among some  <seg xml:id="C17_app522-f1831">straw,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app523-f1831">and</seg> fell asleep. </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p10">
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app525-f1831">“It</seg> was noon when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app527-f1831">awoke; and,</seg> allured by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app529-f1831">
                        <pb xml:id="F1831_v_106" n="90"/>warmth of</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app530-f1831">the sun, which shone brightly on the white ground,</seg> I determined to recommence my  <seg xml:id="C17_app532-f1831">travels; and,</seg> depositing the   <seg xml:id="C17_app535-f1831">remains</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app537-f1831">peasant’s</seg> breakfast in a wallet I found, I proceeded across the fields for several hours,  <seg xml:id="C17_app539-f1831">until</seg> at sunset I  <seg xml:id="C17_app541-f1831">arrived at</seg> a village. How miraculous did this   <seg xml:id="C17_app543-f1831">appear!</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app545-f1831">huts,</seg> the neater  <seg xml:id="C17_app547-f1831">cottages,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app549-f1831">stately houses,</seg> engaged my admiration by  <seg xml:id="C17_app551-f1831">turns.</seg> The vegetables in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app553-f1831">gardens,</seg> the milk and cheese that I saw placed at  <seg xml:id="C17_app555-f1831">the windows of some of the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app556-f1831">cottages,</seg> allured  <seg xml:id="C17_app558-f1831">my appetite.</seg> One of the best of these I  <seg xml:id="C17_app560-f1831">entered;</seg> but I had hardly placed my foot  <seg xml:id="C17_app562-f1831">within</seg> the   <seg xml:id="C17_app564-f1831">door,</seg> before the children  <seg xml:id="C17_app566-f1831">shrieked,</seg> and one of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app568-f1831">women</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app569-f1831">fainted.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app571-f1831">whole</seg> village was  <seg xml:id="C17_app573-f1831">roused;</seg> some  <seg xml:id="C17_app575-f1831">fled, some</seg> attacked  <seg xml:id="C17_app577-f1831">me, until,</seg> grievously bruised by  <seg xml:id="C17_app579-f1831">stones</seg> and   <seg xml:id="C17_app581-f1831">many other kinds of missile</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app582-f1831">weapons,</seg> I escaped to the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app584-f1831">country,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app585-f1831">and</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app586-f1831">fearfully</seg> took refuge in a low  <seg xml:id="C17_app588-f1831">hovel, quite bare,</seg> and making a wretched appearance after the  <seg xml:id="C17_app590-f1831">palaces</seg> I had beheld in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app592-f1831">village.</seg> This  <seg xml:id="C17_app594-f1831">hovel, however, joined</seg> a cottage of a neat and pleasant  <seg xml:id="C17_app596-f1831">appearance; but,</seg> after my late  <seg xml:id="C17_app599-f1831">dearly</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app600-f1831">bought </seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app601-f1831">experience,</seg> I dared not enter it. My place of refuge  <seg xml:id="C17_app603-f1831">was constructed of wood,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app604-f1831">but</seg> so   <seg xml:id="C17_app606-f1831">low,</seg> that I could with difficulty sit upright in it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app608-f1831">No</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app609-f1831">wood, however,</seg> was placed on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app611-f1831">earth,</seg> which formed  <seg xml:id="C17_app613-f1831">the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app614-f1831">floor,</seg> but it was  <seg xml:id="C17_app616-f1831">dry;</seg> and although the wind entered  <seg xml:id="C17_app618-f1831">it</seg> by innumerable  <seg xml:id="C17_app620-f1831">chinks,</seg> I found it an  <seg xml:id="C17_app622-f1831">agreeable asylum</seg> from the snow  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__I">and rain. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p11">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__F"> “Here then I retreated, and lay</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app625-f1831">down</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app626-f1831">happy to have found a shelter, however miserable, from the inclemency of the season,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app628-f1831">still more from the barbarity of man.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p12">
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app630-f1831">“As</seg> soon as morning  <seg xml:id="C17_app632-f1831">dawned,</seg> I crept from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app634-f1831">kennel,</seg> that I might view the adjacent  <seg xml:id="C17_app636-f1831">cottage,</seg> and discover if I could remain in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app638-f1831">habitation</seg> I had found. It was situated  <seg xml:id="C17_app640-f1831">against</seg> the back of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app642-f1831">cottage,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app644-f1831">surrounded</seg> on   <seg xml:id="C17_app646-f1831">the</seg> sides which were exposed by a   <seg xml:id="C17_app648-f1831">pig-sty</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app650-f1831">a clear</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app651-f1831">pool</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app653-f1831">water.</seg> One part was  <seg xml:id="C17_app655-f1831">open,</seg> and by that I had crept  <seg xml:id="C17_app657-f1831">in;</seg> but now  <seg xml:id="C17_app659-f1831">I</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app660-f1831">covered</seg> every crevice  <seg xml:id="C17_app662-f1831">by which I might be</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app663-f1831">perceived with stones and wood,</seg> yet in such a manner that I  <seg xml:id="C17_app665-f1831">might</seg> move  <seg xml:id="C17_app667-f1831">them</seg> on  <seg xml:id="C17_app669-f1831">occasion to pass</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app670-f1831">out:</seg> all the light I enjoyed came through the  <seg xml:id="C17_app672-f1831">sty,</seg> and that was  <seg xml:id="C17_app674-f1831">sufficient</seg> for me. </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p13">
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app676-f1831">“Having</seg> thus arranged my  <seg xml:id="C17_app678-f1831">dwelling, and</seg> carpeted it with clean straw, I  <seg xml:id="C17_app680-f1831">retired;</seg> for I saw the figure of a man  <seg xml:id="C17_app682-f1831">
                        <pb xml:id="F1831_v_107" n="91"/>at</seg> a   <seg xml:id="C17_app684-f1831">distance,</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app686-f1831">remembered</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app687-f1831">too well my treatment the night</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app688-f1831">before,</seg> to trust myself in his power. I had  <seg xml:id="C17_app690-f1831">first, however,</seg> provided for my sustenance for that  <seg xml:id="C17_app692-f1831">day,</seg> by a loaf of  <seg xml:id="C17_app694-f1831">coarse</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app695-f1831">bread,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app697-f1831">purloined,</seg> and a cup  <seg xml:id="C17_app699-f1831">with</seg> which I could   <seg xml:id="C17_app701-f1831">drink,</seg> more conveniently than from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app703-f1831">hand,</seg> of the pure water which  flowed by my   <seg xml:id="C17_app707-f1831">retreat. The floor</seg> was a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app709-f1831">raised,</seg> so that it was kept   <seg xml:id="C17_app712-f1831">perfectly</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app713-f1831">dry,</seg> and by its vicinity to the chimney  <seg xml:id="C17_app715-f1831">of the cottage it was tolerably warm.</seg>
                     <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p14">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__F"> “Being</seg> thus  <seg xml:id="C17_app718-f1831">provided,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app720-f1831">resolved</seg> to reside in this  <seg xml:id="C17_app722-f1831">hovel, until</seg> something should occur which might alter my determination. It was indeed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app724-f1831">paradise,</seg> compared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app726-f1831">bleak</seg> forest, my former residence,  <seg xml:id="C17_app728-f1831">the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app729-f1831">rain-dropping branches,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app731-f1831">dank</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app732-f1831">earth.</seg> I ate my breakfast with  <seg xml:id="C17_app734-f1831">pleasure,</seg> and was about to remove a plank to procure myself a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app736-f1831">water,</seg> when I heard a  <seg xml:id="C17_app738-f1831">step,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app739-f1831">and</seg> looking through a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app741-f1831">chink, I</seg> beheld a young  <seg xml:id="C17_app743-f1831">creature,</seg> with a pail on her  <seg xml:id="C17_app745-f1831">head,</seg> passing before my hovel. The girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app747-f1831">young,</seg> and of gentle  <seg xml:id="C17_app749-f1831">demeanour,</seg> unlike what I have since found cottagers and  <seg xml:id="C17_app751-f1831">farm-house</seg> servants to  <seg xml:id="C17_app753-f1831">be.</seg> Yet she was  <seg xml:id="C17_app755-f1831">meanly dressed,</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app757-f1831">coarse</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app758-f1831">blue</seg> petticoat and a linen jacket being her only   <seg xml:id="C17_app760-f1831">garb;</seg> her fair hair was  <seg xml:id="C17_app762-f1831">plaited,</seg> but not adorned; she looked  <seg xml:id="C17_app764-f1831">patient,</seg> yet sad.  <seg xml:id="C17_app766-f1831">I lost sight of her; and</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app768-f1831">about</seg> a quarter of an hour  <seg xml:id="C17_app770-f1831">she</seg> returned,  <seg xml:id="C17_app772-f1831">bearing the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app773-f1831">pail,</seg> which was now partly filled with milk. As she walked  <seg xml:id="C17_app775-f1831">along,</seg> seemingly incommoded by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app777-f1831">burden,</seg> a young man met  <seg xml:id="C17_app779-f1831">her,</seg> whose countenance expressed a deeper  <seg xml:id="C17_app781-f1831">despondence.</seg> Uttering a few  <seg xml:id="C17_app783-f1831">sounds</seg> with   <seg xml:id="C17_app785-f1831">an air of</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app786-f1831">melancholy,</seg> he took the pail from her  <seg xml:id="C17_app788-f1831">head,</seg> and bore it  <seg xml:id="C17_app790-f1831">to</seg> the cottage himself. She  <seg xml:id="C17_app792-f1831">followed,</seg> and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app794-f1831">disappeared.</seg> Presently I saw the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app796-f1831">again,</seg> with some tools in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app798-f1831">hand,</seg> cross the field  <seg xml:id="C17_app800-f1831">behind</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app802-f1831">cottage;</seg> and the girl was also  <seg xml:id="C17_app804-f1831">busied, sometimes</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app806-f1831">the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app807-f1831">house,</seg> and sometimes in the  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__I">yard. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p15">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__F"> “On examining</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C17_app811-f1831">dwelling,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app813-f1831">found</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app815-f1831">one of the windows</seg> of the cottage  <seg xml:id="C17_app817-f1831">had formerly occupied a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app818-f1831">part</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app820-f1831">it,</seg> but the panes had  <seg xml:id="C17_app822-f1831">been filled up with wood. In one of these was a small and</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app823-f1831">almost</seg> imperceptible  <seg xml:id="C17_app825-f1831">chink, through which</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app826-f1831">the eye could just</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app827-f1831">penetrate. Through</seg> this  <seg xml:id="C17_app829-f1831">crevice</seg> a small room was visible,  <seg xml:id="C17_app831-f1831">whitewashed</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app832-f1831">and</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app833-f1831">clean,</seg> but very bare of  <seg xml:id="C17_app835-f1831">furniture.</seg> In  <seg xml:id="C17_app837-f1831">one</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app838-f1831">corner,</seg> near a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app840-f1831">fire, sat</seg> an old  <seg xml:id="C17_app842-f1831">man,</seg> leaning his head on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app844-f1831">hands</seg> in a  <seg xml:id="C17_app846-f1831">disconsolate <pb xml:id="F1831_v_108" n="92"/>attitude.</seg> The young girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app848-f1831">occupied in arranging the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app849-f1831">cottage;</seg> but presently  <seg xml:id="C17_app851-f1831">she took</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app852-f1831">something</seg> out of  <seg xml:id="C17_app854-f1831">a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app855-f1831">drawer,</seg> which employed her  <seg xml:id="C17_app857-f1831">hands,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app859-f1831">she</seg> sat down beside  <seg xml:id="C17_app861-f1831">the old</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app862-f1831">man, who,</seg> taking up an  <seg xml:id="C17_app864-f1831">instrument,</seg> began to  <seg xml:id="C17_app866-f1831">play,</seg> and to produce  <seg xml:id="C17_app868-f1831">sounds</seg> sweeter than the voice of the thrush or  <seg xml:id="C17_app870-f1831">the</seg> nightingale.  <seg xml:id="C17_app872-f1831">It was a lovely</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app873-f1831">sight,</seg> even to  <seg xml:id="C17_app875-f1831">me,</seg> poor  <seg xml:id="C17_app877-f1831">wretch!</seg> who had never beheld aught beautiful before.  <seg xml:id="C17_app879-f1831">The</seg> silver   <seg xml:id="C17_app881-f1831">hair and</seg> benevolent countenance  <seg xml:id="C17_app883-f1831">of</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app884-f1831">the</seg> aged  <seg xml:id="C17_app886-f1831">cottager</seg> won my  <seg xml:id="C17_app888-f1831">reverence,</seg> while  <seg xml:id="C17_app890-f1831">the</seg> gentle manners of the girl enticed my love. He played a sweet mournful   <seg xml:id="C17_app892-f1831">air,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app894-f1831">perceived</seg> drew tears from the eyes of  <seg xml:id="C17_app896-f1831">his</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app897-f1831">amiable</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app898-f1831">companion,</seg> of which the old man took  <seg xml:id="C17_app900-f1831">no</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app901-f1831">notice, until</seg> she sobbed  <seg xml:id="C17_app903-f1831">audibly;</seg> he  <seg xml:id="C17_app905-f1831">then pronounced a few</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app906-f1831">sounds,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app908-f1831">fair creature,</seg> leaving her  <seg xml:id="C17_app910-f1831">work,</seg> knelt at his  <seg xml:id="C17_app912-f1831">feet.</seg> He  <seg xml:id="C17_app914-f1831">raised her,</seg> and smiled with such  <seg xml:id="C17_app916-f1831">kindness</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app917-f1831">and affection,</seg> that I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app919-f1831">sensations of a peculiar and overpowering nature:</seg> they were a  <seg xml:id="C17_app921-f1831">mixture of pain and</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app922-f1831">pleasure,</seg> such as I had never  <seg xml:id="C17_app924-f1831">before experienced,</seg> either from  <seg xml:id="C17_app926-f1831">hunger or cold,</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app927-f1831">warmth or</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app928-f1831">food;</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app930-f1831">withdrew</seg> from  <seg xml:id="C17_app932-f1831">the window,</seg> unable  <seg xml:id="C17_app934-f1831">to bear</seg> these  <seg xml:id="C17_app936-f1831">emotions.</seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p16">
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app938-f1831">“Soon</seg> after this the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app940-f1831">returned,</seg> bearing on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app942-f1831">shoulders</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app944-f1831">load of</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app945-f1831">wood.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app947-f1831">girl met him at the</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app948-f1831">door,</seg> helped to relieve him of his  <seg xml:id="C17_app950-f1831">burden, and,</seg> taking some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app952-f1831">the fuel</seg> into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app954-f1831">cottage,</seg> placed it on the fire;  <seg xml:id="C17_app956-f1831">then she and the youth went apart into a</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app957-f1831">nook</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app959-f1831">cottage,</seg> and he  <seg xml:id="C17_app961-f1831">showed</seg> her a large loaf and a piece of  <seg xml:id="C17_app963-f1831">cheese.</seg> She seemed  <seg xml:id="C17_app965-f1831">pleased,</seg> and went into the garden for  <seg xml:id="C17_app967-f1831">some</seg> roots and  <seg xml:id="C17_app969-f1831">plants,</seg> which she placed in  <seg xml:id="C17_app971-f1831">water,</seg> and then upon the  <seg xml:id="C17_app973-f1831">fire.</seg> She  <seg xml:id="C17_app975-f1831">afterwards</seg> continued her   <seg xml:id="C17_app977-f1831">work,</seg> whilst the young man went into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app979-f1831">garden,</seg> and appeared busily employed in digging and  <seg xml:id="C17_app981-f1831">pulling up</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app982-f1831">roots. After</seg> he had been employed thus about  <seg xml:id="C17_app984-f1831">an</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app985-f1831">hour,</seg> the young woman joined him, and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app987-f1831">entered</seg> the cottage  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__I">together. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p17">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__F"> “The</seg> old man  <seg xml:id="C17_app991-f1831">had,</seg> in the mean  <seg xml:id="C17_app993-f1831">time,</seg> been  <seg xml:id="C17_app995-f1831">pensive; but,</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app997-f1831">appearance</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app999-f1831">his</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1000-f1831">companions,</seg> he assumed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app1002-f1831">more</seg> cheerful air, and they sat down to eat.   <seg xml:id="C17_app1004-f1831">The</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1005-f1831">meal</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1006-f1831">was quickly</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1007-f1831">despatched.</seg> The young woman was again occupied in arranging the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1009-f1831">cottage;</seg> the old man walked before the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1011-f1831">cottage</seg> in the sun for a few   <seg xml:id="C17_app1014-f1831">minutes,</seg> leaning on the arm of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1016-f1831">youth.</seg> Nothing could exceed in beauty the contrast <pb xml:id="F1831_v_109" n="93"/>between these two <seg xml:id="C17_app1018-f1831">excellent</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1019-f1831">creatures.</seg> One was old, with silver hairs and a countenance beaming with  <seg xml:id="C17_app1021-f1831">benevolence</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1023-f1831">love:</seg> the younger was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1025-f1831">slight</seg> and graceful in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1027-f1831">figure,</seg> and his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1029-f1831">features</seg> were moulded with the finest  <seg xml:id="C17_app1031-f1831">symmetry;</seg> yet his eyes and attitude expressed the utmost sadness and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1033-f1831">despondency.</seg> The old man returned to the cottage; and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1035-f1831">youth,</seg> with tools different from those  <seg xml:id="C17_app1037-f1831">he had used in the morning, directed his steps across the</seg>
                     <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__I">fields. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p18">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__F"> “Night</seg> quickly shut  <seg xml:id="C17_app1040-f1831">in; but,</seg> to my extreme  <seg xml:id="C17_app1042-f1831">wonder,</seg> I found that the cottagers had a means of prolonging  <seg xml:id="C17_app1044-f1831">light</seg> by the use of  <seg xml:id="C17_app1046-f1831">tapers,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1048-f1831">delighted</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1050-f1831">find</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app1052-f1831">the</seg> setting of the sun did not put an end  <seg xml:id="C17_app1054-f1831">to the pleasure I experienced in watching</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1055-f1831">my human</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1056-f1831">neighbours. In</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1058-f1831">evening,</seg> the young girl and her companion were employed in various  <seg xml:id="C17_app1060-f1831">occupations</seg> which I did not   <seg xml:id="C17_app1063-f1831">understand;</seg> and the old man again took  <seg xml:id="C17_app1065-f1831">up the instrument</seg> which produced  <seg xml:id="C17_app1067-f1831">the</seg> divine sounds that had enchanted me in the morning.  <seg xml:id="C17_app1069-f1831">So soon as</seg> he had   <seg xml:id="C17_app1071-f1831">finished,</seg> the youth  <seg xml:id="C17_app1073-f1831">began,</seg> not to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1075-f1831">play,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C17_app1077-f1831">to</seg> utter   <seg xml:id="C17_app1079-f1831">sounds</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="C17_app1080-f1831">that</seg> were  <seg xml:id="C17_app1082-f1831">monotonous,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1084-f1831">neither resembling</seg> the harmony of the old   <seg xml:id="C17_app1086-f1831">man’s</seg> instrument  <seg xml:id="C17_app1088-f1831">nor</seg> the songs of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1090-f1831">birds:</seg> I since found that he read  <seg xml:id="C17_app1092-f1831">aloud,</seg> but at that time I knew nothing of the science of words or letters.   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__I">
               </seg>
                  </p>
                  <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p19">
                     <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__F"> “The family, after having been thus occupied for a short time,</seg> extinguished their  <seg xml:id="C17_app1098-f1831">lights,</seg> and retired, as I conjectured, to  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__I">rest. </seg>
                  </p>
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__F">
            </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1101-f1831">
                     <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="11"/>
                  </seg>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            <div type="collation">
               <seg xml:id="C17_app2-f1831">
                  <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C17"/>
               </seg>
               <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="11"/>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app4-f1831">
                  <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER XI.<head ana="end"/>
               </seg>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1"> “I<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1_hi1">T</hi> is with <seg xml:id="C17_app6-f1831">considerable</seg> difficulty that I remember the  <seg xml:id="C17_app8-f1831">original</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app9-f1831">era</seg> of my  <seg xml:id="C17_app11-f1831">being:</seg> all the events of that period appear confused and indistinct.  <seg xml:id="C17_app13-f1831">A strange</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app14-f1831">multiplicity of sensations</seg> seized  <seg xml:id="C17_app16-f1831">me, and</seg> I saw,  <seg xml:id="C17_app18-f1831">felt, heard,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app20-f1831">smelt,</seg> at the same  <seg xml:id="C17_app22-f1831">time;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app24-f1831">was, indeed,</seg> a long time before I learned to distinguish between the  <seg xml:id="C17_app26-f1831">operations of my various senses. By</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app27-f1831">degrees,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app29-f1831">remember,</seg> a stronger light pressed upon my  <seg xml:id="C17_app31-f1831">nerves,</seg> so that I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app33-f1831">shut</seg> my eyes. Darkness then came over  <seg xml:id="C17_app35-f1831">me,</seg> and troubled  <seg xml:id="C17_app37-f1831">me;</seg> but hardly had I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app41-f1831">this, when, by</seg> opening my  <seg xml:id="C17_app43-f1831">eyes,</seg> as I now  <seg xml:id="C17_app45-f1831">suppose,</seg> the light poured in upon me  <seg xml:id="C17_app47-f1831">again.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app49-f1831">walked, and,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app51-f1831">believe,</seg> descended; but  <seg xml:id="C17_app53-f1831">I</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app54-f1831">presently</seg> found a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app56-f1831">alteration</seg> in my   <seg xml:id="C17_app58-f1831">sensations. Before,</seg> dark  <seg xml:id="C17_app60-f1831">and</seg> opaque bodies had surrounded me, impervious to my touch or  <seg xml:id="C17_app62-f1831">sight; but</seg> I now found that I could wander on at  <seg xml:id="C17_app64-f1831">liberty,</seg> with no obstacles which I could not either surmount or  <seg xml:id="C17_app66-f1831">avoid.</seg> The light  <seg xml:id="C17_app68-f1831">became</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app69-f1831">more</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app70-f1831">and</seg> more  <seg xml:id="C17_app72-f1831">oppressive</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app74-f1831">me; and,</seg> the heat wearying me as I  <seg xml:id="C17_app76-f1831">walked,</seg> I sought a place where I could  <seg xml:id="C17_app78-f1831">receive</seg> shade. This was the forest near  <seg xml:id="C17_app80-f1831">Ingolstadt; and</seg> here  <seg xml:id="C17_app82-f1831">I lay</seg> by the side of a brook  <seg xml:id="C17_app84-f1831">resting from my</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app85-f1831">fatigue, until</seg> I felt tormented by hunger and thirst. This roused me from my nearly dormant  <seg xml:id="C17_app87-f1831">state,</seg> and I ate some berries which I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app89-f1831">hanging</seg> on the   <seg xml:id="C17_app91-f1831">trees,</seg> or lying on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app93-f1831">
                     <pb xml:id="F1831_v_103" n="87"/>ground.</seg> I slaked my thirst  <seg xml:id="C17_app95-f1831">at</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app97-f1831">brook;</seg> and then  <seg xml:id="C17_app99-f1831">lying</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app100-f1831">down,</seg> was overcome by  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p2">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was dark when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app104-f1831">awoke;</seg> I felt cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app106-f1831">also,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app108-f1831">half-frightened,</seg> as it were  <seg xml:id="C17_app110-f1831">instinctively,</seg> finding myself so desolate. Before I had quitted your  <seg xml:id="C17_app112-f1831">apartment,</seg> on a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app114-f1831">cold,</seg> I had covered  <seg xml:id="C17_app116-f1831">myself</seg> with some  <seg xml:id="C17_app118-f1831">clothes;</seg> but these were  <seg xml:id="C17_app120-f1831">insufficient</seg> to secure me from the  <seg xml:id="C17_app122-f1831">dews of night. I was a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app123-f1831">poor, helpless,</seg> miserable  <seg xml:id="C17_app125-f1831">wretch; I knew,</seg> and could  <seg xml:id="C17_app127-f1831">distinguish, nothing;</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app128-f1831">but</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app129-f1831">feeling</seg> pain invade me on all   <seg xml:id="C17_app131-f1831">sides,</seg> I sat down and wept. </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3">
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app133-f1831">“Soon</seg> a gentle light stole over the  <seg xml:id="C17_app135-f1831">heavens,</seg> and gave me a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app137-f1831">pleasure.</seg> I started up, and beheld a radiant form rise  <seg xml:id="C17_app139-f1831">from among the trees.</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app140-f1831">*<note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3_note1">* The moon.</note>
                  </seg> I gazed with a kind of  <seg xml:id="C17_app142-f1831">wonder.</seg> It moved  <seg xml:id="C17_app144-f1831">slowly,</seg> but it enlightened my  <seg xml:id="C17_app146-f1831">path;</seg> and I again went out in search of berries. I was still  <seg xml:id="C17_app148-f1831">cold,</seg> when  <seg xml:id="C17_app150-f1831">under one of the trees I found a huge</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app151-f1831">cloak,</seg> with which  <seg xml:id="C17_app153-f1831">I</seg> covered myself, and sat down  <seg xml:id="C17_app155-f1831">upon</seg> the ground. No distinct ideas occupied my  <seg xml:id="C17_app157-f1831">mind;</seg> all was  <seg xml:id="C17_app159-f1831">confused.</seg> I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app161-f1831">light, and</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app162-f1831">hunger,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app164-f1831">thirst,</seg> and darkness; innumerable sounds rung in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app166-f1831">ears,</seg> and on all sides various scents saluted  <seg xml:id="C17_app168-f1831">me:</seg> the only object that I could distinguish was the  <seg xml:id="C17_app170-f1831">bright moon,</seg> and I fixed my eyes   <seg xml:id="C17_app173-f1831">on</seg> that with pleasure.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__I">
               </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p4">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__F"> “Several</seg> changes of day and night  <seg xml:id="C17_app177-f1831">passed,</seg> and the orb of night had greatly  <seg xml:id="C17_app179-f1831">lessened,</seg> when I began to distinguish my sensations  <seg xml:id="C17_app181-f1831">from each</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app182-f1831">other.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app184-f1831">gradually saw plainly</seg> the clear stream that supplied me with   <seg xml:id="C17_app186-f1831">drink,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app188-f1831">trees that</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app189-f1831">shaded</seg> me with their foliage. I was delighted when I first discovered that a pleasant   <seg xml:id="C17_app191-f1831">sound,</seg> which often   <seg xml:id="C17_app194-f1831">saluted my</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app195-f1831">ears,</seg> proceeded from the throats of  <seg xml:id="C17_app197-f1831">the little</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app198-f1831">winged</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app199-f1831">animals</seg> who  <seg xml:id="C17_app201-f1831">had</seg> often intercepted the light from my eyes. I began also to  <seg xml:id="C17_app203-f1831">observe,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app205-f1831">greater</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app206-f1831">accuracy,</seg> the forms that surrounded  <seg xml:id="C17_app208-f1831">me,</seg> and to perceive the boundaries of the radiant  <seg xml:id="C17_app210-f1831">roof of</seg> light which  <seg xml:id="C17_app212-f1831">canopied</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app213-f1831">me. Sometimes</seg> I tried to imitate the pleasant songs of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app216-f1831">birds,</seg> but was  <seg xml:id="C17_app218-f1831">unable.</seg> Sometimes I  <seg xml:id="C17_app220-f1831">wished to express my sensations in my own</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app221-f1831">mode,</seg> but the uncouth and   <seg xml:id="C17_app224-f1831">inarticulate sounds</seg> which broke from me   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__I">frightened me into silence again. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p5">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__F">
               </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app228-f1831">“The</seg> moon had  <seg xml:id="C17_app230-f1831">disappeared</seg> from the night,  <seg xml:id="C17_app232-f1831">and again,</seg>
                  <pb xml:id="F1831_v_104" n="88"/>with a lessened <seg xml:id="C17_app234-f1831">form,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app235-f1831">showed</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app236-f1831">itself,</seg> while I still remained in the forest. My  <seg xml:id="C17_app238-f1831">sensations</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app239-f1831">had,</seg> by this  <seg xml:id="C17_app241-f1831">time,</seg> become  <seg xml:id="C17_app243-f1831">distinct,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app245-f1831">my mind</seg> received every day   <seg xml:id="C17_app247-f1831">additional</seg> ideas. My eyes became accustomed to the   <seg xml:id="C17_app250-f1831">light,</seg> and to perceive objects in their right forms; I  <seg xml:id="C17_app252-f1831">distinguished</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app254-f1831">insect from the herb,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app255-f1831">and,</seg> by  <seg xml:id="C17_app257-f1831">degrees,</seg> one herb from  <seg xml:id="C17_app259-f1831">another.</seg> I found that the sparrow uttered none but harsh  <seg xml:id="C17_app261-f1831">notes,</seg> whilst  <seg xml:id="C17_app263-f1831">those of</seg> the blackbird   <seg xml:id="C17_app265-f1831">and thrush</seg> were sweet and enticing.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__I">
               </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p6">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__F"> “One day,</seg> when I was oppressed by  <seg xml:id="C17_app269-f1831">cold,</seg> I found a fire  <seg xml:id="C17_app271-f1831">which</seg> had been left by some wandering  <seg xml:id="C17_app273-f1831">beggars,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app275-f1831">overcome</seg> with delight  <seg xml:id="C17_app277-f1831">at the warmth</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app278-f1831">I</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app279-f1831">experienced</seg> from it. In my joy I thrust my hand into the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app281-f1831">embers,</seg> but quickly drew it  <seg xml:id="C17_app283-f1831">out again</seg> with a cry  <seg xml:id="C17_app285-f1831">of</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app286-f1831">pain.</seg> How strange, I thought, that the same cause should  <seg xml:id="C17_app288-f1831">produce such</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app289-f1831">opposite</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app290-f1831">effects! I</seg> examined the materials of the fire, and to my joy found it to be  <seg xml:id="C17_app292-f1831">composed of wood.</seg> I quickly collected some  <seg xml:id="C17_app294-f1831">branches;</seg> but they were  <seg xml:id="C17_app296-f1831">wet,</seg> and would not burn. I was pained at  <seg xml:id="C17_app298-f1831">this,</seg> and sat still watching the  <seg xml:id="C17_app300-f1831">operation</seg> of the fire. The wet wood  <seg xml:id="C17_app302-f1831">which</seg> I had placed near the heat  <seg xml:id="C17_app304-f1831">dried,</seg> and itself   <seg xml:id="C17_app306-f1831">became</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app307-f1831">inflamed.</seg> I reflected on   <seg xml:id="C17_app309-f1831">this; and,</seg> by touching the various  <seg xml:id="C17_app311-f1831">branches,</seg> I discovered the  <seg xml:id="C17_app313-f1831">cause,</seg> and busied myself in  <seg xml:id="C17_app315-f1831">collecting</seg> a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app317-f1831">quantity</seg> of   <seg xml:id="C17_app319-f1831">wood,</seg> that I might dry  <seg xml:id="C17_app321-f1831">it,</seg> and have a  <seg xml:id="C17_app323-f1831">plentiful supply</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app324-f1831">of fire.</seg> When night came   <seg xml:id="C17_app326-f1831">on,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app328-f1831">brought sleep with it ,</seg> I was in the greatest fear lest my fire should be  <seg xml:id="C17_app330-f1831">extinguished.</seg> I covered it carefully with  <seg xml:id="C17_app332-f1831">dry wood and</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app333-f1831">leaves,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app335-f1831">placed</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app336-f1831">wet branches</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app337-f1831">upon it;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app339-f1831">then,</seg> spreading my  <seg xml:id="C17_app341-f1831">cloak,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app343-f1831">lay</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app345-f1831">ground,</seg> and sunk into sleep.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__I">
               </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p7">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was morning when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app349-f1831">awoke,</seg> and my first care was to visit the  <seg xml:id="C17_app351-f1831">fire. I</seg> uncovered  <seg xml:id="C17_app353-f1831">it,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app355-f1831">a gentle breeze quickly fanned it into a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app356-f1831">flame.</seg> I observed this  <seg xml:id="C17_app358-f1831">also,</seg> and contrived a fan of  <seg xml:id="C17_app360-f1831">branches,</seg> which roused the embers when  <seg xml:id="C17_app362-f1831">they</seg> were nearly extinguished. When night  <seg xml:id="C17_app364-f1831">came</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app365-f1831">again,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app367-f1831">found,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app369-f1831">pleasure,</seg> that the fire gave light as well as  <seg xml:id="C17_app371-f1831">heat;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app373-f1831">that</seg> the discovery of this element was useful to me  <seg xml:id="C17_app375-f1831">in my</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app376-f1831">food;</seg> for I found some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app378-f1831">the</seg> offals that the travellers had left had been  <seg xml:id="C17_app380-f1831">roasted,</seg> and tasted much more savoury than the berries I  <seg xml:id="C17_app382-f1831">gathered from the trees.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app384-f1831">tried, therefore,</seg> to dress my food in the same manner, placing  <seg xml:id="C17_app386-f1831">it</seg> on the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app388-f1831">embers.</seg> I found that the berries <pb xml:id="F1831_v_105" n="89"/>were spoiled by this <seg xml:id="C17_app390-f1831">operation,</seg> and the nuts  <seg xml:id="C17_app392-f1831">and roots</seg> much improved.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__I">
               </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p8">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__F"> “Food, however,</seg> became  <seg xml:id="C17_app396-f1831">scarce;</seg> and I often spent  <seg xml:id="C17_app398-f1831">the whole</seg> day searching in vain for a few acorns to assuage the pangs of hunger. When I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app400-f1831">this, I</seg> resolved to quit the place  <seg xml:id="C17_app402-f1831">that</seg> I had hitherto  <seg xml:id="C17_app404-f1831">inhabited,</seg> to seek for  <seg xml:id="C17_app406-f1831">one</seg> where the few wants I experienced would be more easily satisfied. In this   <seg xml:id="C17_app408-f1831">emigration,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app410-f1831">exceedingly</seg> lamented the loss of   <seg xml:id="C17_app412-f1831">the fire which I</seg> had obtained  <seg xml:id="C17_app414-f1831">through accident,</seg> and knew not how to  <seg xml:id="C17_app416-f1831">reproduce</seg> it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app418-f1831">I gave several hours to the</seg> serious consideration  <seg xml:id="C17_app420-f1831">of this difficulty;</seg> but I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app422-f1831">relinquish all</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app423-f1831">attempt</seg> to supply  <seg xml:id="C17_app425-f1831">it; and, wrapping</seg> myself up in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app427-f1831">cloak,</seg> I struck across the wood towards the setting  <seg xml:id="C17_app429-f1831">sun.</seg> I passed three days in these  <seg xml:id="C17_app431-f1831">rambles,</seg> and at length discovered the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app433-f1831">country.</seg> A great fall of snow had taken place the night  <seg xml:id="C17_app435-f1831">before,</seg> and the fields were of one  <seg xml:id="C17_app437-f1831">uniform white;</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app439-f1831">appearance</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C17_app441-f1831">disconsolate,</seg> and I found my feet chilled by the cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app443-f1831">damp</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app444-f1831">substance that covered the</seg>
                  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__I">ground. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p9">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was about seven in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app447-f1831">morning,</seg> and I longed to obtain food and  <seg xml:id="C17_app449-f1831">shelter;</seg> at length I perceived  <seg xml:id="C17_app451-f1831">a small</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app452-f1831">hut, on a rising ground,</seg> which had  <seg xml:id="C17_app454-f1831">doubtless been built for the convenience of</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app455-f1831">some</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app456-f1831">shepherd.</seg> This was a new sight to  <seg xml:id="C17_app458-f1831">me;</seg> and I examined the  <seg xml:id="C17_app460-f1831">structure</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app461-f1831">with great curiosity.</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app462-f1831">Finding the door</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app463-f1831">open,</seg> I entered. An old man sat  <seg xml:id="C17_app465-f1831">in it, near a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app466-f1831">fire,</seg> over  <seg xml:id="C17_app468-f1831">which he was preparing his</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app469-f1831">breakfast.</seg> He turned  <seg xml:id="C17_app471-f1831">on hearing a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app472-f1831">noise; and,</seg> perceiving  <seg xml:id="C17_app474-f1831">me,</seg> shrieked  <seg xml:id="C17_app476-f1831">loudly, and, quitting</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app478-f1831">hut,</seg> ran across the fields with a speed  <seg xml:id="C17_app480-f1831">of which his debilitated form hardly appeared</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app481-f1831">capable. His appearance, different from any I had ever before seen, and</seg> his  <seg xml:id="C17_app483-f1831">flight,</seg> somewhat surprised  <seg xml:id="C17_app485-f1831">me.</seg> But I was  <seg xml:id="C17_app487-f1831">enchanted by</seg> the appearance of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app489-f1831">hut:</seg> here the snow and rain could not  <seg xml:id="C17_app491-f1831">penetrate;</seg> the ground was  <seg xml:id="C17_app493-f1831">dry;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app495-f1831">presented</seg> to me then as   <seg xml:id="C17_app497-f1831">exquisite</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app498-f1831">and divine</seg> a retreat as  <seg xml:id="C17_app500-f1831">Pandæmonium</seg> appeared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app502-f1831">dæmons</seg> of hell  <seg xml:id="C17_app504-f1831">after</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app505-f1831">their sufferings</seg> in the lake of fire. I greedily devoured the   <seg xml:id="C17_app508-f1831">remnants</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app510-f1831">shepherd’s breakfast,</seg> which consisted of bread, cheese,  <seg xml:id="C17_app512-f1831">milk,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app514-f1831">wine; the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app515-f1831">latter, however,</seg> I did not like.  <seg xml:id="C17_app517-f1831">Then,</seg> overcome by  <seg xml:id="C17_app519-f1831">fatigue,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app520-f1831">I lay</seg> down among some  <seg xml:id="C17_app522-f1831">straw,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app523-f1831">and</seg> fell asleep. </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p10">
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app525-f1831">“It</seg> was noon when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app527-f1831">awoke; and,</seg> allured by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app529-f1831">
                     <pb xml:id="F1831_v_106" n="90"/>warmth of</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app530-f1831">the sun, which shone brightly on the white ground,</seg> I determined to recommence my  <seg xml:id="C17_app532-f1831">travels; and,</seg> depositing the   <seg xml:id="C17_app535-f1831">remains</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app537-f1831">peasant’s</seg> breakfast in a wallet I found, I proceeded across the fields for several hours,  <seg xml:id="C17_app539-f1831">until</seg> at sunset I  <seg xml:id="C17_app541-f1831">arrived at</seg> a village. How miraculous did this   <seg xml:id="C17_app543-f1831">appear!</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app545-f1831">huts,</seg> the neater  <seg xml:id="C17_app547-f1831">cottages,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app549-f1831">stately houses,</seg> engaged my admiration by  <seg xml:id="C17_app551-f1831">turns.</seg> The vegetables in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app553-f1831">gardens,</seg> the milk and cheese that I saw placed at  <seg xml:id="C17_app555-f1831">the windows of some of the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app556-f1831">cottages,</seg> allured  <seg xml:id="C17_app558-f1831">my appetite.</seg> One of the best of these I  <seg xml:id="C17_app560-f1831">entered;</seg> but I had hardly placed my foot  <seg xml:id="C17_app562-f1831">within</seg> the   <seg xml:id="C17_app564-f1831">door,</seg> before the children  <seg xml:id="C17_app566-f1831">shrieked,</seg> and one of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app568-f1831">women</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app569-f1831">fainted.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app571-f1831">whole</seg> village was  <seg xml:id="C17_app573-f1831">roused;</seg> some  <seg xml:id="C17_app575-f1831">fled, some</seg> attacked  <seg xml:id="C17_app577-f1831">me, until,</seg> grievously bruised by  <seg xml:id="C17_app579-f1831">stones</seg> and   <seg xml:id="C17_app581-f1831">many other kinds of missile</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app582-f1831">weapons,</seg> I escaped to the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app584-f1831">country,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app585-f1831">and</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app586-f1831">fearfully</seg> took refuge in a low  <seg xml:id="C17_app588-f1831">hovel, quite bare,</seg> and making a wretched appearance after the  <seg xml:id="C17_app590-f1831">palaces</seg> I had beheld in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app592-f1831">village.</seg> This  <seg xml:id="C17_app594-f1831">hovel, however, joined</seg> a cottage of a neat and pleasant  <seg xml:id="C17_app596-f1831">appearance; but,</seg> after my late  <seg xml:id="C17_app599-f1831">dearly</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app600-f1831">bought </seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app601-f1831">experience,</seg> I dared not enter it. My place of refuge  <seg xml:id="C17_app603-f1831">was constructed of wood,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app604-f1831">but</seg> so   <seg xml:id="C17_app606-f1831">low,</seg> that I could with difficulty sit upright in it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app608-f1831">No</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app609-f1831">wood, however,</seg> was placed on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app611-f1831">earth,</seg> which formed  <seg xml:id="C17_app613-f1831">the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app614-f1831">floor,</seg> but it was  <seg xml:id="C17_app616-f1831">dry;</seg> and although the wind entered  <seg xml:id="C17_app618-f1831">it</seg> by innumerable  <seg xml:id="C17_app620-f1831">chinks,</seg> I found it an  <seg xml:id="C17_app622-f1831">agreeable asylum</seg> from the snow  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__I">and rain. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p11">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__F"> “Here then I retreated, and lay</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app625-f1831">down</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app626-f1831">happy to have found a shelter, however miserable, from the inclemency of the season,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app628-f1831">still more from the barbarity of man.</seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p12">
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app630-f1831">“As</seg> soon as morning  <seg xml:id="C17_app632-f1831">dawned,</seg> I crept from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app634-f1831">kennel,</seg> that I might view the adjacent  <seg xml:id="C17_app636-f1831">cottage,</seg> and discover if I could remain in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app638-f1831">habitation</seg> I had found. It was situated  <seg xml:id="C17_app640-f1831">against</seg> the back of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app642-f1831">cottage,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app644-f1831">surrounded</seg> on   <seg xml:id="C17_app646-f1831">the</seg> sides which were exposed by a   <seg xml:id="C17_app648-f1831">pig-sty</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app650-f1831">a clear</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app651-f1831">pool</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app653-f1831">water.</seg> One part was  <seg xml:id="C17_app655-f1831">open,</seg> and by that I had crept  <seg xml:id="C17_app657-f1831">in;</seg> but now  <seg xml:id="C17_app659-f1831">I</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app660-f1831">covered</seg> every crevice  <seg xml:id="C17_app662-f1831">by which I might be</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app663-f1831">perceived with stones and wood,</seg> yet in such a manner that I  <seg xml:id="C17_app665-f1831">might</seg> move  <seg xml:id="C17_app667-f1831">them</seg> on  <seg xml:id="C17_app669-f1831">occasion to pass</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app670-f1831">out:</seg> all the light I enjoyed came through the  <seg xml:id="C17_app672-f1831">sty,</seg> and that was  <seg xml:id="C17_app674-f1831">sufficient</seg> for me. </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p13">
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app676-f1831">“Having</seg> thus arranged my  <seg xml:id="C17_app678-f1831">dwelling, and</seg> carpeted it with clean straw, I  <seg xml:id="C17_app680-f1831">retired;</seg> for I saw the figure of a man  <seg xml:id="C17_app682-f1831">
                     <pb xml:id="F1831_v_107" n="91"/>at</seg> a   <seg xml:id="C17_app684-f1831">distance,</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app686-f1831">remembered</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app687-f1831">too well my treatment the night</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app688-f1831">before,</seg> to trust myself in his power. I had  <seg xml:id="C17_app690-f1831">first, however,</seg> provided for my sustenance for that  <seg xml:id="C17_app692-f1831">day,</seg> by a loaf of  <seg xml:id="C17_app694-f1831">coarse</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app695-f1831">bread,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app697-f1831">purloined,</seg> and a cup  <seg xml:id="C17_app699-f1831">with</seg> which I could   <seg xml:id="C17_app701-f1831">drink,</seg> more conveniently than from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app703-f1831">hand,</seg> of the pure water which  flowed by my   <seg xml:id="C17_app707-f1831">retreat. The floor</seg> was a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app709-f1831">raised,</seg> so that it was kept   <seg xml:id="C17_app712-f1831">perfectly</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app713-f1831">dry,</seg> and by its vicinity to the chimney  <seg xml:id="C17_app715-f1831">of the cottage it was tolerably warm.</seg>
                  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__I">
               </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p14">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__F"> “Being</seg> thus  <seg xml:id="C17_app718-f1831">provided,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app720-f1831">resolved</seg> to reside in this  <seg xml:id="C17_app722-f1831">hovel, until</seg> something should occur which might alter my determination. It was indeed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app724-f1831">paradise,</seg> compared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app726-f1831">bleak</seg> forest, my former residence,  <seg xml:id="C17_app728-f1831">the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app729-f1831">rain-dropping branches,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app731-f1831">dank</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app732-f1831">earth.</seg> I ate my breakfast with  <seg xml:id="C17_app734-f1831">pleasure,</seg> and was about to remove a plank to procure myself a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app736-f1831">water,</seg> when I heard a  <seg xml:id="C17_app738-f1831">step,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app739-f1831">and</seg> looking through a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app741-f1831">chink, I</seg> beheld a young  <seg xml:id="C17_app743-f1831">creature,</seg> with a pail on her  <seg xml:id="C17_app745-f1831">head,</seg> passing before my hovel. The girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app747-f1831">young,</seg> and of gentle  <seg xml:id="C17_app749-f1831">demeanour,</seg> unlike what I have since found cottagers and  <seg xml:id="C17_app751-f1831">farm-house</seg> servants to  <seg xml:id="C17_app753-f1831">be.</seg> Yet she was  <seg xml:id="C17_app755-f1831">meanly dressed,</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app757-f1831">coarse</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app758-f1831">blue</seg> petticoat and a linen jacket being her only   <seg xml:id="C17_app760-f1831">garb;</seg> her fair hair was  <seg xml:id="C17_app762-f1831">plaited,</seg> but not adorned; she looked  <seg xml:id="C17_app764-f1831">patient,</seg> yet sad.  <seg xml:id="C17_app766-f1831">I lost sight of her; and</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app768-f1831">about</seg> a quarter of an hour  <seg xml:id="C17_app770-f1831">she</seg> returned,  <seg xml:id="C17_app772-f1831">bearing the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app773-f1831">pail,</seg> which was now partly filled with milk. As she walked  <seg xml:id="C17_app775-f1831">along,</seg> seemingly incommoded by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app777-f1831">burden,</seg> a young man met  <seg xml:id="C17_app779-f1831">her,</seg> whose countenance expressed a deeper  <seg xml:id="C17_app781-f1831">despondence.</seg> Uttering a few  <seg xml:id="C17_app783-f1831">sounds</seg> with   <seg xml:id="C17_app785-f1831">an air of</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app786-f1831">melancholy,</seg> he took the pail from her  <seg xml:id="C17_app788-f1831">head,</seg> and bore it  <seg xml:id="C17_app790-f1831">to</seg> the cottage himself. She  <seg xml:id="C17_app792-f1831">followed,</seg> and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app794-f1831">disappeared.</seg> Presently I saw the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app796-f1831">again,</seg> with some tools in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app798-f1831">hand,</seg> cross the field  <seg xml:id="C17_app800-f1831">behind</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app802-f1831">cottage;</seg> and the girl was also  <seg xml:id="C17_app804-f1831">busied, sometimes</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app806-f1831">the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app807-f1831">house,</seg> and sometimes in the  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__I">yard. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p15">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__F"> “On examining</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C17_app811-f1831">dwelling,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app813-f1831">found</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app815-f1831">one of the windows</seg> of the cottage  <seg xml:id="C17_app817-f1831">had formerly occupied a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app818-f1831">part</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app820-f1831">it,</seg> but the panes had  <seg xml:id="C17_app822-f1831">been filled up with wood. In one of these was a small and</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app823-f1831">almost</seg> imperceptible  <seg xml:id="C17_app825-f1831">chink, through which</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app826-f1831">the eye could just</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app827-f1831">penetrate. Through</seg> this  <seg xml:id="C17_app829-f1831">crevice</seg> a small room was visible,  <seg xml:id="C17_app831-f1831">whitewashed</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app832-f1831">and</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app833-f1831">clean,</seg> but very bare of  <seg xml:id="C17_app835-f1831">furniture.</seg> In  <seg xml:id="C17_app837-f1831">one</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app838-f1831">corner,</seg> near a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app840-f1831">fire, sat</seg> an old  <seg xml:id="C17_app842-f1831">man,</seg> leaning his head on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app844-f1831">hands</seg> in a  <seg xml:id="C17_app846-f1831">disconsolate <pb xml:id="F1831_v_108" n="92"/>attitude.</seg> The young girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app848-f1831">occupied in arranging the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app849-f1831">cottage;</seg> but presently  <seg xml:id="C17_app851-f1831">she took</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app852-f1831">something</seg> out of  <seg xml:id="C17_app854-f1831">a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app855-f1831">drawer,</seg> which employed her  <seg xml:id="C17_app857-f1831">hands,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app859-f1831">she</seg> sat down beside  <seg xml:id="C17_app861-f1831">the old</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app862-f1831">man, who,</seg> taking up an  <seg xml:id="C17_app864-f1831">instrument,</seg> began to  <seg xml:id="C17_app866-f1831">play,</seg> and to produce  <seg xml:id="C17_app868-f1831">sounds</seg> sweeter than the voice of the thrush or  <seg xml:id="C17_app870-f1831">the</seg> nightingale.  <seg xml:id="C17_app872-f1831">It was a lovely</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app873-f1831">sight,</seg> even to  <seg xml:id="C17_app875-f1831">me,</seg> poor  <seg xml:id="C17_app877-f1831">wretch!</seg> who had never beheld aught beautiful before.  <seg xml:id="C17_app879-f1831">The</seg> silver   <seg xml:id="C17_app881-f1831">hair and</seg> benevolent countenance  <seg xml:id="C17_app883-f1831">of</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app884-f1831">the</seg> aged  <seg xml:id="C17_app886-f1831">cottager</seg> won my  <seg xml:id="C17_app888-f1831">reverence,</seg> while  <seg xml:id="C17_app890-f1831">the</seg> gentle manners of the girl enticed my love. He played a sweet mournful   <seg xml:id="C17_app892-f1831">air,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app894-f1831">perceived</seg> drew tears from the eyes of  <seg xml:id="C17_app896-f1831">his</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app897-f1831">amiable</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app898-f1831">companion,</seg> of which the old man took  <seg xml:id="C17_app900-f1831">no</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app901-f1831">notice, until</seg> she sobbed  <seg xml:id="C17_app903-f1831">audibly;</seg> he  <seg xml:id="C17_app905-f1831">then pronounced a few</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app906-f1831">sounds,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app908-f1831">fair creature,</seg> leaving her  <seg xml:id="C17_app910-f1831">work,</seg> knelt at his  <seg xml:id="C17_app912-f1831">feet.</seg> He  <seg xml:id="C17_app914-f1831">raised her,</seg> and smiled with such  <seg xml:id="C17_app916-f1831">kindness</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app917-f1831">and affection,</seg> that I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app919-f1831">sensations of a peculiar and overpowering nature:</seg> they were a  <seg xml:id="C17_app921-f1831">mixture of pain and</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app922-f1831">pleasure,</seg> such as I had never  <seg xml:id="C17_app924-f1831">before experienced,</seg> either from  <seg xml:id="C17_app926-f1831">hunger or cold,</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app927-f1831">warmth or</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app928-f1831">food;</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app930-f1831">withdrew</seg> from  <seg xml:id="C17_app932-f1831">the window,</seg> unable  <seg xml:id="C17_app934-f1831">to bear</seg> these  <seg xml:id="C17_app936-f1831">emotions.</seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p16">
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app938-f1831">“Soon</seg> after this the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app940-f1831">returned,</seg> bearing on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app942-f1831">shoulders</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app944-f1831">load of</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app945-f1831">wood.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app947-f1831">girl met him at the</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app948-f1831">door,</seg> helped to relieve him of his  <seg xml:id="C17_app950-f1831">burden, and,</seg> taking some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app952-f1831">the fuel</seg> into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app954-f1831">cottage,</seg> placed it on the fire;  <seg xml:id="C17_app956-f1831">then she and the youth went apart into a</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app957-f1831">nook</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app959-f1831">cottage,</seg> and he  <seg xml:id="C17_app961-f1831">showed</seg> her a large loaf and a piece of  <seg xml:id="C17_app963-f1831">cheese.</seg> She seemed  <seg xml:id="C17_app965-f1831">pleased,</seg> and went into the garden for  <seg xml:id="C17_app967-f1831">some</seg> roots and  <seg xml:id="C17_app969-f1831">plants,</seg> which she placed in  <seg xml:id="C17_app971-f1831">water,</seg> and then upon the  <seg xml:id="C17_app973-f1831">fire.</seg> She  <seg xml:id="C17_app975-f1831">afterwards</seg> continued her   <seg xml:id="C17_app977-f1831">work,</seg> whilst the young man went into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app979-f1831">garden,</seg> and appeared busily employed in digging and  <seg xml:id="C17_app981-f1831">pulling up</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app982-f1831">roots. After</seg> he had been employed thus about  <seg xml:id="C17_app984-f1831">an</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app985-f1831">hour,</seg> the young woman joined him, and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app987-f1831">entered</seg> the cottage  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__I">together. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p17">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__F"> “The</seg> old man  <seg xml:id="C17_app991-f1831">had,</seg> in the mean  <seg xml:id="C17_app993-f1831">time,</seg> been  <seg xml:id="C17_app995-f1831">pensive; but,</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app997-f1831">appearance</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app999-f1831">his</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1000-f1831">companions,</seg> he assumed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app1002-f1831">more</seg> cheerful air, and they sat down to eat.   <seg xml:id="C17_app1004-f1831">The</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1005-f1831">meal</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1006-f1831">was quickly</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1007-f1831">despatched.</seg> The young woman was again occupied in arranging the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1009-f1831">cottage;</seg> the old man walked before the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1011-f1831">cottage</seg> in the sun for a few   <seg xml:id="C17_app1014-f1831">minutes,</seg> leaning on the arm of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1016-f1831">youth.</seg> Nothing could exceed in beauty the contrast <pb xml:id="F1831_v_109" n="93"/>between these two <seg xml:id="C17_app1018-f1831">excellent</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1019-f1831">creatures.</seg> One was old, with silver hairs and a countenance beaming with  <seg xml:id="C17_app1021-f1831">benevolence</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1023-f1831">love:</seg> the younger was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1025-f1831">slight</seg> and graceful in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1027-f1831">figure,</seg> and his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1029-f1831">features</seg> were moulded with the finest  <seg xml:id="C17_app1031-f1831">symmetry;</seg> yet his eyes and attitude expressed the utmost sadness and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1033-f1831">despondency.</seg> The old man returned to the cottage; and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1035-f1831">youth,</seg> with tools different from those  <seg xml:id="C17_app1037-f1831">he had used in the morning, directed his steps across the</seg>
                  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__I">fields. </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p18">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__F"> “Night</seg> quickly shut  <seg xml:id="C17_app1040-f1831">in; but,</seg> to my extreme  <seg xml:id="C17_app1042-f1831">wonder,</seg> I found that the cottagers had a means of prolonging  <seg xml:id="C17_app1044-f1831">light</seg> by the use of  <seg xml:id="C17_app1046-f1831">tapers,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1048-f1831">delighted</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1050-f1831">find</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app1052-f1831">the</seg> setting of the sun did not put an end  <seg xml:id="C17_app1054-f1831">to the pleasure I experienced in watching</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1055-f1831">my human</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1056-f1831">neighbours. In</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1058-f1831">evening,</seg> the young girl and her companion were employed in various  <seg xml:id="C17_app1060-f1831">occupations</seg> which I did not   <seg xml:id="C17_app1063-f1831">understand;</seg> and the old man again took  <seg xml:id="C17_app1065-f1831">up the instrument</seg> which produced  <seg xml:id="C17_app1067-f1831">the</seg> divine sounds that had enchanted me in the morning.  <seg xml:id="C17_app1069-f1831">So soon as</seg> he had   <seg xml:id="C17_app1071-f1831">finished,</seg> the youth  <seg xml:id="C17_app1073-f1831">began,</seg> not to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1075-f1831">play,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C17_app1077-f1831">to</seg> utter   <seg xml:id="C17_app1079-f1831">sounds</seg>
                  <seg xml:id="C17_app1080-f1831">that</seg> were  <seg xml:id="C17_app1082-f1831">monotonous,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1084-f1831">neither resembling</seg> the harmony of the old   <seg xml:id="C17_app1086-f1831">man’s</seg> instrument  <seg xml:id="C17_app1088-f1831">nor</seg> the songs of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1090-f1831">birds:</seg> I since found that he read  <seg xml:id="C17_app1092-f1831">aloud,</seg> but at that time I knew nothing of the science of words or letters.   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__I">
               </seg>
               </p>
               <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p19">
                  <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__F"> “The family, after having been thus occupied for a short time,</seg> extinguished their  <seg xml:id="C17_app1098-f1831">lights,</seg> and retired, as I conjectured, to  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__I">rest. </seg>
               </p>
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__F">
            </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1101-f1831">
                  <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="11"/>
               </seg>
            </div>
         </body>
         <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="collation">
            <seg xml:id="C17_app2-f1831">
               <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C17"/>
            </seg>
            <milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="11"/>
            <seg xml:id="C17_app4-f1831">
               <head ana="start"/>CHAPTER XI.<head ana="end"/>
            </seg>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1"> “I<hi xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p1_hi1">T</hi> is with <seg xml:id="C17_app6-f1831">considerable</seg> difficulty that I remember the  <seg xml:id="C17_app8-f1831">original</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app9-f1831">era</seg> of my  <seg xml:id="C17_app11-f1831">being:</seg> all the events of that period appear confused and indistinct.  <seg xml:id="C17_app13-f1831">A strange</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app14-f1831">multiplicity of sensations</seg> seized  <seg xml:id="C17_app16-f1831">me, and</seg> I saw,  <seg xml:id="C17_app18-f1831">felt, heard,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app20-f1831">smelt,</seg> at the same  <seg xml:id="C17_app22-f1831">time;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app24-f1831">was, indeed,</seg> a long time before I learned to distinguish between the  <seg xml:id="C17_app26-f1831">operations of my various senses. By</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app27-f1831">degrees,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app29-f1831">remember,</seg> a stronger light pressed upon my  <seg xml:id="C17_app31-f1831">nerves,</seg> so that I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app33-f1831">shut</seg> my eyes. Darkness then came over  <seg xml:id="C17_app35-f1831">me,</seg> and troubled  <seg xml:id="C17_app37-f1831">me;</seg> but hardly had I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app41-f1831">this, when, by</seg> opening my  <seg xml:id="C17_app43-f1831">eyes,</seg> as I now  <seg xml:id="C17_app45-f1831">suppose,</seg> the light poured in upon me  <seg xml:id="C17_app47-f1831">again.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app49-f1831">walked, and,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app51-f1831">believe,</seg> descended; but  <seg xml:id="C17_app53-f1831">I</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app54-f1831">presently</seg> found a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app56-f1831">alteration</seg> in my   <seg xml:id="C17_app58-f1831">sensations. Before,</seg> dark  <seg xml:id="C17_app60-f1831">and</seg> opaque bodies had surrounded me, impervious to my touch or  <seg xml:id="C17_app62-f1831">sight; but</seg> I now found that I could wander on at  <seg xml:id="C17_app64-f1831">liberty,</seg> with no obstacles which I could not either surmount or  <seg xml:id="C17_app66-f1831">avoid.</seg> The light  <seg xml:id="C17_app68-f1831">became</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app69-f1831">more</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app70-f1831">and</seg> more  <seg xml:id="C17_app72-f1831">oppressive</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app74-f1831">me; and,</seg> the heat wearying me as I  <seg xml:id="C17_app76-f1831">walked,</seg> I sought a place where I could  <seg xml:id="C17_app78-f1831">receive</seg> shade. This was the forest near  <seg xml:id="C17_app80-f1831">Ingolstadt; and</seg> here  <seg xml:id="C17_app82-f1831">I lay</seg> by the side of a brook  <seg xml:id="C17_app84-f1831">resting from my</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app85-f1831">fatigue, until</seg> I felt tormented by hunger and thirst. This roused me from my nearly dormant  <seg xml:id="C17_app87-f1831">state,</seg> and I ate some berries which I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app89-f1831">hanging</seg> on the   <seg xml:id="C17_app91-f1831">trees,</seg> or lying on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app93-f1831">
                  <pb xml:id="F1831_v_103" n="87"/>ground.</seg> I slaked my thirst  <seg xml:id="C17_app95-f1831">at</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app97-f1831">brook;</seg> and then  <seg xml:id="C17_app99-f1831">lying</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app100-f1831">down,</seg> was overcome by  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__I">sleep. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p2">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app102-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was dark when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app104-f1831">awoke;</seg> I felt cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app106-f1831">also,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app108-f1831">half-frightened,</seg> as it were  <seg xml:id="C17_app110-f1831">instinctively,</seg> finding myself so desolate. Before I had quitted your  <seg xml:id="C17_app112-f1831">apartment,</seg> on a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app114-f1831">cold,</seg> I had covered  <seg xml:id="C17_app116-f1831">myself</seg> with some  <seg xml:id="C17_app118-f1831">clothes;</seg> but these were  <seg xml:id="C17_app120-f1831">insufficient</seg> to secure me from the  <seg xml:id="C17_app122-f1831">dews of night. I was a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app123-f1831">poor, helpless,</seg> miserable  <seg xml:id="C17_app125-f1831">wretch; I knew,</seg> and could  <seg xml:id="C17_app127-f1831">distinguish, nothing;</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app128-f1831">but</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app129-f1831">feeling</seg> pain invade me on all   <seg xml:id="C17_app131-f1831">sides,</seg> I sat down and wept. </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3">
               <seg xml:id="C17_app133-f1831">“Soon</seg> a gentle light stole over the  <seg xml:id="C17_app135-f1831">heavens,</seg> and gave me a sensation of  <seg xml:id="C17_app137-f1831">pleasure.</seg> I started up, and beheld a radiant form rise  <seg xml:id="C17_app139-f1831">from among the trees.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app140-f1831">*<note xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p3_note1">* The moon.</note>
               </seg> I gazed with a kind of  <seg xml:id="C17_app142-f1831">wonder.</seg> It moved  <seg xml:id="C17_app144-f1831">slowly,</seg> but it enlightened my  <seg xml:id="C17_app146-f1831">path;</seg> and I again went out in search of berries. I was still  <seg xml:id="C17_app148-f1831">cold,</seg> when  <seg xml:id="C17_app150-f1831">under one of the trees I found a huge</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app151-f1831">cloak,</seg> with which  <seg xml:id="C17_app153-f1831">I</seg> covered myself, and sat down  <seg xml:id="C17_app155-f1831">upon</seg> the ground. No distinct ideas occupied my  <seg xml:id="C17_app157-f1831">mind;</seg> all was  <seg xml:id="C17_app159-f1831">confused.</seg> I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app161-f1831">light, and</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app162-f1831">hunger,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app164-f1831">thirst,</seg> and darkness; innumerable sounds rung in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app166-f1831">ears,</seg> and on all sides various scents saluted  <seg xml:id="C17_app168-f1831">me:</seg> the only object that I could distinguish was the  <seg xml:id="C17_app170-f1831">bright moon,</seg> and I fixed my eyes   <seg xml:id="C17_app173-f1831">on</seg> that with pleasure.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p4">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app175-f1831__F"> “Several</seg> changes of day and night  <seg xml:id="C17_app177-f1831">passed,</seg> and the orb of night had greatly  <seg xml:id="C17_app179-f1831">lessened,</seg> when I began to distinguish my sensations  <seg xml:id="C17_app181-f1831">from each</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app182-f1831">other.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app184-f1831">gradually saw plainly</seg> the clear stream that supplied me with   <seg xml:id="C17_app186-f1831">drink,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app188-f1831">trees that</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app189-f1831">shaded</seg> me with their foliage. I was delighted when I first discovered that a pleasant   <seg xml:id="C17_app191-f1831">sound,</seg> which often   <seg xml:id="C17_app194-f1831">saluted my</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app195-f1831">ears,</seg> proceeded from the throats of  <seg xml:id="C17_app197-f1831">the little</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app198-f1831">winged</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app199-f1831">animals</seg> who  <seg xml:id="C17_app201-f1831">had</seg> often intercepted the light from my eyes. I began also to  <seg xml:id="C17_app203-f1831">observe,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app205-f1831">greater</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app206-f1831">accuracy,</seg> the forms that surrounded  <seg xml:id="C17_app208-f1831">me,</seg> and to perceive the boundaries of the radiant  <seg xml:id="C17_app210-f1831">roof of</seg> light which  <seg xml:id="C17_app212-f1831">canopied</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app213-f1831">me. Sometimes</seg> I tried to imitate the pleasant songs of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app216-f1831">birds,</seg> but was  <seg xml:id="C17_app218-f1831">unable.</seg> Sometimes I  <seg xml:id="C17_app220-f1831">wished to express my sensations in my own</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app221-f1831">mode,</seg> but the uncouth and   <seg xml:id="C17_app224-f1831">inarticulate sounds</seg> which broke from me   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__I">frightened me into silence again. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p5">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app227-f1831__F">
               </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app228-f1831">“The</seg> moon had  <seg xml:id="C17_app230-f1831">disappeared</seg> from the night,  <seg xml:id="C17_app232-f1831">and again,</seg>
               <pb xml:id="F1831_v_104" n="88"/>with a lessened <seg xml:id="C17_app234-f1831">form,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app235-f1831">showed</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app236-f1831">itself,</seg> while I still remained in the forest. My  <seg xml:id="C17_app238-f1831">sensations</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app239-f1831">had,</seg> by this  <seg xml:id="C17_app241-f1831">time,</seg> become  <seg xml:id="C17_app243-f1831">distinct,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app245-f1831">my mind</seg> received every day   <seg xml:id="C17_app247-f1831">additional</seg> ideas. My eyes became accustomed to the   <seg xml:id="C17_app250-f1831">light,</seg> and to perceive objects in their right forms; I  <seg xml:id="C17_app252-f1831">distinguished</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app254-f1831">insect from the herb,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app255-f1831">and,</seg> by  <seg xml:id="C17_app257-f1831">degrees,</seg> one herb from  <seg xml:id="C17_app259-f1831">another.</seg> I found that the sparrow uttered none but harsh  <seg xml:id="C17_app261-f1831">notes,</seg> whilst  <seg xml:id="C17_app263-f1831">those of</seg> the blackbird   <seg xml:id="C17_app265-f1831">and thrush</seg> were sweet and enticing.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p6">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app267-f1831__F"> “One day,</seg> when I was oppressed by  <seg xml:id="C17_app269-f1831">cold,</seg> I found a fire  <seg xml:id="C17_app271-f1831">which</seg> had been left by some wandering  <seg xml:id="C17_app273-f1831">beggars,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app275-f1831">overcome</seg> with delight  <seg xml:id="C17_app277-f1831">at the warmth</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app278-f1831">I</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app279-f1831">experienced</seg> from it. In my joy I thrust my hand into the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app281-f1831">embers,</seg> but quickly drew it  <seg xml:id="C17_app283-f1831">out again</seg> with a cry  <seg xml:id="C17_app285-f1831">of</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app286-f1831">pain.</seg> How strange, I thought, that the same cause should  <seg xml:id="C17_app288-f1831">produce such</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app289-f1831">opposite</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app290-f1831">effects! I</seg> examined the materials of the fire, and to my joy found it to be  <seg xml:id="C17_app292-f1831">composed of wood.</seg> I quickly collected some  <seg xml:id="C17_app294-f1831">branches;</seg> but they were  <seg xml:id="C17_app296-f1831">wet,</seg> and would not burn. I was pained at  <seg xml:id="C17_app298-f1831">this,</seg> and sat still watching the  <seg xml:id="C17_app300-f1831">operation</seg> of the fire. The wet wood  <seg xml:id="C17_app302-f1831">which</seg> I had placed near the heat  <seg xml:id="C17_app304-f1831">dried,</seg> and itself   <seg xml:id="C17_app306-f1831">became</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app307-f1831">inflamed.</seg> I reflected on   <seg xml:id="C17_app309-f1831">this; and,</seg> by touching the various  <seg xml:id="C17_app311-f1831">branches,</seg> I discovered the  <seg xml:id="C17_app313-f1831">cause,</seg> and busied myself in  <seg xml:id="C17_app315-f1831">collecting</seg> a great  <seg xml:id="C17_app317-f1831">quantity</seg> of   <seg xml:id="C17_app319-f1831">wood,</seg> that I might dry  <seg xml:id="C17_app321-f1831">it,</seg> and have a  <seg xml:id="C17_app323-f1831">plentiful supply</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app324-f1831">of fire.</seg> When night came   <seg xml:id="C17_app326-f1831">on,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app328-f1831">brought sleep with it ,</seg> I was in the greatest fear lest my fire should be  <seg xml:id="C17_app330-f1831">extinguished.</seg> I covered it carefully with  <seg xml:id="C17_app332-f1831">dry wood and</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app333-f1831">leaves,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app335-f1831">placed</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app336-f1831">wet branches</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app337-f1831">upon it;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app339-f1831">then,</seg> spreading my  <seg xml:id="C17_app341-f1831">cloak,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app343-f1831">lay</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app345-f1831">ground,</seg> and sunk into sleep.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p7">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app347-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was morning when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app349-f1831">awoke,</seg> and my first care was to visit the  <seg xml:id="C17_app351-f1831">fire. I</seg> uncovered  <seg xml:id="C17_app353-f1831">it,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app355-f1831">a gentle breeze quickly fanned it into a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app356-f1831">flame.</seg> I observed this  <seg xml:id="C17_app358-f1831">also,</seg> and contrived a fan of  <seg xml:id="C17_app360-f1831">branches,</seg> which roused the embers when  <seg xml:id="C17_app362-f1831">they</seg> were nearly extinguished. When night  <seg xml:id="C17_app364-f1831">came</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app365-f1831">again,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app367-f1831">found,</seg> with  <seg xml:id="C17_app369-f1831">pleasure,</seg> that the fire gave light as well as  <seg xml:id="C17_app371-f1831">heat;</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app373-f1831">that</seg> the discovery of this element was useful to me  <seg xml:id="C17_app375-f1831">in my</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app376-f1831">food;</seg> for I found some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app378-f1831">the</seg> offals that the travellers had left had been  <seg xml:id="C17_app380-f1831">roasted,</seg> and tasted much more savoury than the berries I  <seg xml:id="C17_app382-f1831">gathered from the trees.</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app384-f1831">tried, therefore,</seg> to dress my food in the same manner, placing  <seg xml:id="C17_app386-f1831">it</seg> on the live  <seg xml:id="C17_app388-f1831">embers.</seg> I found that the berries <pb xml:id="F1831_v_105" n="89"/>were spoiled by this <seg xml:id="C17_app390-f1831">operation,</seg> and the nuts  <seg xml:id="C17_app392-f1831">and roots</seg> much improved.  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p8">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app394-f1831__F"> “Food, however,</seg> became  <seg xml:id="C17_app396-f1831">scarce;</seg> and I often spent  <seg xml:id="C17_app398-f1831">the whole</seg> day searching in vain for a few acorns to assuage the pangs of hunger. When I found  <seg xml:id="C17_app400-f1831">this, I</seg> resolved to quit the place  <seg xml:id="C17_app402-f1831">that</seg> I had hitherto  <seg xml:id="C17_app404-f1831">inhabited,</seg> to seek for  <seg xml:id="C17_app406-f1831">one</seg> where the few wants I experienced would be more easily satisfied. In this   <seg xml:id="C17_app408-f1831">emigration,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app410-f1831">exceedingly</seg> lamented the loss of   <seg xml:id="C17_app412-f1831">the fire which I</seg> had obtained  <seg xml:id="C17_app414-f1831">through accident,</seg> and knew not how to  <seg xml:id="C17_app416-f1831">reproduce</seg> it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app418-f1831">I gave several hours to the</seg> serious consideration  <seg xml:id="C17_app420-f1831">of this difficulty;</seg> but I was obliged to  <seg xml:id="C17_app422-f1831">relinquish all</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app423-f1831">attempt</seg> to supply  <seg xml:id="C17_app425-f1831">it; and, wrapping</seg> myself up in my  <seg xml:id="C17_app427-f1831">cloak,</seg> I struck across the wood towards the setting  <seg xml:id="C17_app429-f1831">sun.</seg> I passed three days in these  <seg xml:id="C17_app431-f1831">rambles,</seg> and at length discovered the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app433-f1831">country.</seg> A great fall of snow had taken place the night  <seg xml:id="C17_app435-f1831">before,</seg> and the fields were of one  <seg xml:id="C17_app437-f1831">uniform white;</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app439-f1831">appearance</seg> was  <seg xml:id="C17_app441-f1831">disconsolate,</seg> and I found my feet chilled by the cold  <seg xml:id="C17_app443-f1831">damp</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app444-f1831">substance that covered the</seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__I">ground. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p9">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app445-f1831__F"> “It</seg> was about seven in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app447-f1831">morning,</seg> and I longed to obtain food and  <seg xml:id="C17_app449-f1831">shelter;</seg> at length I perceived  <seg xml:id="C17_app451-f1831">a small</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app452-f1831">hut, on a rising ground,</seg> which had  <seg xml:id="C17_app454-f1831">doubtless been built for the convenience of</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app455-f1831">some</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app456-f1831">shepherd.</seg> This was a new sight to  <seg xml:id="C17_app458-f1831">me;</seg> and I examined the  <seg xml:id="C17_app460-f1831">structure</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app461-f1831">with great curiosity.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app462-f1831">Finding the door</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app463-f1831">open,</seg> I entered. An old man sat  <seg xml:id="C17_app465-f1831">in it, near a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app466-f1831">fire,</seg> over  <seg xml:id="C17_app468-f1831">which he was preparing his</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app469-f1831">breakfast.</seg> He turned  <seg xml:id="C17_app471-f1831">on hearing a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app472-f1831">noise; and,</seg> perceiving  <seg xml:id="C17_app474-f1831">me,</seg> shrieked  <seg xml:id="C17_app476-f1831">loudly, and, quitting</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app478-f1831">hut,</seg> ran across the fields with a speed  <seg xml:id="C17_app480-f1831">of which his debilitated form hardly appeared</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app481-f1831">capable. His appearance, different from any I had ever before seen, and</seg> his  <seg xml:id="C17_app483-f1831">flight,</seg> somewhat surprised  <seg xml:id="C17_app485-f1831">me.</seg> But I was  <seg xml:id="C17_app487-f1831">enchanted by</seg> the appearance of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app489-f1831">hut:</seg> here the snow and rain could not  <seg xml:id="C17_app491-f1831">penetrate;</seg> the ground was  <seg xml:id="C17_app493-f1831">dry;</seg> and it  <seg xml:id="C17_app495-f1831">presented</seg> to me then as   <seg xml:id="C17_app497-f1831">exquisite</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app498-f1831">and divine</seg> a retreat as  <seg xml:id="C17_app500-f1831">Pandæmonium</seg> appeared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app502-f1831">dæmons</seg> of hell  <seg xml:id="C17_app504-f1831">after</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app505-f1831">their sufferings</seg> in the lake of fire. I greedily devoured the   <seg xml:id="C17_app508-f1831">remnants</seg> of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app510-f1831">shepherd’s breakfast,</seg> which consisted of bread, cheese,  <seg xml:id="C17_app512-f1831">milk,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app514-f1831">wine; the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app515-f1831">latter, however,</seg> I did not like.  <seg xml:id="C17_app517-f1831">Then,</seg> overcome by  <seg xml:id="C17_app519-f1831">fatigue,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app520-f1831">I lay</seg> down among some  <seg xml:id="C17_app522-f1831">straw,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app523-f1831">and</seg> fell asleep. </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p10">
               <seg xml:id="C17_app525-f1831">“It</seg> was noon when I  <seg xml:id="C17_app527-f1831">awoke; and,</seg> allured by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app529-f1831">
                  <pb xml:id="F1831_v_106" n="90"/>warmth of</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app530-f1831">the sun, which shone brightly on the white ground,</seg> I determined to recommence my  <seg xml:id="C17_app532-f1831">travels; and,</seg> depositing the   <seg xml:id="C17_app535-f1831">remains</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app537-f1831">peasant’s</seg> breakfast in a wallet I found, I proceeded across the fields for several hours,  <seg xml:id="C17_app539-f1831">until</seg> at sunset I  <seg xml:id="C17_app541-f1831">arrived at</seg> a village. How miraculous did this   <seg xml:id="C17_app543-f1831">appear!</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app545-f1831">huts,</seg> the neater  <seg xml:id="C17_app547-f1831">cottages,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app549-f1831">stately houses,</seg> engaged my admiration by  <seg xml:id="C17_app551-f1831">turns.</seg> The vegetables in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app553-f1831">gardens,</seg> the milk and cheese that I saw placed at  <seg xml:id="C17_app555-f1831">the windows of some of the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app556-f1831">cottages,</seg> allured  <seg xml:id="C17_app558-f1831">my appetite.</seg> One of the best of these I  <seg xml:id="C17_app560-f1831">entered;</seg> but I had hardly placed my foot  <seg xml:id="C17_app562-f1831">within</seg> the   <seg xml:id="C17_app564-f1831">door,</seg> before the children  <seg xml:id="C17_app566-f1831">shrieked,</seg> and one of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app568-f1831">women</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app569-f1831">fainted.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app571-f1831">whole</seg> village was  <seg xml:id="C17_app573-f1831">roused;</seg> some  <seg xml:id="C17_app575-f1831">fled, some</seg> attacked  <seg xml:id="C17_app577-f1831">me, until,</seg> grievously bruised by  <seg xml:id="C17_app579-f1831">stones</seg> and   <seg xml:id="C17_app581-f1831">many other kinds of missile</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app582-f1831">weapons,</seg> I escaped to the open  <seg xml:id="C17_app584-f1831">country,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app585-f1831">and</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app586-f1831">fearfully</seg> took refuge in a low  <seg xml:id="C17_app588-f1831">hovel, quite bare,</seg> and making a wretched appearance after the  <seg xml:id="C17_app590-f1831">palaces</seg> I had beheld in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app592-f1831">village.</seg> This  <seg xml:id="C17_app594-f1831">hovel, however, joined</seg> a cottage of a neat and pleasant  <seg xml:id="C17_app596-f1831">appearance; but,</seg> after my late  <seg xml:id="C17_app599-f1831">dearly</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app600-f1831">bought </seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app601-f1831">experience,</seg> I dared not enter it. My place of refuge  <seg xml:id="C17_app603-f1831">was constructed of wood,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app604-f1831">but</seg> so   <seg xml:id="C17_app606-f1831">low,</seg> that I could with difficulty sit upright in it.  <seg xml:id="C17_app608-f1831">No</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app609-f1831">wood, however,</seg> was placed on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app611-f1831">earth,</seg> which formed  <seg xml:id="C17_app613-f1831">the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app614-f1831">floor,</seg> but it was  <seg xml:id="C17_app616-f1831">dry;</seg> and although the wind entered  <seg xml:id="C17_app618-f1831">it</seg> by innumerable  <seg xml:id="C17_app620-f1831">chinks,</seg> I found it an  <seg xml:id="C17_app622-f1831">agreeable asylum</seg> from the snow  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__I">and rain. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p11">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app624-f1831__F"> “Here then I retreated, and lay</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app625-f1831">down</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app626-f1831">happy to have found a shelter, however miserable, from the inclemency of the season,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app628-f1831">still more from the barbarity of man.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p12">
               <seg xml:id="C17_app630-f1831">“As</seg> soon as morning  <seg xml:id="C17_app632-f1831">dawned,</seg> I crept from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app634-f1831">kennel,</seg> that I might view the adjacent  <seg xml:id="C17_app636-f1831">cottage,</seg> and discover if I could remain in the  <seg xml:id="C17_app638-f1831">habitation</seg> I had found. It was situated  <seg xml:id="C17_app640-f1831">against</seg> the back of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app642-f1831">cottage,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app644-f1831">surrounded</seg> on   <seg xml:id="C17_app646-f1831">the</seg> sides which were exposed by a   <seg xml:id="C17_app648-f1831">pig-sty</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app650-f1831">a clear</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app651-f1831">pool</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app653-f1831">water.</seg> One part was  <seg xml:id="C17_app655-f1831">open,</seg> and by that I had crept  <seg xml:id="C17_app657-f1831">in;</seg> but now  <seg xml:id="C17_app659-f1831">I</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app660-f1831">covered</seg> every crevice  <seg xml:id="C17_app662-f1831">by which I might be</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app663-f1831">perceived with stones and wood,</seg> yet in such a manner that I  <seg xml:id="C17_app665-f1831">might</seg> move  <seg xml:id="C17_app667-f1831">them</seg> on  <seg xml:id="C17_app669-f1831">occasion to pass</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app670-f1831">out:</seg> all the light I enjoyed came through the  <seg xml:id="C17_app672-f1831">sty,</seg> and that was  <seg xml:id="C17_app674-f1831">sufficient</seg> for me. </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p13">
               <seg xml:id="C17_app676-f1831">“Having</seg> thus arranged my  <seg xml:id="C17_app678-f1831">dwelling, and</seg> carpeted it with clean straw, I  <seg xml:id="C17_app680-f1831">retired;</seg> for I saw the figure of a man  <seg xml:id="C17_app682-f1831">
                  <pb xml:id="F1831_v_107" n="91"/>at</seg> a   <seg xml:id="C17_app684-f1831">distance,</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app686-f1831">remembered</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app687-f1831">too well my treatment the night</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app688-f1831">before,</seg> to trust myself in his power. I had  <seg xml:id="C17_app690-f1831">first, however,</seg> provided for my sustenance for that  <seg xml:id="C17_app692-f1831">day,</seg> by a loaf of  <seg xml:id="C17_app694-f1831">coarse</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app695-f1831">bread,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app697-f1831">purloined,</seg> and a cup  <seg xml:id="C17_app699-f1831">with</seg> which I could   <seg xml:id="C17_app701-f1831">drink,</seg> more conveniently than from my  <seg xml:id="C17_app703-f1831">hand,</seg> of the pure water which  flowed by my   <seg xml:id="C17_app707-f1831">retreat. The floor</seg> was a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app709-f1831">raised,</seg> so that it was kept   <seg xml:id="C17_app712-f1831">perfectly</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app713-f1831">dry,</seg> and by its vicinity to the chimney  <seg xml:id="C17_app715-f1831">of the cottage it was tolerably warm.</seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p14">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app716-f1831__F"> “Being</seg> thus  <seg xml:id="C17_app718-f1831">provided,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app720-f1831">resolved</seg> to reside in this  <seg xml:id="C17_app722-f1831">hovel, until</seg> something should occur which might alter my determination. It was indeed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app724-f1831">paradise,</seg> compared to the  <seg xml:id="C17_app726-f1831">bleak</seg> forest, my former residence,  <seg xml:id="C17_app728-f1831">the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app729-f1831">rain-dropping branches,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app731-f1831">dank</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app732-f1831">earth.</seg> I ate my breakfast with  <seg xml:id="C17_app734-f1831">pleasure,</seg> and was about to remove a plank to procure myself a little  <seg xml:id="C17_app736-f1831">water,</seg> when I heard a  <seg xml:id="C17_app738-f1831">step,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app739-f1831">and</seg> looking through a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app741-f1831">chink, I</seg> beheld a young  <seg xml:id="C17_app743-f1831">creature,</seg> with a pail on her  <seg xml:id="C17_app745-f1831">head,</seg> passing before my hovel. The girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app747-f1831">young,</seg> and of gentle  <seg xml:id="C17_app749-f1831">demeanour,</seg> unlike what I have since found cottagers and  <seg xml:id="C17_app751-f1831">farm-house</seg> servants to  <seg xml:id="C17_app753-f1831">be.</seg> Yet she was  <seg xml:id="C17_app755-f1831">meanly dressed,</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app757-f1831">coarse</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app758-f1831">blue</seg> petticoat and a linen jacket being her only   <seg xml:id="C17_app760-f1831">garb;</seg> her fair hair was  <seg xml:id="C17_app762-f1831">plaited,</seg> but not adorned; she looked  <seg xml:id="C17_app764-f1831">patient,</seg> yet sad.  <seg xml:id="C17_app766-f1831">I lost sight of her; and</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app768-f1831">about</seg> a quarter of an hour  <seg xml:id="C17_app770-f1831">she</seg> returned,  <seg xml:id="C17_app772-f1831">bearing the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app773-f1831">pail,</seg> which was now partly filled with milk. As she walked  <seg xml:id="C17_app775-f1831">along,</seg> seemingly incommoded by the  <seg xml:id="C17_app777-f1831">burden,</seg> a young man met  <seg xml:id="C17_app779-f1831">her,</seg> whose countenance expressed a deeper  <seg xml:id="C17_app781-f1831">despondence.</seg> Uttering a few  <seg xml:id="C17_app783-f1831">sounds</seg> with   <seg xml:id="C17_app785-f1831">an air of</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app786-f1831">melancholy,</seg> he took the pail from her  <seg xml:id="C17_app788-f1831">head,</seg> and bore it  <seg xml:id="C17_app790-f1831">to</seg> the cottage himself. She  <seg xml:id="C17_app792-f1831">followed,</seg> and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app794-f1831">disappeared.</seg> Presently I saw the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app796-f1831">again,</seg> with some tools in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app798-f1831">hand,</seg> cross the field  <seg xml:id="C17_app800-f1831">behind</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app802-f1831">cottage;</seg> and the girl was also  <seg xml:id="C17_app804-f1831">busied, sometimes</seg> in  <seg xml:id="C17_app806-f1831">the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app807-f1831">house,</seg> and sometimes in the  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__I">yard. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p15">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app809-f1831__F"> “On examining</seg> my  <seg xml:id="C17_app811-f1831">dwelling,</seg> I  <seg xml:id="C17_app813-f1831">found</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app815-f1831">one of the windows</seg> of the cottage  <seg xml:id="C17_app817-f1831">had formerly occupied a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app818-f1831">part</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app820-f1831">it,</seg> but the panes had  <seg xml:id="C17_app822-f1831">been filled up with wood. In one of these was a small and</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app823-f1831">almost</seg> imperceptible  <seg xml:id="C17_app825-f1831">chink, through which</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app826-f1831">the eye could just</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app827-f1831">penetrate. Through</seg> this  <seg xml:id="C17_app829-f1831">crevice</seg> a small room was visible,  <seg xml:id="C17_app831-f1831">whitewashed</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app832-f1831">and</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app833-f1831">clean,</seg> but very bare of  <seg xml:id="C17_app835-f1831">furniture.</seg> In  <seg xml:id="C17_app837-f1831">one</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app838-f1831">corner,</seg> near a small  <seg xml:id="C17_app840-f1831">fire, sat</seg> an old  <seg xml:id="C17_app842-f1831">man,</seg> leaning his head on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app844-f1831">hands</seg> in a  <seg xml:id="C17_app846-f1831">disconsolate <pb xml:id="F1831_v_108" n="92"/>attitude.</seg> The young girl was  <seg xml:id="C17_app848-f1831">occupied in arranging the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app849-f1831">cottage;</seg> but presently  <seg xml:id="C17_app851-f1831">she took</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app852-f1831">something</seg> out of  <seg xml:id="C17_app854-f1831">a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app855-f1831">drawer,</seg> which employed her  <seg xml:id="C17_app857-f1831">hands,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app859-f1831">she</seg> sat down beside  <seg xml:id="C17_app861-f1831">the old</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app862-f1831">man, who,</seg> taking up an  <seg xml:id="C17_app864-f1831">instrument,</seg> began to  <seg xml:id="C17_app866-f1831">play,</seg> and to produce  <seg xml:id="C17_app868-f1831">sounds</seg> sweeter than the voice of the thrush or  <seg xml:id="C17_app870-f1831">the</seg> nightingale.  <seg xml:id="C17_app872-f1831">It was a lovely</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app873-f1831">sight,</seg> even to  <seg xml:id="C17_app875-f1831">me,</seg> poor  <seg xml:id="C17_app877-f1831">wretch!</seg> who had never beheld aught beautiful before.  <seg xml:id="C17_app879-f1831">The</seg> silver   <seg xml:id="C17_app881-f1831">hair and</seg> benevolent countenance  <seg xml:id="C17_app883-f1831">of</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app884-f1831">the</seg> aged  <seg xml:id="C17_app886-f1831">cottager</seg> won my  <seg xml:id="C17_app888-f1831">reverence,</seg> while  <seg xml:id="C17_app890-f1831">the</seg> gentle manners of the girl enticed my love. He played a sweet mournful   <seg xml:id="C17_app892-f1831">air,</seg> which I  <seg xml:id="C17_app894-f1831">perceived</seg> drew tears from the eyes of  <seg xml:id="C17_app896-f1831">his</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app897-f1831">amiable</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app898-f1831">companion,</seg> of which the old man took  <seg xml:id="C17_app900-f1831">no</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app901-f1831">notice, until</seg> she sobbed  <seg xml:id="C17_app903-f1831">audibly;</seg> he  <seg xml:id="C17_app905-f1831">then pronounced a few</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app906-f1831">sounds,</seg> and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app908-f1831">fair creature,</seg> leaving her  <seg xml:id="C17_app910-f1831">work,</seg> knelt at his  <seg xml:id="C17_app912-f1831">feet.</seg> He  <seg xml:id="C17_app914-f1831">raised her,</seg> and smiled with such  <seg xml:id="C17_app916-f1831">kindness</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app917-f1831">and affection,</seg> that I felt  <seg xml:id="C17_app919-f1831">sensations of a peculiar and overpowering nature:</seg> they were a  <seg xml:id="C17_app921-f1831">mixture of pain and</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app922-f1831">pleasure,</seg> such as I had never  <seg xml:id="C17_app924-f1831">before experienced,</seg> either from  <seg xml:id="C17_app926-f1831">hunger or cold,</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app927-f1831">warmth or</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app928-f1831">food;</seg> and I  <seg xml:id="C17_app930-f1831">withdrew</seg> from  <seg xml:id="C17_app932-f1831">the window,</seg> unable  <seg xml:id="C17_app934-f1831">to bear</seg> these  <seg xml:id="C17_app936-f1831">emotions.</seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p16">
               <seg xml:id="C17_app938-f1831">“Soon</seg> after this the young man  <seg xml:id="C17_app940-f1831">returned,</seg> bearing on his  <seg xml:id="C17_app942-f1831">shoulders</seg> a  <seg xml:id="C17_app944-f1831">load of</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app945-f1831">wood.</seg> The  <seg xml:id="C17_app947-f1831">girl met him at the</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app948-f1831">door,</seg> helped to relieve him of his  <seg xml:id="C17_app950-f1831">burden, and,</seg> taking some of  <seg xml:id="C17_app952-f1831">the fuel</seg> into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app954-f1831">cottage,</seg> placed it on the fire;  <seg xml:id="C17_app956-f1831">then she and the youth went apart into a</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app957-f1831">nook</seg> of the   <seg xml:id="C17_app959-f1831">cottage,</seg> and he  <seg xml:id="C17_app961-f1831">showed</seg> her a large loaf and a piece of  <seg xml:id="C17_app963-f1831">cheese.</seg> She seemed  <seg xml:id="C17_app965-f1831">pleased,</seg> and went into the garden for  <seg xml:id="C17_app967-f1831">some</seg> roots and  <seg xml:id="C17_app969-f1831">plants,</seg> which she placed in  <seg xml:id="C17_app971-f1831">water,</seg> and then upon the  <seg xml:id="C17_app973-f1831">fire.</seg> She  <seg xml:id="C17_app975-f1831">afterwards</seg> continued her   <seg xml:id="C17_app977-f1831">work,</seg> whilst the young man went into the  <seg xml:id="C17_app979-f1831">garden,</seg> and appeared busily employed in digging and  <seg xml:id="C17_app981-f1831">pulling up</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app982-f1831">roots. After</seg> he had been employed thus about  <seg xml:id="C17_app984-f1831">an</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app985-f1831">hour,</seg> the young woman joined him, and they  <seg xml:id="C17_app987-f1831">entered</seg> the cottage  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__I">together. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p17">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app989-f1831__F"> “The</seg> old man  <seg xml:id="C17_app991-f1831">had,</seg> in the mean  <seg xml:id="C17_app993-f1831">time,</seg> been  <seg xml:id="C17_app995-f1831">pensive; but,</seg> on the  <seg xml:id="C17_app997-f1831">appearance</seg> of  <seg xml:id="C17_app999-f1831">his</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1000-f1831">companions,</seg> he assumed a  <seg xml:id="C17_app1002-f1831">more</seg> cheerful air, and they sat down to eat.   <seg xml:id="C17_app1004-f1831">The</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1005-f1831">meal</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1006-f1831">was quickly</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1007-f1831">despatched.</seg> The young woman was again occupied in arranging the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1009-f1831">cottage;</seg> the old man walked before the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1011-f1831">cottage</seg> in the sun for a few   <seg xml:id="C17_app1014-f1831">minutes,</seg> leaning on the arm of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1016-f1831">youth.</seg> Nothing could exceed in beauty the contrast <pb xml:id="F1831_v_109" n="93"/>between these two <seg xml:id="C17_app1018-f1831">excellent</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1019-f1831">creatures.</seg> One was old, with silver hairs and a countenance beaming with  <seg xml:id="C17_app1021-f1831">benevolence</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1023-f1831">love:</seg> the younger was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1025-f1831">slight</seg> and graceful in his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1027-f1831">figure,</seg> and his  <seg xml:id="C17_app1029-f1831">features</seg> were moulded with the finest  <seg xml:id="C17_app1031-f1831">symmetry;</seg> yet his eyes and attitude expressed the utmost sadness and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1033-f1831">despondency.</seg> The old man returned to the cottage; and the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1035-f1831">youth,</seg> with tools different from those  <seg xml:id="C17_app1037-f1831">he had used in the morning, directed his steps across the</seg>
               <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__I">fields. </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p18">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1038-f1831__F"> “Night</seg> quickly shut  <seg xml:id="C17_app1040-f1831">in; but,</seg> to my extreme  <seg xml:id="C17_app1042-f1831">wonder,</seg> I found that the cottagers had a means of prolonging  <seg xml:id="C17_app1044-f1831">light</seg> by the use of  <seg xml:id="C17_app1046-f1831">tapers,</seg> and was  <seg xml:id="C17_app1048-f1831">delighted</seg> to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1050-f1831">find</seg> that  <seg xml:id="C17_app1052-f1831">the</seg> setting of the sun did not put an end  <seg xml:id="C17_app1054-f1831">to the pleasure I experienced in watching</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1055-f1831">my human</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1056-f1831">neighbours. In</seg> the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1058-f1831">evening,</seg> the young girl and her companion were employed in various  <seg xml:id="C17_app1060-f1831">occupations</seg> which I did not   <seg xml:id="C17_app1063-f1831">understand;</seg> and the old man again took  <seg xml:id="C17_app1065-f1831">up the instrument</seg> which produced  <seg xml:id="C17_app1067-f1831">the</seg> divine sounds that had enchanted me in the morning.  <seg xml:id="C17_app1069-f1831">So soon as</seg> he had   <seg xml:id="C17_app1071-f1831">finished,</seg> the youth  <seg xml:id="C17_app1073-f1831">began,</seg> not to  <seg xml:id="C17_app1075-f1831">play,</seg> but  <seg xml:id="C17_app1077-f1831">to</seg> utter   <seg xml:id="C17_app1079-f1831">sounds</seg>
               <seg xml:id="C17_app1080-f1831">that</seg> were  <seg xml:id="C17_app1082-f1831">monotonous,</seg> and  <seg xml:id="C17_app1084-f1831">neither resembling</seg> the harmony of the old   <seg xml:id="C17_app1086-f1831">man’s</seg> instrument  <seg xml:id="C17_app1088-f1831">nor</seg> the songs of the  <seg xml:id="C17_app1090-f1831">birds:</seg> I since found that he read  <seg xml:id="C17_app1092-f1831">aloud,</seg> but at that time I knew nothing of the science of words or letters.   <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__I">
               </seg>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="novel1_letter4_chapter11_div4_div11_p19">
               <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1096-f1831__F"> “The family, after having been thus occupied for a short time,</seg> extinguished their  <seg xml:id="C17_app1098-f1831">lights,</seg> and retired, as I conjectured, to  <seg part="I" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__I">rest. </seg>
            </p>
            <seg part="F" xml:id="C17_app1100-f1831__F">
            </seg>
            <seg xml:id="C17_app1101-f1831">
               <milestone unit="chapter" type="end" n="11"/>
            </seg>
         </div>
         <seg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="C17_app2-f1831">
            <anchor type="collate" xml:id="C17"/>
         </seg>
         <anchor xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="collate" xml:id="C17"/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
